<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin><![CDATA[Razuvaev, V. N.]]></origin>
        <origin><![CDATA[Apasova, E. B.]]></origin>
        <origin><![CDATA[Martuganov, R. A.]]></origin>
        <title><![CDATA[Six- and Three-Hourly Meteorological Observations from 223 U.S.S.R. Stations]]></title>
        <geoform></geoform>
        <onlink><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/]]></onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract><![CDATA[Six- and Three-Hourly Meteorological Observations from 223 U.S.S.R. Stations]]></abstract>
      <supplinf></supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate><![CDATA[18910101]]></begdate>
          <enddate><![CDATA[19901231]]></enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress></progress>
      <update> As appropriate</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc><![CDATA[20.620]]></westbc>
        <eastbc><![CDATA[-173.230]]></eastbc>
        <northbc><![CDATA[73.500]]></northbc>
        <southbc><![CDATA[35.280]]></southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>CDIAC</themekt>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Russia]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[U.S.S.R.]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Air Temperature]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Atmospheric Phenomena]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Cloud Amount]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Cloud Height]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Dew Point Temperature]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Former Soviet Union]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Hourly Data]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Precipitation Amount]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Relative Humidity]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Sea Level Pressure]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Soil Temperature]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Visibility]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Water Vapor Pressure]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Weather Type]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Wind Direction]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Wind Speed]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[NDP-048]]></themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Thematic Area</themekt>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Place Keywords</placekt>
        <placekey></placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Dale Kaiser; email: kaiserdp@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntfax></cntfax>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg></cntorg>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Dale Kaiser; email: kaiserdp@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice></cntvoice>
        <cntfax></cntfax>
        <cntemail></cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc></resdesc>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/]]></computer>
            <accinstr></accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20120918 124123</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Dale Kaiser; email: kaiserdp@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice></cntvoice>
        <cntemail></cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  </metainfo>
  <Local-Control-Number>Created 20050809 143555 by 160.91.18.40</Local-Control-Number>
  <mercury>
    <begdate></begdate>
    <enddate></enddate>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Russia]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[U.S.S.R.]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Air Temperature]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Atmospheric Phenomena]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Cloud Amount]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Cloud Height]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Dew Point Temperature]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Former Soviet Union]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Hourly Data]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Precipitation Amount]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Relative Humidity]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Sea Level Pressure]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Soil Temperature]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Visibility]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Water Vapor Pressure]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Weather Type]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Wind Direction]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Wind Speed]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[NDP-048]]></Keywords>
    <Documentation_Link>
      <Text><![CDATA[&#239;&#187;&#191;
Contributed by
V. N. Razuvaev, E. B. Apasova, R. A. Martuganov
All-Russian Research Institute
of Hydrometeorological Information-World Data Centre
Prepared by
D. P. Kaiser and G. P. Marino
)
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
Oak Ridge National Laboratory
Prepared for the
Climate Change Research Division
Office of Biological and Environmental Research
U.S. Department of Energy
Prepared by the
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
OAK RIDGE NATIONAL LABORATORY
Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831-6290
managed by
University of Tennessee-Battelle, LLC
for the
U.S. DEPARTMENT OF ENERGY
V. N. Razuvaev, E. B. Apasova, R. A. Martuganov
All-Russian Research Institute
of Hydrometeorological Information-World Data Centre
Fortran and SAS Data Retrieval Programs (.for and .sas files) - These files are provided for the benefit of users with FORTRAN or SAS on their systems, enabling them to read any of the data files in this database using these software packages. The program files are:
 Variable Variable Starting Ending
 Variable type width column column
 SEQNUM Numeric 3 1 3
 WMO Numeric 5 5 9
 NAME Character 25 11 35
 LAT Numeric 5 37 41
 LON Numeric 7 43 49
 ELEV Numeric 6 51 56
 BMONTH Numeric 2 61 62
 BYEAR Numeric 4 64 67
 EMONTH Numeric 2 69 70
 EYEAR Numeric 4 72 75
 where
 SEQNUM is the sequence number of the station in the data base (1-223);
 WMO is the WMO No. of the station;
 NAME is the name of the station;
 LAT is the latitude of the station in decimal degrees north;
 LON is the longitude of the station in decimal degrees east;
 ELEV is the elevation of the station above sea level (meters) missing elevations
 are coded as -999.9;
 BMONTH is the beginning month of the station's period of record;
 BYEAR is the beginning year of the station's period of record;
 EMONTH is the ending month of the station's period of record; and
 EYEAR is the ending year of the station's period of record.
24966 - October 1, 1981
25551 - January 1, 1982
27648 - January 1, 1970
27947 - April 1, 1981
34123 - April 1, 1981
 Variable Variable Starting Ending
 Variable type width column column
 WMO Numeric 5 1 5
 TYPE Character 4 7 10
 YEAR Numeric 4 12 15
 MONTH Numeric 2 17 18
 DAY Numeric 2 20 21
 DIST Character 2 23 24
 DIRECT Character 3 26 28
 where
 WMO is the WMO No. of the station;
 TYPE is the type of change indicated by this entry. The possible values of TYPE
 are as follows:
 RAIN = rain gauge replacement (i.e., change from old-type gauge
 to Tretyakov-type gauge). Each station will have only one
 RAIN entry. When this type of entry is used, DIST and
 DIRECT (described below) are not relevant and thus are
 coded as blanks;
 MOVE = station relocation. Each station will have at least one
 MOVE entry. If a station moved on more than one
 occasion, then separate entries are included for each
 relocation. If a station never moved, then that station will
 have only one MOVE entry; in this entry, YEAR,
 MONTH, DAY, DIST, and DIRECT (described below) are
 all coded as missing. In other words, if a station has only
 one MOVE entry, and if all variables in that MOVE entry
 are coded as missing, then the given station never moved;
 YEAR is the year in which the change took place. Missing years are coded as
 999;
 MONTH is the month in which the change took place. Missing months are coded
 as 9;
 DAY is the day on which the change took place. Missing days are coded as 9;
 DIST is the distance (km) that the station was moved. Missing distances are
 coded as 9. A distance of zero indicates that the station moved less than 1
 km. DIST only applies to station relocation entries (i.e., lines in which
 TYPE = MOVE). In rain gauge replacement entries (i.e., lines in which
 TYPE = RAIN), DIST is not relevant and thus is coded as blanks; and
 DIRECT is the direction in which the station was moved (e.g., N = north, SE =
 southeast). Missing directions are coded as 99. DIRECT only applies to
 station relocation entries (i.e., lines in which TYPE = MOVE). In rain
 gauge replacement entries (i.e., lines in which TYPE = RAIN), DIRECT is
 not relevant and thus is coded as blanks.
 Variable Starting Ending
 Variable width column column
 WMO 5 1 5
 YEAR 4 6 9
 MONTH 2 10 11
 DAY 2 12 13
 HOUR 2 14 15
 RH 3 16 18
 RHQF 1 19 19
 VAPORP 3 20 22
 VAPQF 1 23 23
 SLP 5 24 28
 SLPQF 1 29 29
 HDEF 3 30 32
 HDEFQF 1 33 33
 PCHR 1 34 34
 PCHRQF 1 35 35
 PTND 3 36 38
 PTNDQF 1 39 39
 VIS 2 40 41
 VISCF 1 42 42
 VISQF 1 43 43
 HCLD 2 44 45
 HCLDCF 1 46 46
 HCLDQF 1 47 47
 TDEW 3 48 50
 TDEWQF 1 51 51
 GRND 1 52 52
 GRNDQF 1 53 53
 TCLD 2 54 55
 TCLDCF 1 56 56
 TCLDQF 1 57 57
 LCLD 2 58 59
 LCLDCF 1 60 60
 LCLDQF 1 61 61
 WDIR 2 62 63
 WDIRQF 1 64 64
 WSPD 2 65 66
 WSPDQF 1 67 67
 PRCP 4 68 71
 PRCPCF 1 72 72
 PRCPQF 1 73 73
 STAP 5 74 78
 STAPQF 1 79 79
 SOILT 3 80 82
 SOILQF 1 83 83
 W 1 84 84
 WCF 1 85 85
 WQF 1 86 86
 WW 2 87 88
 WWQF 1 89 89
 AIRT 4 90 93
 AIRTQF 1 94 94
 APH1 1 95 95
 APH1CF 1 96 96
 APH1QF 1 97 97
 APH2 1 98 98
 APH2CF 1 99 99
 APH2QF 1 100 100
 APH3 1 101 101
 APH3CF 1 102 102
 APH3QF 1 103 103
 APH4 1 104 104
 APH4CF 1 105 105
 APH4QF 1 106 106
 APH5 1 107 107
 APH5CF 1 108 108
 APH5QF 1 109 109
 APH6 1 110 110
 APH6CF 1 111 111
 APH6QF 1 112 112
 APH7 1 113 113
 APH7CF 1 114 114
 APH7QF 1 115 115
 CLDH 1 116 116
 CLDHCF 1 117 117
 CLDHQF 1 118 118
 CLDM 1 119 119
 CLDMQF 1 120 120
 CLDL1 1 121 121
 CLDL1F 1 122 122
 CLDL2 1 123 123
 CLDL2F 1 124 124
 CLDL3 1 125 125
 CLDL3F 1 126 126
 WIR 1 127 127
 WIRF 1 128 128
 where
 WMO is the WMO number of the station;
 YEAR is the year (Greenwich) of the observations in the record;
 MONTH is the month (Greenwich) of the observations in the record;
 DAY is the day (Greenwich) of the observations in the record;
 HOUR is the GMT of the observations in the record;
 RH is the relative humidity of the air (expressed in percent) as determined by
 use of a psychrometer. Relative humidity is defined as the ratio of the
 observed vapor pressure to the saturation vapor pressure for the observed
 air temperature. Values of observations may range from 0 to 100%.
 Missing observations are coded as 999;
 RHQF is the quality flag for the relative humidity observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 VAPORP is the water vapor pressure of the air [expressed in tenths of hectopascals
 (hPa)] as determined by use of a psychrometer. The water vapor pressure
 is the partial pressure of the water vapor contained in the air. Values of
 observations considered valid may range from 0.0 to 95.0 hPa. Missing
 observations are coded as 999;
 VAPQF is the quality flag for the water vapor pressure observation (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 SLP is the sea level pressure of the air (expressed in tenths of hPa) as
 determined by use of a barometer. Because a station would rarely be able
 to position a barometer precisely at sea level, the air pressure measured at
 a station is "reduced" to sea level by using a standard barometric height
 formula. Values of observations considered valid may range from 900.0 to
 1100.0 hPa. At stations located above a certain elevation (500 m through
 1980; 800 m since 1981), air pressure is not reduced to sea level, but is
 assigned the missing code 99999;
 SLPQF is the quality flag for the sea level pressure observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 HDEF is the humidity deficit (saturation deficiency); the difference between the
 saturation vapor pressure and the actual water vapor pressure at a given
 temperature and pressure as measured in tenths of hPa. Valid values may
 range from 0.0 to 95.0 hPa. Missing observations are coded as 999;
 HDEFQF is the quality flag for the humidity deficit observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 PCHR is the pressure tendency characteristic, corresponding to the shape of the
 barograph trace of air pressure at the station for the preceding 3-h period.
 This is a coded value ranging from 0 to 8, as explained below (a missing
 value is coded as 9):
 0 = increasing, then decreasing; pressure unchanged or higher than 3 h ago;
 1 = increasing, then steady; increasing, then weaker increase;
 current pressure is higher than 3 h ago;
 2 = uniform or non-uniform increase; current pressure is higher than 3 h ago;
 3 = decreasing, then increasing; steady, then increasing; or
 increasing, then increasing more rapidly; current pressure is
 higher than 3 h ago;;
 4 = steady; pressure is the same as 3 h ago;
 5 = decreasing, then increasing; pressure is the same or lower than 3 h ago;
 6 = decreasing, then steady; or decreasing then decreasing more
 slowly; current pressure is lower than 3 h ago;
 7 = decreasing steadily or unsteadily; current pressure is lower than 3 h ago;
 8 = increasing, then decreasing; steady, then decreasing; or
 decreasing, then decreasing more quickly; current pressure is
 lower than 3 h ago;
 PCHRQF is the quality flag for the pressure tendency characteristic (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 PTND is the pressure tendency value (i.e., the absolute difference between the
 current air pressure at the station and that which was observed 3 h before).
 The sign of PTND is indicated by the value of PCHR: if PCHR is equal to
 0, 1, 2, or 3, then PTND is positive; if PCHR is equal to 4 then PTND
 should equal 0; and, if PCHR is equal to 5, 6, 7, or 8, then PTND is
 negative. Values are given in tenths of hPa; observations considered valid
 may range from 0.0 to 20.0 hPa, and a missing observation is coded as
 999);
 PTNDQF is the quality flag for the pressure tendency value (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 VIS is the horizontal visibility, given as a coded value indicating distance in
 km. The horizontal visibility is defined as the maximum distance at which
 an absolutely black body of rather large angular dimensions (over 15
 angular min) can be distinguished against the background of the sky in
 daylight, or the distance at which an unfocused light source of a given
 intensity becomes indistinguishable at night. Horizontal visibility depends
 on atmospheric phenomena. Thus, in the fog it can be reduced to zero,
 while in clear arctic air it can reach hundreds of kilometers. Coded values
 may range from 00 to 50 and from 56 to 99. Codes 00-50 and 56-89 are
 used when visibility is measured using instruments; codes 90-99 are used
 when visibility is estimated visually. The codes and their meanings are as
 follows:
 00-50 = indicates visibility in tenths of km (i.e., 0.0 km to 5.0 km).
 For example, 25 = 2.5 km (00 is the code for visibility less
 than 0.1 km);
 51-55 = not used;
 56-80 = the range 6 km to 30 km. Visibility in whole kilometers
 may be determined by subtracting 50 from the code, e.g., a
 code of 65 indicates the visibility is 15 km;
 81 = 35 km;
 82 = 40 km;
 83 = 45 km;
 84 = 50 km;
 85 = 55 km;
 86 = 60 km;
 87 = 65 km;
 88 = 70 km;
 89 = &gt;70 km;
 90 = &lt;0.05 km;
 91 = 0.05 km;
 92 = 0.2 km;
 93 = 0.5 km;
 94 = 1 km (about 1/2 mile);
 95 = 2 km (about 1 mile);
 96 = 4 km (about 2 miles);
 97 = 10 km (about 6 miles);
 98 = 20 km (about 12 miles); and
 99 = &gt;50 km (&gt;30 miles).
 If VIS = 99 with both the complement and quality flags set to 9 (see
 below), the observation is missing.
 VISCF is the horizontal visibility complement flag. VISCF = 0 indicates the
 visibility corresponds to the value given for VIS; VISCF = 1 indicates the
 visibility is actually greater than the value given for VIS; VISCF = 9
 indicates a suspect or missing observation;
 VISQF is the quality flag for the horizontal visibility value (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 HCLD is the height above ground of the base of the lowest cloud. This height is
 usually coded in hundreds of meters, as detailed in the following:
 00 = less than or equal to 50 m with fog present;
 01-25 = 100 m to 2500 m, e.g., 10 = 1000 m;
 98 = no clouds below 2500 m, however there may be mid- or
 high-level clouds whose height has not been determined;
 99 = no clouds or traces of clouds whose height has not been
 determined; or observation is missing if both complement
 and quality flags are set to 9 (see below);
 HCLDCF is the complement flag for the lowest cloud height observation. A value of
 0 means the height was measured using instrumentation; a value of 1
 indicates the height was estimated visually. This flag is set to 9 in the
 case of a suspect or missing observation;
 HCLDQF is the quality flag for the lowest cloud height observation (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 TDEW is the dew point temperature in whole degrees celsius. The dew point
 temperature is defined as the temperature to which moist air must be
 cooled, with air pressure and water vapor pressure held constant, in order
 that it just reach saturation with respect to the water in the air. The dew
 point is determined by using a psychrometer. Observations considered
 valid may range from -70&#194;&#176; to +40&#194;&#176;C. Missing observations are coded as 999;
 TDEWQF is the quality flag for the dew point temperature (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 GRND is the ground state, a visual observation of the state of the ground surface
 in the vicinity of the station made usually near 0800 and 2000 LMT. This
 is a coded value as detailed in the following:
 0 = surface of ground dry (no appreciable amount of dust or loose sand);
 1 = surface of ground moist (no pools);
 2 = surface of ground wet (standing water in small or large pools on surface);
 3 = surface of ground frozen;
 4 = glaze on ground, but no snow or melting snow;
 5 = ice, snow, or melting snow covering less than one-half of the ground;
 6 = ice, snow, or melting snow covering more than one-half of the ground;
 7 = ice, snow, or melting snow covering ground completely;
 8 = loose dry snow, dust, or sand covering more than one-half of the ground;
 9 = loose dry snow, dust, or sand covering ground completely (if GRNDQF = 0;
 otherwise, the observation is missing);
 GRNDQF is the quality flag for the ground state observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 TCLD is the total cloud amount, estimated visually by an observer according to a
 10-point system (i.e., in tenths of sky cover). A value of 0 indicates no
 clouds present or &lt;1/10 sky cover, a value of 10 indicates an overcast sky
 (with or without gaps amounting to &lt;1/10 sky cover; see explanation of
 complement flag below), and a value of 99 indicates a missing
 observation. The gaps between individual cloud elements, typical of some
 cloud genera (e.g., altocumulus and stratocumulus) are not to be included
 as part of the total cloud cover estimate (i.e., they are counted as clear sky);
 TCLDCF is the total cloud amount complement flag. TCLDCF = 1 is used if
 10-point cloudiness (overcast) is observed with gaps; TCLDCF = 0 is
 coded for all other valid cloud amounts; and TCLDCF = 9 indicates a
 suspect or missing observation;
 TCLDQF is the quality flag for the total cloud amount observation (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 LCLD is the low-cloud amount, estimated visually by an observer according to a
 10-point system (i.e., in tenths of sky cover). A value of 0 indicates no
 low clouds present or &lt;1/10 of the sky is covered with low clouds. The
 gaps between individual cloud elements, typical of some cloud genera
 (e.g., stratocumulus and cumulus) are not to be included as part of the low
 cloud cover estimate (i.e., they are counted as clear sky). Missing
 observations are coded as 99;
 LCLDCF is the low-cloud amount complement flag. TCLDCF = 1 is used if
 10-point cloudiness (overcast) is observed with gaps; TCLDCF = 0 is
 coded for all other valid low-cloud amounts; and TCLDCF = 9 indicates a
 suspect or missing observation;
 LCLDQF is the quality flag for the total cloud amount observation (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 WDIR is the direction from which the wind is blowing, as measured 10-12 m
 above ground level. This is a coded observation, the values for which are
 given as follows:
 Code Wind direction
 ---- --------------
 00 = calm winds
 02 = NNE
 05 = NE
 07 = ENE
 09 = E
 11 = ESE
 14 = SE
 16 = SSE
 18 = S
 20 = SSW
 23 = SW
 25 = WSW
 27 = W
 29 = WNW
 32 = NW
 34 = NNW
 36 = N
 99 = variable winds (if WDIRQF = 0; otherwise, the observation is missing);
 WDIRQF is the quality flag for the wind direction observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation). Missing
 observations are coded as 99;
 WSPD is the wind speed in m/s as measured 10-12 m above ground level.
 Observations considered valid may range from 0 to 60 m/s;
 WSPDQF is the quality flag for the wind speed observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 PRCP is the precipitation amount to the nearest tenth of a millimeter.
 Observations considered valid may range from 0 to 5000 (0 mm to 500 mm).
 Missing observations are coded as 9999. Rain gauges are positioned
 2 m above ground level, and were read at 0700 and 1900 LMT from 1936
 through 1965. In 1946, the old-style gauge (exact type unknown) was
 replaced with the Tretyakov-type gauge (see Appendix A for the date of
 implementation at each site). Beginning in 1966, gauges were read at
 0300, 0900, 1500, and 2100 MLT in timezone 2; at 0300, 0600, 1500,
 and 1800 MLT in zones 3-5; at 0300 and 1500 MLT in zones 6-8; at
 0000, 0300, 1200, and 1500 MLT in zones 9-11; and at 2100, 0300, 0900,
 and 1500 MLT in zone 12. Also, beginning in 1966, wetting corrections
 of 0.2 mm were applied to each hourly measurement. (Because four
 observations per day were collected at stations in timezones 2-5 and
 9-12, four corrections were counted in the calculation of daily totals;
 therefore, total daily corrections are higher for stations in these areas.)
 From 1966 onward, readings at some stations were also taken at the
 observing hours closest to 0800 and 2000 LMT. Beginning in 1986,
 readings at 0300 and 1500 MLT were discontinued at all stations except
 those in timezone 2. (The term "timezone" in the preceding corresponds
 to assigning the numbers 1-12 to 12 timezones stretching from west to
 east across the FSU. The timezone of each station in this
 sense may be obtained by subtracting 1 from the value of the ZONE
 variable in the file .)
 PRCPCF is the precipitation amount complement flag. It is set to 1 if a trace of
 precipitation has been measured, i.e., &lt;0.1 mm. This flag is set to 0 for all
 other valid precipitation observations, and is set to 9 for suspect or missing
 precipitation observations;
 PRCPQF is the quality flag for the precipitation amount (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 STAP is the pressure of the air at station level (expressed in tenths of hPa) as
 determined by use of a barometer. Values of observations considered valid
 may range from 600.0 to 1100.0 hPa. Validity is of course assessed by
 considering factors such as the station's elevation above sea level,
 geographic location, season, and pressures at neighboring stations.
 Missing observations are coded as 99999;
 STAPQF is the quality flag for the station level pressure observation (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 SOILT is the soil surface temperature, expressed in whole degrees celsius. Soil
 surface temperature is measured at a smooth, unshaded site that is devoid
 of vegetation. When the ground is snow-covered, the thermometer is
 placed on the snow surface and the temperature of the snow cover is
 measured. Observations considered valid may range from -75 to +75&#194;&#176;C.
 Missing observations are coded as 999;
 SOILQF is the quality flag for the soil surface temperature (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 W is the past weather code, used in describing the meteorological conditions
 observed between the past and current observations. At 0000, 0600, 1200,
 and 1800 GMT this code describes weather from the previous 6-hour
 period; at 0300, 0900, 1500, and 2100 GMT it describes weather for the
 previous 3-hour period. The codes and their meanings are as follows:
 0 = clear sky or no more than 5/10s cloud amount;
 1 = variable sky; cloud amount was both less than and greater than
 5/10 sky cover during the preceding three hours;
 2 = overcast or cloud amount greater than 5/10s;
 3 = sand or dust storm, or drifting or blowing snow;
 4 = fog, ice fog, or thick haze or smoke;
 5 = drizzle;
 6 = rain;
 7 = snow, or rain and snow mixed;
 8 = shower(s);
 9 = thunderstorm, with or without precipitation (if WQF = 0;
 otherwise, the observation is missing);
 WCF is the past weather complement flag. It is set to 0 when used with the
 previously defined past weather codes, however it is set to 1 for past
 weather codes 3, 7, and 8 if the past weather also included a snowstorm.
 The complement flag is set to 9 in the case of a suspect or missing past
 weather observation;
 WQF is the quality flag for the past weather observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 WW is the present weather code, reflecting the meteorological conditions at the
 time of observation or during the preceding 1-h period. Codes range from
 00 to 99 and are defined as follows:
 Code Present weather
 ---- ---------------
 00-19 = no precipitation, fog, dust storm, sandstorm, drifting or
 blowing snow at the station at the time of observation
 and, except for codes 09 and 17, during preceding hour;
 00 = cloud development conditions unknown;
 01 = cloud generally dispersing;
 02 = state of sky on the whole unchanged;
 03 = clouds generally forming or developing;
 04 = visibility reduced by smoke or volcanic ash;
 05 = haze;
 06 = widespread dust in suspension in the air;
 07 = dust or sand raised by wind at or near the station at the
 time of observation;
 08 = well developed dust whirl(s) seen at or near the station;
 09 = dust storm within sight;
 10 = mist, steam mist (light fog);
 11 = patches of shallow fog, or, from 1966 onward, ice fog;
 12 = more or less continuous shallow fog, or, from 1966
 onward, ice fog;
 13 = lightning visible, no thunder heard;
 14 = precipitation within sight, not reaching the ground;
 15 = precipitation within sight, reaching the ground or the
 surface of the sea, but distant (i.e., estimated to be
 more than 5 km from the station);
 16 = precipitation within sight, reaching the ground or the
 surface of the sea, near to, but not at the station;
 17 = thunderstorm, but no precipitation at the station or
 within sight;
 18 = squall;
 19 = funnel cloud;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 20-29 = precipitation, fog, ice fog, or thunderstorm at the
 station during the preceding hour but not at the time of
 the observation;
 20 = drizzle or snow grains;
 21 = rain;
 22 = snow;
 23 = rain and snow or ice pellets;
 24 = freezing drizzle or freezing rain;
 25 = showers of rain;
 26 = showers of snow, or of rain and snow;
 27 = shower of hail, or ice pellets;
 28 = fog or ice fog;
 29 = thunderstorm;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 30-39 = dust storm or sandstorm, drifting or blowing snow at
 the time of observation;
 30 = slight or moderate dust storm or sandstorm subsiding;
 31 = slight or moderate dust storm or sandstorm, no
 appreciable change during the preceding hour;
 32 = slight or moderate dust storm or sandstorm, increasing;
 33 = severe dust storm or sandstorm, decreasing;
 34 = severe dust storm or sandstorm with no appreciable change;
 35 = severe dust storm or sandstorm, increasing;
 36 = slight or moderate drifting snow;
 37 = heavy drifting snow;
 38 = slight or moderate blowing snow;
 39 = heavy blowing snow;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 40-49 = fog or ice fog at the time of observation;
 40 = fog or ice fog near the station;
 41 = fog or ice fog in patches;
 42 = fog or ice fog decreasing, sky discernible;
 43 = fog or ice fog decreasing, sky not discernible;
 44 = fog, or, from 1966 onward, ice fog; sky discernible; no
 appreciable change;
 45 = fog, or, from 1966 onward, ice fog; sky not
 discernible; no appreciable change;
 46 = fog or ice fog, sky discernible, becoming thicker;
 47 = fog or ice fog, sky not discernible, becoming thicker;
 48 = fog, depositing rime, sky discernible;
 49 = fog, depositing rime, sky not discernible;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 50-59 = drizzle at the station at the time of observation;
 50 = drizzle intermittent, slight at time of observation;
 51 = drizzle continuous, slight at time of observation;
 52 = drizzle intermittent, moderate at time of observation;
 53 = drizzle continuous, moderate at time of observation;
 54 = drizzle intermittent, heavy at time of observation;
 55 = drizzle continuous, heavy at time of observation;
 56 = drizzle, freezing, slight;
 57 = drizzle, freezing, heavy;
 58 = drizzle and rain, moderate or heavy;
 59 = drizzle and rain, moderate or heavy;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 60-69 = rain at the station at the time of observation;
 60 = rain intermittent, slight;
 61 = rain continuous, slight;
 62 = rain intermittent, moderate;
 63 = rain continuous, moderate;
 64 = rain intermittent, heavy;
 65 = rain continuous, heavy;
 66 = rain, freezing, slight;
 67 = rain, freezing, moderate or heavy;
 68 = rain or drizzle and snow, slight;
 69 = rain or drizzle and snow, moderate or heavy;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 70-79 = solid precipitation not in showers at the time of
 observation;
 70 = intermittent fall of snow flakes, slight;
 71 = continuous fall of snow flakes, slight;
 72 = intermittent fall of snow flakes, moderate;
 73 = continuous fall of snow flakes, moderate;
 74 = intermittent fall of snow flakes, heavy;
 75 = continuous fall of snow flakes, heavy;
 76 = diamond dust;
 77 = snow grains;
 78 = isolated starlike snow crystals;
 79 = ice pellets;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 80-90 = showery precipitation at the time of observation;
 80 = rain shower(s), slight;
 81 = rain shower(s), moderate or heavy;
 82 = rain shower(s), violent;
 83 = shower(s) of rain and snow mixed, slight;
 84 = shower(s) of rain and snow mixed, moderate or heavy;
 85 = snow shower(s), slight;
 86 = snow shower(s), moderate or heavy;
 87 = shower(s) of snow pellets or small hail, slight;
 88 = shower(s) of snow pellets or small hail, moderate or heavy;
 89 = shower(s) of hail, slight;
 90 = shower(s) of hail, moderate or heavy;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 91-99 = thunderstorm during the preceding hour or at the time
 of observation;
 91 = slight rain at time of observation, thunderstorm during
 the preceding hour;
 92 = moderate or heavy rain at time of observation,
 thunderstorm during the preceding hour;
 93 = slight snow or hail at the time of observation,
 thunderstorm during the preceding hour;
 94 = moderate or heavy snow or hail at the time of
 observation, thunderstorm during preceding hour;
 95 = thunderstorm, slight or moderate with rain and/or snow
 at the time of observation;
 96 = thunderstorm, slight or moderate with hail at the time
 of observation;
 97 = thunderstorm, heavy, with rain or snow at time of
 observation;
 98 = thunderstorm, combined with dust storm or sandstorm
 at time of observation;
 99 = thunderstorm, heavy, with hail at the time of
 observation (if WWQF = 0; otherwise, the observation
 is missing);
 WWQF is the quality flag for the present weather observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 AIRT is the air temperature (tenths of degrees celsius), measured 2 m above
 ground or snow surface level. Observations considered valid may range
 from -70.0&#194;&#176; to +55.0&#194;&#176;C. Missing observations are coded as 9999;
 AIRTQF is the quality flag for air temperature (0 indicates a valid observation; 9
 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 APH1-APH7 are seven atmospheric phenomena groups, used for reporting various
 atmospheric phenomena during the ten minutes preceding the observation
 hour. These phenomena are observed visually, as are estimates of their
 intensity. Atmospheric phenomena intensity can be weak, moderate or
 strong. The phenomena are described by means of codes that are
 particular to each of the seven groups. A coded value of 0 indicates that
 atmospheric phenomena were not observed at the time of observation.
 Additional codes and their meanings are as follows:
 APH1 group: 1 = not used;
 2 = not used;
 3 = dew;
 4 = rime;
 5 = crystalline frost, grain frost;
 6 = glazed frost;
 7 = rime and crystalline frost;
 8 = rime and glazed frost;
 9 = crystalline frost and glazed frost;
 APH2 group: 1 = not used before 1966, from 1966 onward: snow haze;
 2 = haze;
 3 = mist;
 4 = ground fog;
 5 = crystalline fog, sky visible;
 6 = ice fog;
 7 = fog, sky visible;
 8 = fog;
 9 = not used before 1966, from 1966 onward: shallow ice fog;
 APH3 group: 1 = drifting dust;
 2 = funnel cloud;
 3 = dust storm;
 4 = whirl;
 5 = drifting snow;
 6 = blowing snow;
 7 = blizzard;
 8 = snow storm;
 9 = not used;
 APH4 group: 1 = before 1966: corona around sun/moon; not used
 from 1966 onward;
 2 = sunshine;
 3 = before 1966: halo around sun/moon; not used from
 1966 onward;
 4 = snow grains and sunshine;
 5 = snow pellets and sunshine;
 6 = snow grains;
 7 = snow pellets;
 8 = ice pellets;
 9 = ice pellets and sunshine;
 APH5 group: 1 = not used;
 2 = glazed rain;
 3 = drizzle;
 4 = rain;
 5 = rain shower;
 6 = glazed rain, rain;
 7 = glazed rain, rain shower;
 8 = not used;
 9 = not used;
 APH6 group: 1 = not used;
 2 = mirage;
 3 = ice needles;
 4 = snow melting;
 5 = snow melting shower;
 6 = not used;
 7 = snow;
 8 = snow shower;
 9 = not used;
 APH7 group: 1 = not used;
 2 = sea soaring (lake or river soaring);
 3 = polar lights;
 4 = sea soaring and polar lights;
 5 = summer lightning;
 6 = before 1966, thunderstorm in the distance; not used
 from 1966 onward;
 7 = thunderstorm;
 8 = hail;
 9 = thunderstorm and hail;
 APH1CF- are the corresponding complement flags for the seven atmospheric
 APH7CF phenomena groups. These flags are used to denote whether or not an
 observation has been made, and if so, to denote the intensity of the
 phenomena. A complement flag of 0 accompanying an atmospheric
 phenomena code of 0 means none of the phenomena in a particular group
 have been observed. When accompanying a nonzero phenomena code, a
 complement flag of 0 denotes phenomena of weak intensity, 1 denotes
 moderate intensity, and 2 denotes strong intensity. A complement flag of
 9, when accompanied by a quality flag of 9 (see below) indicates a suspect
 or missing observation;
 APH1QF- are quality flags for the seven atmospheric phenomena groups (0 indicates
 APH7QF a valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 CLDH is the coded value for the high-level cloud type. High clouds are defined
 as those with bases higher than 6000 m and include cirrus (Ci),
 cirrocumulus (Cc), and cirrostratus (Cs) clouds. Codes have the following
 meanings:
 0 = cloud type is not indicated, but low- or mid-level clouds
 observed, with total cloud amount ranging anywhere from 1/10
 to overcast with gaps; high-level clouds are absent or amount
 to less than 1/10 sky cover;
 1 = Ci;
 2 = Cc;
 3 = Cs;
 4 = Ci and Cc;
 5 = Ci and Cs;
 6 = Cc and Cs;
 7 = Ci, Cc, and Cs;
 8 = high cloud presence and type cannot be determined because of
 continuous fog or snowstorm; or high-level cloud presence and
 type cannot be determined because of overcast conditions at
 lower levels;
 9 = complete absence of clouds or, in the case of translucent fog,
 clear in the zenith (if CLDHQF =0; otherwise the observation
 is missing);
 CLDHCF is the high-level cloud type complement flag. It is set to 0 when the
 high-level cloud type has been determined with no fog present; set to 1
 when the high-level cloud type has been determined with translucent fog
 or when the high-level cloud type cannot be determined because of
 continuous fog; and set to 9 if the high-level cloud type is suspect or
 missing.
 CLDHQF is the high-level cloud type quality flag (0 indicates a valid observation; 9
 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 CLDM is the coded value for the mid-level cloud type. Mid-level clouds are
 defined as those with bases between 2000 m and 6000 m; they include
 altocumulus (Ac) and altostratus (As) clouds. Codes have the following
 meanings:
 0 = cloud type is not indicated, but high-level clouds (amount
 ranging from 1/10 to overcast) and/or low-level clouds (amount
 ranging from 1/10 to overcast with gaps) observed; mid-level
 clouds are absent or amount to less than 1/10 sky cover;
 1 = Ac;
 2 = As;
 3 = not used;
 4 = Ac and As;
 5-7 = not used;
 8 = mid-level cloud presence and type cannot be determined due to
 fog or snowstorm; or mid-level cloud presence and type cannot
 be determined because of overcast at lower levels;
 9 = complete absence of clouds or, in the case of translucent fog,
 clear in the zenith (if CLDMQF =0; otherwise the observation
 is missing);
 CLDMQF is the mid-level cloud type quality flag (0 indicates a valid observation;
 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 CLDL1 is the first of three code groups for describing low-level cloud type.
 Low-level clouds are defined as those with bases lower than 2000 m; they
 include stratocumulus (Sc), stratus (St), nimbostratus (Ns), cumulus (Cu),
 and cumulonimbus (Cb) clouds. Codes have the following meanings:
 0 = cloud type is not indicated, but high- or mid-level clouds
 observed, with total cloud amount ranging anywhere from 1/10
 to overcast; low-level clouds of the CLDL1 group (see below)
 are absent or amount to less than 1/10 sky cover;
 1 = Cu;
 2 = Cb;
 3 = not used;
 4 = Cu and Cb;
 5-7 = not used;
 8 = low-level cloud presence and type cannot be determined due to
 fog or snowstorm;
 9 = complete absence of clouds or, in the case of translucent fog,
 clear in the zenith (if CLDL1F =0; otherwise the observation is
 missing);
 CLDL1F is the low-level cloud type quality flag for the first low-level cloud group
 (0 indicates a valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing
 observation);
 CLDL2 is the second of three code groups for describing low-level cloud type.
 Low-level clouds are defined as those with bases lower than 2000 m; they
 include stratocumulus (Sc), stratus (St), nimbostratus (Ns), cumulus (Cu),
 and cumulonimbus (Cb) clouds. Codes have the following meanings:
 0 = cloud type is not indicated, but high- or mid-level clouds
 observed, with total cloud amount ranging anywhere from 1/10
 to overcast; low-level clouds of the CLDL2 group (see below)
 are absent or amount to less than 1/10 sky cover;
 1 = St;
 2 = Sc;
 3 = not used;
 4 = St and Sc;
 5-7 = not used;
 8 = low-level cloud presence and type cannot be determined due to
 fog or snowstorm;
 9 = complete absence of clouds or, in the case of translucent fog,
 clear in the zenith (if CLDL2F =0; otherwise the observation is
 missing);
 CLDL2F is the low-level cloud type quality flag for the second low-level cloud
 group. (0 indicates a valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing
 observation.);
 CLDL3 is the third of three code groups for describing low-level cloud type.
 Low-level clouds are defined as those with bases lower than 2000 m; they
 include stratocumulus (Sc), stratus (St), nimbostratus (Ns), cumulus (Cu),
 and cumulonimbus (Cb) clouds. Codes have the following meanings:
 0 = cloud type is not indicated, but high- or mid-level clouds
 observed, with total cloud amount ranging anywhere from 1/10
 to overcast; low-level clouds of the CLDL3 group (see below)
 are absent or amount to less than 1/10 sky cover;
 1 = not used;
 2 = Ns;
 3 = fractostratus (Fs) and fractocumulus (Fc) of bad weather (also
 known as scud);
 4-5 = not used;
 6 = Ns and Frnb;
 7 = not used;
 8 = low-level cloud presence and type cannot be determined due to
 fog or snowstorm;
 9 = complete absence of clouds or, in the case of translucent fog,
 clear in the zenith (if CLDL3F =0; otherwise the observation is missing);
 CLDL3F is the low-level cloud type quality flag for the third low-level cloud group
 (0 indicates a valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing
 observation);
 WIR is the wind irregularity characteristic. It is a coded value used to describe
 the wind speed as steady or gusty and the wind direction as constant or
 variable. The wind is considered to be steady if its speed remains
 essentially constant over the course of two minutes; otherwise it is
 considered gusty. The wind direction is considered constant if over the
 course of two minutes it varies within one compass point; otherwise it is
 considered to be variable. Observations of this variable are only present in
 the 6-hourly data records (i.e., in the pre-1966 data). The 3-hourly records
 (1966 onward) contain a value of 9 to indicate missing data. For the pre-
 1966 data, a value of 9 is also used to indicate a missing value. Codes for
 observations have the following meanings:
 0 = no wind;
 1 = steady speed, constant direction;
 2 = steady, variable;
 3 = gusty, constant;
 4 = gusty, variable;
 5 = characteristic is not defined;
 6 = the wind speed and direction at this hour are considered suspect.
 WIRF is the wind irregularity characteristic quality flag (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation).
&#239;&#187;&#191;
 &#160;&amp;middot;&#160;]]></Text>
    </Documentation_Link>
    <OME_Software_Version>Version 4.7.5, Revision Date: 04 Apr 2006</OME_Software_Version>
    <OME_DTD_Version>metadata10.dtd</OME_DTD_Version>
    <Temporal_Resolution></Temporal_Resolution>
    <enddate_blank></enddate_blank>
    <Harvest_Date>2017-09-01</Harvest_Date>
    <File_ID>Created 20050809 143555 by 160.91.18.40</File_ID>
    <Spatial_Extent></Spatial_Extent>
    <CDIAC>
      <Product_number><![CDATA[doi 10.3334/CDIAC/cli.ndp048]]></Product_number>
      <Product_title><![CDATA[Six- and Three-Hourly Meteorological Observations from 223 U.S.S.R. Stations]]></Product_title>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Razuvaev, V. N.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[All-Russian Research Institute of Hydrometeorological Information]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[World Data Centre]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Apasova, E. B.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[All-Russian Research Institute of Hydrometeorological Information]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[World Data Centre ]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Martuganov, R. A.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[All-Russian Research Institute of Hydrometeorological Information]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[World Data Centre ]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Thematic_area><![CDATA[Climate]]></Thematic_area>
      <Site_info>
        <Site_name><![CDATA[Soviet Union]]></Site_name>
        <Site_URL><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/epubs/ndp/ndp048/ndp048.html]]></Site_URL>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/]]></Site_data_file>
      </Site_info>
      <Data_site></Data_site>
      <Variable><![CDATA[AIRT]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[AIRTQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH1]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH1CF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH1QF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH2]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH2CF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH2QF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH3]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH3CF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH3QF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH4]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH4CF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH4QF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH5CF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH5QF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH6]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH6CF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH6QF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH7]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH7CF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[APH7QF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[BMONTH]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[BYEAR]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CLDH]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CLDHCF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CLDHQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CLDL1]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CLDL1F]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CLDL2]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CLDL2F]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CLDL3]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CLDL3F]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CLDM]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CLDMQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[DAY]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[DIRECT]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[DIST]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[ELEV]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[EMONTH]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[EYEAR]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[GAP]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[GRND]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[GRNDQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[HCLD]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[HCLDCF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[HCLDQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[HDEF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[HDEFQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[HOUR]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[LAT]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[LCLD]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[LCLDCF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[LCLDQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[LON]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[MONTH]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[NAME]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[PCHR]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[PCHRQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[PRCP]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[PRCPCF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[PRCPQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[PTND]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[PTNDQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[RH]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[RHQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SEQNUM]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SLP]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SLPQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SOILQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SOILT]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[STAP]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[STAPQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[TCLD]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[TCLDCF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[TCLDQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[TDEW]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[TDEWQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[TYPE]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[VAPORP]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[VAPQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[VIS]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[VISCF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[VISQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[W]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[WCF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[WDIR]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[WDIRQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[WIR]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[WIRF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[WMO]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[WQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[WSPD]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[WSPDQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[WW]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[WWQF]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[YEAR]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[ZONE]]></Variable>
      <Descriptive_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/epubs/ndp/ndp048/ndp048.html&#239;&#187;&#191;
Contributed by
V. N. Razuvaev, E. B. Apasova, R. A. Martuganov
All-Russian Research Institute
of Hydrometeorological Information-World Data Centre
Prepared by
D. P. Kaiser and G. P. Marino
)
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
Oak Ridge National Laboratory
Prepared for the
Climate Change Research Division
Office of Biological and Environmental Research
U.S. Department of Energy
Prepared by the
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
OAK RIDGE NATIONAL LABORATORY
Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831-6290
managed by
University of Tennessee-Battelle, LLC
for the
U.S. DEPARTMENT OF ENERGY
V. N. Razuvaev, E. B. Apasova, R. A. Martuganov
All-Russian Research Institute
of Hydrometeorological Information-World Data Centre
Fortran and SAS Data Retrieval Programs (.for and .sas files) - These files are provided for the benefit of users with FORTRAN or SAS on their systems, enabling them to read any of the data files in this database using these software packages. The program files are:
 Variable Variable Starting Ending
 Variable type width column column
 SEQNUM Numeric 3 1 3
 WMO Numeric 5 5 9
 NAME Character 25 11 35
 LAT Numeric 5 37 41
 LON Numeric 7 43 49
 ELEV Numeric 6 51 56
 BMONTH Numeric 2 61 62
 BYEAR Numeric 4 64 67
 EMONTH Numeric 2 69 70
 EYEAR Numeric 4 72 75
 where
 SEQNUM is the sequence number of the station in the data base (1-223);
 WMO is the WMO No. of the station;
 NAME is the name of the station;
 LAT is the latitude of the station in decimal degrees north;
 LON is the longitude of the station in decimal degrees east;
 ELEV is the elevation of the station above sea level (meters) missing elevations
 are coded as -999.9;
 BMONTH is the beginning month of the station's period of record;
 BYEAR is the beginning year of the station's period of record;
 EMONTH is the ending month of the station's period of record; and
 EYEAR is the ending year of the station's period of record.
24966 - October 1, 1981
25551 - January 1, 1982
27648 - January 1, 1970
27947 - April 1, 1981
34123 - April 1, 1981
 Variable Variable Starting Ending
 Variable type width column column
 WMO Numeric 5 1 5
 TYPE Character 4 7 10
 YEAR Numeric 4 12 15
 MONTH Numeric 2 17 18
 DAY Numeric 2 20 21
 DIST Character 2 23 24
 DIRECT Character 3 26 28
 where
 WMO is the WMO No. of the station;
 TYPE is the type of change indicated by this entry. The possible values of TYPE
 are as follows:
 RAIN = rain gauge replacement (i.e., change from old-type gauge
 to Tretyakov-type gauge). Each station will have only one
 RAIN entry. When this type of entry is used, DIST and
 DIRECT (described below) are not relevant and thus are
 coded as blanks;
 MOVE = station relocation. Each station will have at least one
 MOVE entry. If a station moved on more than one
 occasion, then separate entries are included for each
 relocation. If a station never moved, then that station will
 have only one MOVE entry; in this entry, YEAR,
 MONTH, DAY, DIST, and DIRECT (described below) are
 all coded as missing. In other words, if a station has only
 one MOVE entry, and if all variables in that MOVE entry
 are coded as missing, then the given station never moved;
 YEAR is the year in which the change took place. Missing years are coded as
 999;
 MONTH is the month in which the change took place. Missing months are coded
 as 9;
 DAY is the day on which the change took place. Missing days are coded as 9;
 DIST is the distance (km) that the station was moved. Missing distances are
 coded as 9. A distance of zero indicates that the station moved less than 1
 km. DIST only applies to station relocation entries (i.e., lines in which
 TYPE = MOVE). In rain gauge replacement entries (i.e., lines in which
 TYPE = RAIN), DIST is not relevant and thus is coded as blanks; and
 DIRECT is the direction in which the station was moved (e.g., N = north, SE =
 southeast). Missing directions are coded as 99. DIRECT only applies to
 station relocation entries (i.e., lines in which TYPE = MOVE). In rain
 gauge replacement entries (i.e., lines in which TYPE = RAIN), DIRECT is
 not relevant and thus is coded as blanks.
 Variable Starting Ending
 Variable width column column
 WMO 5 1 5
 YEAR 4 6 9
 MONTH 2 10 11
 DAY 2 12 13
 HOUR 2 14 15
 RH 3 16 18
 RHQF 1 19 19
 VAPORP 3 20 22
 VAPQF 1 23 23
 SLP 5 24 28
 SLPQF 1 29 29
 HDEF 3 30 32
 HDEFQF 1 33 33
 PCHR 1 34 34
 PCHRQF 1 35 35
 PTND 3 36 38
 PTNDQF 1 39 39
 VIS 2 40 41
 VISCF 1 42 42
 VISQF 1 43 43
 HCLD 2 44 45
 HCLDCF 1 46 46
 HCLDQF 1 47 47
 TDEW 3 48 50
 TDEWQF 1 51 51
 GRND 1 52 52
 GRNDQF 1 53 53
 TCLD 2 54 55
 TCLDCF 1 56 56
 TCLDQF 1 57 57
 LCLD 2 58 59
 LCLDCF 1 60 60
 LCLDQF 1 61 61
 WDIR 2 62 63
 WDIRQF 1 64 64
 WSPD 2 65 66
 WSPDQF 1 67 67
 PRCP 4 68 71
 PRCPCF 1 72 72
 PRCPQF 1 73 73
 STAP 5 74 78
 STAPQF 1 79 79
 SOILT 3 80 82
 SOILQF 1 83 83
 W 1 84 84
 WCF 1 85 85
 WQF 1 86 86
 WW 2 87 88
 WWQF 1 89 89
 AIRT 4 90 93
 AIRTQF 1 94 94
 APH1 1 95 95
 APH1CF 1 96 96
 APH1QF 1 97 97
 APH2 1 98 98
 APH2CF 1 99 99
 APH2QF 1 100 100
 APH3 1 101 101
 APH3CF 1 102 102
 APH3QF 1 103 103
 APH4 1 104 104
 APH4CF 1 105 105
 APH4QF 1 106 106
 APH5 1 107 107
 APH5CF 1 108 108
 APH5QF 1 109 109
 APH6 1 110 110
 APH6CF 1 111 111
 APH6QF 1 112 112
 APH7 1 113 113
 APH7CF 1 114 114
 APH7QF 1 115 115
 CLDH 1 116 116
 CLDHCF 1 117 117
 CLDHQF 1 118 118
 CLDM 1 119 119
 CLDMQF 1 120 120
 CLDL1 1 121 121
 CLDL1F 1 122 122
 CLDL2 1 123 123
 CLDL2F 1 124 124
 CLDL3 1 125 125
 CLDL3F 1 126 126
 WIR 1 127 127
 WIRF 1 128 128
 where
 WMO is the WMO number of the station;
 YEAR is the year (Greenwich) of the observations in the record;
 MONTH is the month (Greenwich) of the observations in the record;
 DAY is the day (Greenwich) of the observations in the record;
 HOUR is the GMT of the observations in the record;
 RH is the relative humidity of the air (expressed in percent) as determined by
 use of a psychrometer. Relative humidity is defined as the ratio of the
 observed vapor pressure to the saturation vapor pressure for the observed
 air temperature. Values of observations may range from 0 to 100%.
 Missing observations are coded as 999;
 RHQF is the quality flag for the relative humidity observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 VAPORP is the water vapor pressure of the air [expressed in tenths of hectopascals
 (hPa)] as determined by use of a psychrometer. The water vapor pressure
 is the partial pressure of the water vapor contained in the air. Values of
 observations considered valid may range from 0.0 to 95.0 hPa. Missing
 observations are coded as 999;
 VAPQF is the quality flag for the water vapor pressure observation (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 SLP is the sea level pressure of the air (expressed in tenths of hPa) as
 determined by use of a barometer. Because a station would rarely be able
 to position a barometer precisely at sea level, the air pressure measured at
 a station is "reduced" to sea level by using a standard barometric height
 formula. Values of observations considered valid may range from 900.0 to
 1100.0 hPa. At stations located above a certain elevation (500 m through
 1980; 800 m since 1981), air pressure is not reduced to sea level, but is
 assigned the missing code 99999;
 SLPQF is the quality flag for the sea level pressure observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 HDEF is the humidity deficit (saturation deficiency); the difference between the
 saturation vapor pressure and the actual water vapor pressure at a given
 temperature and pressure as measured in tenths of hPa. Valid values may
 range from 0.0 to 95.0 hPa. Missing observations are coded as 999;
 HDEFQF is the quality flag for the humidity deficit observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 PCHR is the pressure tendency characteristic, corresponding to the shape of the
 barograph trace of air pressure at the station for the preceding 3-h period.
 This is a coded value ranging from 0 to 8, as explained below (a missing
 value is coded as 9):
 0 = increasing, then decreasing; pressure unchanged or higher than 3 h ago;
 1 = increasing, then steady; increasing, then weaker increase;
 current pressure is higher than 3 h ago;
 2 = uniform or non-uniform increase; current pressure is higher than 3 h ago;
 3 = decreasing, then increasing; steady, then increasing; or
 increasing, then increasing more rapidly; current pressure is
 higher than 3 h ago;;
 4 = steady; pressure is the same as 3 h ago;
 5 = decreasing, then increasing; pressure is the same or lower than 3 h ago;
 6 = decreasing, then steady; or decreasing then decreasing more
 slowly; current pressure is lower than 3 h ago;
 7 = decreasing steadily or unsteadily; current pressure is lower than 3 h ago;
 8 = increasing, then decreasing; steady, then decreasing; or
 decreasing, then decreasing more quickly; current pressure is
 lower than 3 h ago;
 PCHRQF is the quality flag for the pressure tendency characteristic (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 PTND is the pressure tendency value (i.e., the absolute difference between the
 current air pressure at the station and that which was observed 3 h before).
 The sign of PTND is indicated by the value of PCHR: if PCHR is equal to
 0, 1, 2, or 3, then PTND is positive; if PCHR is equal to 4 then PTND
 should equal 0; and, if PCHR is equal to 5, 6, 7, or 8, then PTND is
 negative. Values are given in tenths of hPa; observations considered valid
 may range from 0.0 to 20.0 hPa, and a missing observation is coded as
 999);
 PTNDQF is the quality flag for the pressure tendency value (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 VIS is the horizontal visibility, given as a coded value indicating distance in
 km. The horizontal visibility is defined as the maximum distance at which
 an absolutely black body of rather large angular dimensions (over 15
 angular min) can be distinguished against the background of the sky in
 daylight, or the distance at which an unfocused light source of a given
 intensity becomes indistinguishable at night. Horizontal visibility depends
 on atmospheric phenomena. Thus, in the fog it can be reduced to zero,
 while in clear arctic air it can reach hundreds of kilometers. Coded values
 may range from 00 to 50 and from 56 to 99. Codes 00-50 and 56-89 are
 used when visibility is measured using instruments; codes 90-99 are used
 when visibility is estimated visually. The codes and their meanings are as
 follows:
 00-50 = indicates visibility in tenths of km (i.e., 0.0 km to 5.0 km).
 For example, 25 = 2.5 km (00 is the code for visibility less
 than 0.1 km);
 51-55 = not used;
 56-80 = the range 6 km to 30 km. Visibility in whole kilometers
 may be determined by subtracting 50 from the code, e.g., a
 code of 65 indicates the visibility is 15 km;
 81 = 35 km;
 82 = 40 km;
 83 = 45 km;
 84 = 50 km;
 85 = 55 km;
 86 = 60 km;
 87 = 65 km;
 88 = 70 km;
 89 = &gt;70 km;
 90 = &lt;0.05 km;
 91 = 0.05 km;
 92 = 0.2 km;
 93 = 0.5 km;
 94 = 1 km (about 1/2 mile);
 95 = 2 km (about 1 mile);
 96 = 4 km (about 2 miles);
 97 = 10 km (about 6 miles);
 98 = 20 km (about 12 miles); and
 99 = &gt;50 km (&gt;30 miles).
 If VIS = 99 with both the complement and quality flags set to 9 (see
 below), the observation is missing.
 VISCF is the horizontal visibility complement flag. VISCF = 0 indicates the
 visibility corresponds to the value given for VIS; VISCF = 1 indicates the
 visibility is actually greater than the value given for VIS; VISCF = 9
 indicates a suspect or missing observation;
 VISQF is the quality flag for the horizontal visibility value (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 HCLD is the height above ground of the base of the lowest cloud. This height is
 usually coded in hundreds of meters, as detailed in the following:
 00 = less than or equal to 50 m with fog present;
 01-25 = 100 m to 2500 m, e.g., 10 = 1000 m;
 98 = no clouds below 2500 m, however there may be mid- or
 high-level clouds whose height has not been determined;
 99 = no clouds or traces of clouds whose height has not been
 determined; or observation is missing if both complement
 and quality flags are set to 9 (see below);
 HCLDCF is the complement flag for the lowest cloud height observation. A value of
 0 means the height was measured using instrumentation; a value of 1
 indicates the height was estimated visually. This flag is set to 9 in the
 case of a suspect or missing observation;
 HCLDQF is the quality flag for the lowest cloud height observation (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 TDEW is the dew point temperature in whole degrees celsius. The dew point
 temperature is defined as the temperature to which moist air must be
 cooled, with air pressure and water vapor pressure held constant, in order
 that it just reach saturation with respect to the water in the air. The dew
 point is determined by using a psychrometer. Observations considered
 valid may range from -70&#194;&#176; to +40&#194;&#176;C. Missing observations are coded as 999;
 TDEWQF is the quality flag for the dew point temperature (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 GRND is the ground state, a visual observation of the state of the ground surface
 in the vicinity of the station made usually near 0800 and 2000 LMT. This
 is a coded value as detailed in the following:
 0 = surface of ground dry (no appreciable amount of dust or loose sand);
 1 = surface of ground moist (no pools);
 2 = surface of ground wet (standing water in small or large pools on surface);
 3 = surface of ground frozen;
 4 = glaze on ground, but no snow or melting snow;
 5 = ice, snow, or melting snow covering less than one-half of the ground;
 6 = ice, snow, or melting snow covering more than one-half of the ground;
 7 = ice, snow, or melting snow covering ground completely;
 8 = loose dry snow, dust, or sand covering more than one-half of the ground;
 9 = loose dry snow, dust, or sand covering ground completely (if GRNDQF = 0;
 otherwise, the observation is missing);
 GRNDQF is the quality flag for the ground state observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 TCLD is the total cloud amount, estimated visually by an observer according to a
 10-point system (i.e., in tenths of sky cover). A value of 0 indicates no
 clouds present or &lt;1/10 sky cover, a value of 10 indicates an overcast sky
 (with or without gaps amounting to &lt;1/10 sky cover; see explanation of
 complement flag below), and a value of 99 indicates a missing
 observation. The gaps between individual cloud elements, typical of some
 cloud genera (e.g., altocumulus and stratocumulus) are not to be included
 as part of the total cloud cover estimate (i.e., they are counted as clear sky);
 TCLDCF is the total cloud amount complement flag. TCLDCF = 1 is used if
 10-point cloudiness (overcast) is observed with gaps; TCLDCF = 0 is
 coded for all other valid cloud amounts; and TCLDCF = 9 indicates a
 suspect or missing observation;
 TCLDQF is the quality flag for the total cloud amount observation (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 LCLD is the low-cloud amount, estimated visually by an observer according to a
 10-point system (i.e., in tenths of sky cover). A value of 0 indicates no
 low clouds present or &lt;1/10 of the sky is covered with low clouds. The
 gaps between individual cloud elements, typical of some cloud genera
 (e.g., stratocumulus and cumulus) are not to be included as part of the low
 cloud cover estimate (i.e., they are counted as clear sky). Missing
 observations are coded as 99;
 LCLDCF is the low-cloud amount complement flag. TCLDCF = 1 is used if
 10-point cloudiness (overcast) is observed with gaps; TCLDCF = 0 is
 coded for all other valid low-cloud amounts; and TCLDCF = 9 indicates a
 suspect or missing observation;
 LCLDQF is the quality flag for the total cloud amount observation (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 WDIR is the direction from which the wind is blowing, as measured 10-12 m
 above ground level. This is a coded observation, the values for which are
 given as follows:
 Code Wind direction
 ---- --------------
 00 = calm winds
 02 = NNE
 05 = NE
 07 = ENE
 09 = E
 11 = ESE
 14 = SE
 16 = SSE
 18 = S
 20 = SSW
 23 = SW
 25 = WSW
 27 = W
 29 = WNW
 32 = NW
 34 = NNW
 36 = N
 99 = variable winds (if WDIRQF = 0; otherwise, the observation is missing);
 WDIRQF is the quality flag for the wind direction observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation). Missing
 observations are coded as 99;
 WSPD is the wind speed in m/s as measured 10-12 m above ground level.
 Observations considered valid may range from 0 to 60 m/s;
 WSPDQF is the quality flag for the wind speed observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 PRCP is the precipitation amount to the nearest tenth of a millimeter.
 Observations considered valid may range from 0 to 5000 (0 mm to 500 mm).
 Missing observations are coded as 9999. Rain gauges are positioned
 2 m above ground level, and were read at 0700 and 1900 LMT from 1936
 through 1965. In 1946, the old-style gauge (exact type unknown) was
 replaced with the Tretyakov-type gauge (see Appendix A for the date of
 implementation at each site). Beginning in 1966, gauges were read at
 0300, 0900, 1500, and 2100 MLT in timezone 2; at 0300, 0600, 1500,
 and 1800 MLT in zones 3-5; at 0300 and 1500 MLT in zones 6-8; at
 0000, 0300, 1200, and 1500 MLT in zones 9-11; and at 2100, 0300, 0900,
 and 1500 MLT in zone 12. Also, beginning in 1966, wetting corrections
 of 0.2 mm were applied to each hourly measurement. (Because four
 observations per day were collected at stations in timezones 2-5 and
 9-12, four corrections were counted in the calculation of daily totals;
 therefore, total daily corrections are higher for stations in these areas.)
 From 1966 onward, readings at some stations were also taken at the
 observing hours closest to 0800 and 2000 LMT. Beginning in 1986,
 readings at 0300 and 1500 MLT were discontinued at all stations except
 those in timezone 2. (The term "timezone" in the preceding corresponds
 to assigning the numbers 1-12 to 12 timezones stretching from west to
 east across the FSU. The timezone of each station in this
 sense may be obtained by subtracting 1 from the value of the ZONE
 variable in the file .)
 PRCPCF is the precipitation amount complement flag. It is set to 1 if a trace of
 precipitation has been measured, i.e., &lt;0.1 mm. This flag is set to 0 for all
 other valid precipitation observations, and is set to 9 for suspect or missing
 precipitation observations;
 PRCPQF is the quality flag for the precipitation amount (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 STAP is the pressure of the air at station level (expressed in tenths of hPa) as
 determined by use of a barometer. Values of observations considered valid
 may range from 600.0 to 1100.0 hPa. Validity is of course assessed by
 considering factors such as the station's elevation above sea level,
 geographic location, season, and pressures at neighboring stations.
 Missing observations are coded as 99999;
 STAPQF is the quality flag for the station level pressure observation (0 indicates a
 valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 SOILT is the soil surface temperature, expressed in whole degrees celsius. Soil
 surface temperature is measured at a smooth, unshaded site that is devoid
 of vegetation. When the ground is snow-covered, the thermometer is
 placed on the snow surface and the temperature of the snow cover is
 measured. Observations considered valid may range from -75 to +75&#194;&#176;C.
 Missing observations are coded as 999;
 SOILQF is the quality flag for the soil surface temperature (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 W is the past weather code, used in describing the meteorological conditions
 observed between the past and current observations. At 0000, 0600, 1200,
 and 1800 GMT this code describes weather from the previous 6-hour
 period; at 0300, 0900, 1500, and 2100 GMT it describes weather for the
 previous 3-hour period. The codes and their meanings are as follows:
 0 = clear sky or no more than 5/10s cloud amount;
 1 = variable sky; cloud amount was both less than and greater than
 5/10 sky cover during the preceding three hours;
 2 = overcast or cloud amount greater than 5/10s;
 3 = sand or dust storm, or drifting or blowing snow;
 4 = fog, ice fog, or thick haze or smoke;
 5 = drizzle;
 6 = rain;
 7 = snow, or rain and snow mixed;
 8 = shower(s);
 9 = thunderstorm, with or without precipitation (if WQF = 0;
 otherwise, the observation is missing);
 WCF is the past weather complement flag. It is set to 0 when used with the
 previously defined past weather codes, however it is set to 1 for past
 weather codes 3, 7, and 8 if the past weather also included a snowstorm.
 The complement flag is set to 9 in the case of a suspect or missing past
 weather observation;
 WQF is the quality flag for the past weather observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 WW is the present weather code, reflecting the meteorological conditions at the
 time of observation or during the preceding 1-h period. Codes range from
 00 to 99 and are defined as follows:
 Code Present weather
 ---- ---------------
 00-19 = no precipitation, fog, dust storm, sandstorm, drifting or
 blowing snow at the station at the time of observation
 and, except for codes 09 and 17, during preceding hour;
 00 = cloud development conditions unknown;
 01 = cloud generally dispersing;
 02 = state of sky on the whole unchanged;
 03 = clouds generally forming or developing;
 04 = visibility reduced by smoke or volcanic ash;
 05 = haze;
 06 = widespread dust in suspension in the air;
 07 = dust or sand raised by wind at or near the station at the
 time of observation;
 08 = well developed dust whirl(s) seen at or near the station;
 09 = dust storm within sight;
 10 = mist, steam mist (light fog);
 11 = patches of shallow fog, or, from 1966 onward, ice fog;
 12 = more or less continuous shallow fog, or, from 1966
 onward, ice fog;
 13 = lightning visible, no thunder heard;
 14 = precipitation within sight, not reaching the ground;
 15 = precipitation within sight, reaching the ground or the
 surface of the sea, but distant (i.e., estimated to be
 more than 5 km from the station);
 16 = precipitation within sight, reaching the ground or the
 surface of the sea, near to, but not at the station;
 17 = thunderstorm, but no precipitation at the station or
 within sight;
 18 = squall;
 19 = funnel cloud;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 20-29 = precipitation, fog, ice fog, or thunderstorm at the
 station during the preceding hour but not at the time of
 the observation;
 20 = drizzle or snow grains;
 21 = rain;
 22 = snow;
 23 = rain and snow or ice pellets;
 24 = freezing drizzle or freezing rain;
 25 = showers of rain;
 26 = showers of snow, or of rain and snow;
 27 = shower of hail, or ice pellets;
 28 = fog or ice fog;
 29 = thunderstorm;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 30-39 = dust storm or sandstorm, drifting or blowing snow at
 the time of observation;
 30 = slight or moderate dust storm or sandstorm subsiding;
 31 = slight or moderate dust storm or sandstorm, no
 appreciable change during the preceding hour;
 32 = slight or moderate dust storm or sandstorm, increasing;
 33 = severe dust storm or sandstorm, decreasing;
 34 = severe dust storm or sandstorm with no appreciable change;
 35 = severe dust storm or sandstorm, increasing;
 36 = slight or moderate drifting snow;
 37 = heavy drifting snow;
 38 = slight or moderate blowing snow;
 39 = heavy blowing snow;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 40-49 = fog or ice fog at the time of observation;
 40 = fog or ice fog near the station;
 41 = fog or ice fog in patches;
 42 = fog or ice fog decreasing, sky discernible;
 43 = fog or ice fog decreasing, sky not discernible;
 44 = fog, or, from 1966 onward, ice fog; sky discernible; no
 appreciable change;
 45 = fog, or, from 1966 onward, ice fog; sky not
 discernible; no appreciable change;
 46 = fog or ice fog, sky discernible, becoming thicker;
 47 = fog or ice fog, sky not discernible, becoming thicker;
 48 = fog, depositing rime, sky discernible;
 49 = fog, depositing rime, sky not discernible;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 50-59 = drizzle at the station at the time of observation;
 50 = drizzle intermittent, slight at time of observation;
 51 = drizzle continuous, slight at time of observation;
 52 = drizzle intermittent, moderate at time of observation;
 53 = drizzle continuous, moderate at time of observation;
 54 = drizzle intermittent, heavy at time of observation;
 55 = drizzle continuous, heavy at time of observation;
 56 = drizzle, freezing, slight;
 57 = drizzle, freezing, heavy;
 58 = drizzle and rain, moderate or heavy;
 59 = drizzle and rain, moderate or heavy;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 60-69 = rain at the station at the time of observation;
 60 = rain intermittent, slight;
 61 = rain continuous, slight;
 62 = rain intermittent, moderate;
 63 = rain continuous, moderate;
 64 = rain intermittent, heavy;
 65 = rain continuous, heavy;
 66 = rain, freezing, slight;
 67 = rain, freezing, moderate or heavy;
 68 = rain or drizzle and snow, slight;
 69 = rain or drizzle and snow, moderate or heavy;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 70-79 = solid precipitation not in showers at the time of
 observation;
 70 = intermittent fall of snow flakes, slight;
 71 = continuous fall of snow flakes, slight;
 72 = intermittent fall of snow flakes, moderate;
 73 = continuous fall of snow flakes, moderate;
 74 = intermittent fall of snow flakes, heavy;
 75 = continuous fall of snow flakes, heavy;
 76 = diamond dust;
 77 = snow grains;
 78 = isolated starlike snow crystals;
 79 = ice pellets;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 80-90 = showery precipitation at the time of observation;
 80 = rain shower(s), slight;
 81 = rain shower(s), moderate or heavy;
 82 = rain shower(s), violent;
 83 = shower(s) of rain and snow mixed, slight;
 84 = shower(s) of rain and snow mixed, moderate or heavy;
 85 = snow shower(s), slight;
 86 = snow shower(s), moderate or heavy;
 87 = shower(s) of snow pellets or small hail, slight;
 88 = shower(s) of snow pellets or small hail, moderate or heavy;
 89 = shower(s) of hail, slight;
 90 = shower(s) of hail, moderate or heavy;
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 91-99 = thunderstorm during the preceding hour or at the time
 of observation;
 91 = slight rain at time of observation, thunderstorm during
 the preceding hour;
 92 = moderate or heavy rain at time of observation,
 thunderstorm during the preceding hour;
 93 = slight snow or hail at the time of observation,
 thunderstorm during the preceding hour;
 94 = moderate or heavy snow or hail at the time of
 observation, thunderstorm during preceding hour;
 95 = thunderstorm, slight or moderate with rain and/or snow
 at the time of observation;
 96 = thunderstorm, slight or moderate with hail at the time
 of observation;
 97 = thunderstorm, heavy, with rain or snow at time of
 observation;
 98 = thunderstorm, combined with dust storm or sandstorm
 at time of observation;
 99 = thunderstorm, heavy, with hail at the time of
 observation (if WWQF = 0; otherwise, the observation
 is missing);
 WWQF is the quality flag for the present weather observation (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 AIRT is the air temperature (tenths of degrees celsius), measured 2 m above
 ground or snow surface level. Observations considered valid may range
 from -70.0&#194;&#176; to +55.0&#194;&#176;C. Missing observations are coded as 9999;
 AIRTQF is the quality flag for air temperature (0 indicates a valid observation; 9
 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 APH1-APH7 are seven atmospheric phenomena groups, used for reporting various
 atmospheric phenomena during the ten minutes preceding the observation
 hour. These phenomena are observed visually, as are estimates of their
 intensity. Atmospheric phenomena intensity can be weak, moderate or
 strong. The phenomena are described by means of codes that are
 particular to each of the seven groups. A coded value of 0 indicates that
 atmospheric phenomena were not observed at the time of observation.
 Additional codes and their meanings are as follows:
 APH1 group: 1 = not used;
 2 = not used;
 3 = dew;
 4 = rime;
 5 = crystalline frost, grain frost;
 6 = glazed frost;
 7 = rime and crystalline frost;
 8 = rime and glazed frost;
 9 = crystalline frost and glazed frost;
 APH2 group: 1 = not used before 1966, from 1966 onward: snow haze;
 2 = haze;
 3 = mist;
 4 = ground fog;
 5 = crystalline fog, sky visible;
 6 = ice fog;
 7 = fog, sky visible;
 8 = fog;
 9 = not used before 1966, from 1966 onward: shallow ice fog;
 APH3 group: 1 = drifting dust;
 2 = funnel cloud;
 3 = dust storm;
 4 = whirl;
 5 = drifting snow;
 6 = blowing snow;
 7 = blizzard;
 8 = snow storm;
 9 = not used;
 APH4 group: 1 = before 1966: corona around sun/moon; not used
 from 1966 onward;
 2 = sunshine;
 3 = before 1966: halo around sun/moon; not used from
 1966 onward;
 4 = snow grains and sunshine;
 5 = snow pellets and sunshine;
 6 = snow grains;
 7 = snow pellets;
 8 = ice pellets;
 9 = ice pellets and sunshine;
 APH5 group: 1 = not used;
 2 = glazed rain;
 3 = drizzle;
 4 = rain;
 5 = rain shower;
 6 = glazed rain, rain;
 7 = glazed rain, rain shower;
 8 = not used;
 9 = not used;
 APH6 group: 1 = not used;
 2 = mirage;
 3 = ice needles;
 4 = snow melting;
 5 = snow melting shower;
 6 = not used;
 7 = snow;
 8 = snow shower;
 9 = not used;
 APH7 group: 1 = not used;
 2 = sea soaring (lake or river soaring);
 3 = polar lights;
 4 = sea soaring and polar lights;
 5 = summer lightning;
 6 = before 1966, thunderstorm in the distance; not used
 from 1966 onward;
 7 = thunderstorm;
 8 = hail;
 9 = thunderstorm and hail;
 APH1CF- are the corresponding complement flags for the seven atmospheric
 APH7CF phenomena groups. These flags are used to denote whether or not an
 observation has been made, and if so, to denote the intensity of the
 phenomena. A complement flag of 0 accompanying an atmospheric
 phenomena code of 0 means none of the phenomena in a particular group
 have been observed. When accompanying a nonzero phenomena code, a
 complement flag of 0 denotes phenomena of weak intensity, 1 denotes
 moderate intensity, and 2 denotes strong intensity. A complement flag of
 9, when accompanied by a quality flag of 9 (see below) indicates a suspect
 or missing observation;
 APH1QF- are quality flags for the seven atmospheric phenomena groups (0 indicates
 APH7QF a valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 CLDH is the coded value for the high-level cloud type. High clouds are defined
 as those with bases higher than 6000 m and include cirrus (Ci),
 cirrocumulus (Cc), and cirrostratus (Cs) clouds. Codes have the following
 meanings:
 0 = cloud type is not indicated, but low- or mid-level clouds
 observed, with total cloud amount ranging anywhere from 1/10
 to overcast with gaps; high-level clouds are absent or amount
 to less than 1/10 sky cover;
 1 = Ci;
 2 = Cc;
 3 = Cs;
 4 = Ci and Cc;
 5 = Ci and Cs;
 6 = Cc and Cs;
 7 = Ci, Cc, and Cs;
 8 = high cloud presence and type cannot be determined because of
 continuous fog or snowstorm; or high-level cloud presence and
 type cannot be determined because of overcast conditions at
 lower levels;
 9 = complete absence of clouds or, in the case of translucent fog,
 clear in the zenith (if CLDHQF =0; otherwise the observation
 is missing);
 CLDHCF is the high-level cloud type complement flag. It is set to 0 when the
 high-level cloud type has been determined with no fog present; set to 1
 when the high-level cloud type has been determined with translucent fog
 or when the high-level cloud type cannot be determined because of
 continuous fog; and set to 9 if the high-level cloud type is suspect or
 missing.
 CLDHQF is the high-level cloud type quality flag (0 indicates a valid observation; 9
 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 CLDM is the coded value for the mid-level cloud type. Mid-level clouds are
 defined as those with bases between 2000 m and 6000 m; they include
 altocumulus (Ac) and altostratus (As) clouds. Codes have the following
 meanings:
 0 = cloud type is not indicated, but high-level clouds (amount
 ranging from 1/10 to overcast) and/or low-level clouds (amount
 ranging from 1/10 to overcast with gaps) observed; mid-level
 clouds are absent or amount to less than 1/10 sky cover;
 1 = Ac;
 2 = As;
 3 = not used;
 4 = Ac and As;
 5-7 = not used;
 8 = mid-level cloud presence and type cannot be determined due to
 fog or snowstorm; or mid-level cloud presence and type cannot
 be determined because of overcast at lower levels;
 9 = complete absence of clouds or, in the case of translucent fog,
 clear in the zenith (if CLDMQF =0; otherwise the observation
 is missing);
 CLDMQF is the mid-level cloud type quality flag (0 indicates a valid observation;
 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation);
 CLDL1 is the first of three code groups for describing low-level cloud type.
 Low-level clouds are defined as those with bases lower than 2000 m; they
 include stratocumulus (Sc), stratus (St), nimbostratus (Ns), cumulus (Cu),
 and cumulonimbus (Cb) clouds. Codes have the following meanings:
 0 = cloud type is not indicated, but high- or mid-level clouds
 observed, with total cloud amount ranging anywhere from 1/10
 to overcast; low-level clouds of the CLDL1 group (see below)
 are absent or amount to less than 1/10 sky cover;
 1 = Cu;
 2 = Cb;
 3 = not used;
 4 = Cu and Cb;
 5-7 = not used;
 8 = low-level cloud presence and type cannot be determined due to
 fog or snowstorm;
 9 = complete absence of clouds or, in the case of translucent fog,
 clear in the zenith (if CLDL1F =0; otherwise the observation is
 missing);
 CLDL1F is the low-level cloud type quality flag for the first low-level cloud group
 (0 indicates a valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing
 observation);
 CLDL2 is the second of three code groups for describing low-level cloud type.
 Low-level clouds are defined as those with bases lower than 2000 m; they
 include stratocumulus (Sc), stratus (St), nimbostratus (Ns), cumulus (Cu),
 and cumulonimbus (Cb) clouds. Codes have the following meanings:
 0 = cloud type is not indicated, but high- or mid-level clouds
 observed, with total cloud amount ranging anywhere from 1/10
 to overcast; low-level clouds of the CLDL2 group (see below)
 are absent or amount to less than 1/10 sky cover;
 1 = St;
 2 = Sc;
 3 = not used;
 4 = St and Sc;
 5-7 = not used;
 8 = low-level cloud presence and type cannot be determined due to
 fog or snowstorm;
 9 = complete absence of clouds or, in the case of translucent fog,
 clear in the zenith (if CLDL2F =0; otherwise the observation is
 missing);
 CLDL2F is the low-level cloud type quality flag for the second low-level cloud
 group. (0 indicates a valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing
 observation.);
 CLDL3 is the third of three code groups for describing low-level cloud type.
 Low-level clouds are defined as those with bases lower than 2000 m; they
 include stratocumulus (Sc), stratus (St), nimbostratus (Ns), cumulus (Cu),
 and cumulonimbus (Cb) clouds. Codes have the following meanings:
 0 = cloud type is not indicated, but high- or mid-level clouds
 observed, with total cloud amount ranging anywhere from 1/10
 to overcast; low-level clouds of the CLDL3 group (see below)
 are absent or amount to less than 1/10 sky cover;
 1 = not used;
 2 = Ns;
 3 = fractostratus (Fs) and fractocumulus (Fc) of bad weather (also
 known as scud);
 4-5 = not used;
 6 = Ns and Frnb;
 7 = not used;
 8 = low-level cloud presence and type cannot be determined due to
 fog or snowstorm;
 9 = complete absence of clouds or, in the case of translucent fog,
 clear in the zenith (if CLDL3F =0; otherwise the observation is missing);
 CLDL3F is the low-level cloud type quality flag for the third low-level cloud group
 (0 indicates a valid observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing
 observation);
 WIR is the wind irregularity characteristic. It is a coded value used to describe
 the wind speed as steady or gusty and the wind direction as constant or
 variable. The wind is considered to be steady if its speed remains
 essentially constant over the course of two minutes; otherwise it is
 considered gusty. The wind direction is considered constant if over the
 course of two minutes it varies within one compass point; otherwise it is
 considered to be variable. Observations of this variable are only present in
 the 6-hourly data records (i.e., in the pre-1966 data). The 3-hourly records
 (1966 onward) contain a value of 9 to indicate missing data. For the pre-
 1966 data, a value of 9 is also used to indicate a missing value. Codes for
 observations have the following meanings:
 0 = no wind;
 1 = steady speed, constant direction;
 2 = steady, variable;
 3 = gusty, constant;
 4 = gusty, variable;
 5 = characteristic is not defined;
 6 = the wind speed and direction at this hour are considered suspect.
 WIRF is the wind irregularity characteristic quality flag (0 indicates a valid
 observation; 9 indicates a suspect or missing observation).
&#239;&#187;&#191;
 &#160;&amp;middot;&#160;]]></Descriptive_file>
      <Data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/ndp048.txt]]></Data_file>
      <Data_IO_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/data.for]]></Data_IO_file>
      <Data_IO_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/data.sas]]></Data_IO_file>
      <Data_IO_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/gaps.for]]></Data_IO_file>
      <Data_IO_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/gaps.sas]]></Data_IO_file>
      <Data_IO_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/history.for]]></Data_IO_file>
      <Data_IO_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/history.sas]]></Data_IO_file>
      <Data_IO_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/invent.for]]></Data_IO_file>
      <Data_IO_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/invent.sas]]></Data_IO_file>
      <Data_IO_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/timezone.for]]></Data_IO_file>
      <Data_IO_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/timezone.sas]]></Data_IO_file>
      <Initial_date_of_data_publication><![CDATA[19950101]]></Initial_date_of_data_publication>
      <Most_recent_date_of_data_publication><![CDATA[19980301]]></Most_recent_date_of_data_publication>
      <Data_file_location><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp048/]]></Data_file_location>
      <Total_size_of_all_files><![CDATA[643MB]]></Total_size_of_all_files>
      <Distribution><![CDATA[external]]></Distribution>
      <CDIAC_contact><![CDATA[Dale Kaiser; email: kaiserdp@ornl.gov]]></CDIAC_contact>
      <Notes><![CDATA[ This database contains 6- and 3-hourly meteorological observations from a 223-station network of the former Soviet Union. These data have been made available through cooperation between the two principal climate data centers of the United States and the former Soviet Union: the National Climatic Data Center (NCDC), in Asheville, North Carolina, and the All-Russian Research Institute of Hydrometeorological Information--World Data Centre (RIHMI-WDC) in Obninsk, Russia. The first version of this database extended through the mid-1980s (ending year dependent upon station) and was made available in 1995 by the Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center (CDIAC) as NDP-048. This update of the database includes data through 1990. Station records consist of 6- and 3-hourly observations of some 24 meteorological variables including temperature, past and present weather type, precipitation amount, cloud amount and type, sea level pressure, relative humidity, and wind direction and speed. The 6-hourly observations extend from 1936 through 1965; the 3-hourly observations extend from 1966 through 1990. These data have undergone extensive quality assurance checks by RIHMI-WDC, NCDC, and CDIAC. The database represents a wealth of meteorological information for a large and climatologically important portion of the earth's land area, and should prove extremely useful for a wide variety of regional climate change studies.
<br><br>
 This numeric data package (NDP) consists of a printed document detailing the initial version of the database (Razuvaev et al. 1995) that extended through the mid-1980s, 15 updated data retrieval and documentation files, and 223 data files updated through 1990 (one per station; ~2.9 gigabytes total, in uncompressed form) that are available via the Internet through CDIAC's Web site or anonymous FTP (File Transfer Protocol) server, and upon request, various magnetic media.]]></Notes>
    </CDIAC>
  </mercury>
</metadata>
