<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin><![CDATA[Lewis, E. R.]]></origin>
        <origin><![CDATA[Wallace, D. W. R.]]></origin>
        <title><![CDATA[Program Developed for CO2 System Calculations]]></title>
        <geoform></geoform>
        <onlink><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/xml/cdp/metadata/Alex_Kozyr/CDIAC_105.xml]]></onlink>
        <onlink><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/co2sys]]></onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract><![CDATA[Program Developed for CO2 System Calculations]]></abstract>
      <supplinf></supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate><![CDATA[1900000]]></begdate>
          <enddate><![CDATA[1900000]]></enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress></progress>
      <update> As appropriate</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc></westbc>
        <eastbc></eastbc>
        <northbc></northbc>
        <southbc></southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>CDIAC</themekt>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Aragonite]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Calcite]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Fugacity]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Inorganic Carbon]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[pH]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Partial Pressure of CO2 ]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Total Alkalinity]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Total Inorganic CO2]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Freshwater]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Salt Water]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Temperature]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Phosphate]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Pressure]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Salinity]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Silicate]]></themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Thematic Area</themekt>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Place Keywords</placekt>
        <placekey></placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Alex Kozyr; email: kozyra@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntfax></cntfax>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg></cntorg>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Alex Kozyr; email: kozyra@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice></cntvoice>
        <cntfax></cntfax>
        <cntemail></cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc></resdesc>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/]]></computer>
            <accinstr></accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20050808 152403</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Alex Kozyr; email: kozyra@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice></cntvoice>
        <cntemail></cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  </metainfo>
  <Local-Control-Number>Created 20050808 152403 by 160.91.18.40</Local-Control-Number>
  <mercury>
    <begdate></begdate>
    <enddate></enddate>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Aragonite]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Calcite]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Fugacity]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Inorganic Carbon]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[pH]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Partial Pressure of CO2 ]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Total Alkalinity]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Total Inorganic CO2]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Freshwater]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Salt Water]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Temperature]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Phosphate]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Pressure]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Salinity]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Silicate]]></Keywords>
    <Documentation_Link>
      <Text><![CDATA[&#239;&#187;&#191;
By
Atmospheric Sciences Division
Brookhaven National Laboratory
Department of Oceanography
 Dalhousie University
 1355 Oxford Street
 PO BOX 15000
Prepared by
Linda J. Allison
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
Oak Ridge National Laboratory
Investigators interested in studying the ocean carbonate system are not
in complete agreement on how to calculate inorganic carbon speciation in
seawater. Over the years there have been many determinations and reviews of
the constants used to describe the dissociation of carbon dioxide (CO) in the
ocean, but no universally accepted set of constants exists. Several subtly
different pH scales remain in common use, as do variations in the definition
of total alkalinity and arguments over the relative merits of reporting the
partial pressure versus the fugacity of CO measurements become
steadily more accurate and investigators seek to evaluate very small changes
in concentrations, these issues grow in importance.
 We recently released a computer program that we hope will be of
general use and perhaps help to clear up some of the confusion. Given any two
of the four measurable carbonate system parameters, this program calculates the
other two, together with the inorganic carbon speciation and the saturation of
calcite and aragonite. The program also allows the user to select from four
different pH scales and several sets of dissociation constants widely cited in
the literature.
Run in "single input" mode, the program reports calculated results
together with the sensitivity of the calculated parameters to uncertainties in
input parameters, constants, and the like. Run in "batch input" mode, the
program can be used to process large data sets, such as cruise data derived
from spreadsheets. In writing the code we spent considerable time
cross-checking the relevant literature and checking units and scales. We are
reasonably confident that the program itself does not introduce any errors and
is consistent with the primary literature.
The program is written in compiled MICROSOFT QuickBASIC and runs under DOS on
almost any personal computer processor. As a result, the user interface is
functional but not flashy. The program includes on-line documentation as well
as a listing of typographical errors and inconsistencies culled from the literature. We may
develop a MICROSOFT Visual Basic for Applications version if the demand for it is
sufficient.
 performs calculations relating parameters of
the carbon dioxide (CO) system in seawater and freshwater. The program uses two
of the four measurable parameters of the CO system
[total alkalinity (),
total inorganic CO),
) or
partial pressure of CO)] to calculate the other
two parameters at a set of input conditions (temperature and pressure) and a set of
output conditions chosen by the user. It replaces and extends the programs
CO2SYSTM.EXE, FCO2TCO2.EXE, PHTCO2.EXE, and CO2BTCH.EXE, which were released
in May 1995. It may be run in 
or and has
a variety of options for the various constants and
parameters
section is available that includes documentation on various topics relevant
to the program. This program may be run on any 80 x 86 computer equipped with
the DOS operating system by simply typing CO2SYS at the prompt after loading
the executable file CO2SYS.EXE.
 system in seawater is characterized by four measurable
parameters: ,
TCO, the carbonate, and the
 bicarbonate),
,
and either .
 in wet (100%
water-saturated) air which is in equilibrium with the sample.
Both 
are proportional to the dissolved CO.
The fugacity is about 0.3% to 0.4% lower than the partial pressure over the
range of interest, due to the nonideality of CO are
independent
of temperature and pressure; fCO, and pH are not. The
 knowledge of any
two of these parameters, along with the temperature, salinity, pressure,
abundances of other constituents of seawater, and the relevant equilibrium
constants, allows the determination of the other two parameters.
Unfortunately, this is not as easy as it sounds. The two
definitions of in current usage differ in how minor species
are treated. Four different 
 [total, seawater, free, and NBS (National Bureau of Standards, now the
 National Institute of Standards and Technology)] are in current usage (it is even
more complicated in the literature where the
distinction between the total scale and the seawater scale has not always
been made). The situation with the equilibrium constants is potentially more
confusing: There are and
K (the first and second dissociation constants of carbonic acid in seawater) and
also several formulations for the other dissociation constants of interest, on various pH and
concentration scales.
Many of these differences are slight, but their importance is in
direct proportion to the desired precision of the calculated values. The
correction for the nonideality of CO, for instance, is only around 0.3%
under most conditions, but this correction is near the precision of some measurements
systems. The difference in the definitions of 
consists mainly in the treatment of phosphate. This difference may seem minor, but a modest phosphate
concentration, such as 3 micro-moles per kilogram of seawater
(&#181;mol/kg-SW), can result in a difference in fCO
(or pCO,
depending on the definition of alkalinity. This difference, therefore, is quite significant.
We evaluated several other programs that performed calculations
relating the seawater CO system parameters. These programs differed in the values of the
constants used and in what contributions to the alkalinity were considered. To get an
idea of the differences, we ran three programs
with the following inputs: TA = 2300 &#181;mol/kg-SW;
TCO = 2000 &#181;mol/kg-SW; no
phosphate or silicate (two of the programs did not have an option to include
these); and temperature (&#176;C), salinity [on the Practical Salinity Scale (PSS)],
and pressure (in dbar) equal to 20, 35, and 0,
respectively. The results were as follows:
 and thus are difficult
to compare. The values for pCO, though, should be the same regardless of pH
scale, as should the values for the concentrations of HCO and
CO
Closer inspection (this means looking at the codes) reveals some of
the reasons for the differences. Program 1 did not include the contribution
of OH to the alkalinity (which would be about 5 &#181;mol/kg-SW),
nor did it
include the contributions of phosphate and silicate. It used the K
values from Goyet and Poisson (1989) and the value of K from data of Khoo et al.
(1977) but refit by other investigators. It did not include a correction for the
nonideality of CO, but did include pressure corrections. Program 2 did not
include the contributions of phosphate and silicate, but did include pressure corrections and a
correction for the nonideality of CO. The values
of K were those of Roy et al. (1993), and the value of
 K was that of
Dickson (1990a). Program 3 did include the contributions of phosphate and
silicate, but had no corrections for the nonideality of CO or for pressure.
The values of K used were from Mehrbach et al. (1973). Each of the
programs used a different value for K
It can thus be seen how different programs, with no coding errors,
can yield very different results. Because of this, we decided to provide a
single program that encompassed a wide variety of system
constants, etc. in order to facilitate the assessment of the
CO
single-input mode,
and allows for a variety of options, including
,
two distinct formulations for 
(Dickson 1990a; Khoo et al. 1977), the choice of four 
 (free, total, seawater, or NBS), and the
 use of either or
 or
 pCO, and pH) may be chosen as the inputs from which the other two parameters
will be calculated. Contributions to the alkalinity from phosphate, silicate,
and OH are included, as are the 
and the nonideality of
CO section is available
 that includes discussions of the
various options and provides for the values
used and for other topics that are
relevant to the program. Every effort has been made to make this program as
correct, complete, and user-friendly as possible. However, the program is not
fail-safe, and some familiarity with the CO system in seawater is assumed.
Most of the fits to the constants are valid only over a restricted range of
salinities (mostly 20 to 40). Values outside of this range should not be
expected to yield correct results.
The units used for the variables in this program are
micro-moles per kilogram of seawater (&#181;mol/kg-SW) for concentrations of TA,
TCO, etc.;
micro-atmospheres (&#181;atm) for pCO; and parts per million (ppm) for
the mole ratio of CO in dry air. All temperatures are in &#176;C, all
salinities are on the PSS, and all pressures are in
dbar. Depth in meters may be used instead of pressure; these parameters differ by
only 3% at
10,000 dbar and less at lower pressures, well within the uncertainties of the
 on the equilibrium constants. In this program, units for the
 concentration of
[H], necessary to clearly define the pH scale, are mol/kg-SW for the total,
seawater, and free 
 (note that the original definition
in the literature for the free pH scale was in molal units), and mol/kg-HO
(molal) for the NBS scale (by definition).
Because the equilibrium constants given in the literature are on various
pH scales and in various concentration units (molar, molal, or mol/kg-SW),
it is imperative that they be converted correctly to the desired scale. In
developing this program, much work was done to ensure that these conversions were made correctly.
Data are sparse for many of the constants. The values used in this program
were those we chose to be the best from the available data. Many errors
and inconsistencies were found in the literature. In writing this program, a
list of these was compiled. This list is included as an
Appendix to this report because it may be of interest to those
involved in calculations for the carbonate system. Although most of the errors are very minor, it is
 hoped
that the use of this list will save time and effort for anyone wishing to delve further
into the topic.
 or
pCO, the
system has no solution for the given input conditions. If this situation arises in
single-input mode, the user is notified and the parameters may be re-entered.
If this occurs in batch-input mode, -999 is printed for TA, pH, and the other
calculated parameters for that sample.
The programs CO2SYSTM.EXE, FCO2TCO2.EXE, PHTCO2.EXE, and CO2BTCH.EXE were
released in May 1995. To the best of our knowledge, no serious errors have been found in these
programs. One possible problem is that the fits for the
constants are not valid for extrapolation to salinity 0.
Version 0.00, from February 1997, was only preliminary and should not be used
for calculations. The pressure corrections to the carbonate solubilities
were incorrect.
Version 1.02 was released in March 1997. The pressure corrections to the
pH scale conversions were done incorrectly. These errors had a very
minor effect in most cases.
It differs from version 1.03 only cosmetically (typographical errors were corrected, etc.).
No differences should exist between calculations performed using this version
and version 1.03.
Version 1.05 was released in October 1997.
It differs from version 1.04 cosmetically (e.g., typographical errors were corrected) and in that
some different code was used for better efficiency (no code errors were found).
No differences should exist between calculations performed using this version
and versions 1.03 and 1.04.
In single-input mode, after selection of the various options for the
values of the constants, etc., the user is prompted for the following:
system parameters are given, may be those at which measurements were performed
in the laboratory, for example, while the output conditions may refer to 
conditions. The program will use "default" values for a variable (i.e., the last value
occurring for that particular
variable, given in parentheses) when the user hits the "enter" key. These default values
may be useful for comparing the effects that various formulations of the
constants have on the calculated parameters.
 system parameters
at the input conditions. TA and TCO, which do not vary with temperature and
pressure, are used to calculate the pH and fCO at the output
conditions. Also calculated for both the input and the output conditions are:
The user may scroll forward or backwards through the various screens.
Information is available for the various
options and can be accessed while running the program.
 and the 2S (two
standard deviation) precision of the constants K to allow an estimate
to be made of the uncertainty of the final answer due to the uncertainty in
the equilibrium constants.
Batch-input mode is designed to be used with large data sets such as
files created by MICROSOFT EXCEL or other spreadsheet programs. In this mode,
data are read from an input file and results are calculated and printed to an
output file. After the various options are chosen, the user is prompted for:
 that the input data be in the correct format and that
the correct order of the CO
Units used are &#181;mol/kg-SW and &#181;atm.
 Six example data files, CASE1.INP - CASE6.INP, are included with the
program; there is one data file for each of the choices of CO system input parameters.
 Following
 is the sample data file CASE1.INP: 
 This is CASE1.INP, a test program for CO2SYS. It works for case 1.
 line1, 35., 3., 55., 20., 0, 5, 1000, 2400., 2200.
 line2, 35., 0, 0, 20, 0, 5, 1000, 2400., 2300.
 line3, 33., 2., 122., 15, 0, 5, 0, 2300., 2200.
 line4, 35., 0, 0, 20, 0, 15, 0, 2300., 2100.
 line5, 33., 3., 2., 25, 0, 10, 100, 2200., 2100.
In this example, the input data are comma-separated (this is recommended),
but they
 may also be space-separated. For space-separated data, the
ID fields be within double quotes; for comma-separated data, this is
not required. (Note that MICROSOFT EXCEL puts double quotes around each double quote
when importing a CSV file).
 It can occur that for certain inputs of TCO
 (or pCO), the
system has no solution for the given input conditions. If this occurs, -999
is printed for the TA, pH, and the other calculated parameters.
the user may define a numeric value to be the missing-value designator (MVD).
If an MVD is not defined by the user, the default value -9 will be used. IT IS
IMPERATIVE THAT A VALUE BE PROVIDED IN EACH OF THE INPUT DATA FIELDS; therefore,
unknown values should always be set equal to the MVD.
 system parameters, no
calculations will be made and each output variable will be given the value of the MVD.
If the MVD is input for one of the non-CO system parameters, a default value
will be used in calculations and that sample will be flagged (if that option has been
chosen). HOWEVER, the MVD will be printed in the output file for that
variable. OBVIOUSLY, CAUTION SHOULD BE USED IN INTERPRETING THE RESULTS WHEN
THERE ARE MISSING VALUES IN THE INPUT FILE.
The output data are comma-separated with one line per sample. Each line contains the
same fields as the input data plus the following calculated values:
, an extra field will be appended.
 This field will contain the
MVD value if there are missing data or a zero if there are no missing data.
 The pH values are reported
on the scale chosen by the user. To load the output file into MICROSOFT EXCEL, simply
open it as comma-separated with the extension "CSV".
the various dissociation constants:
the concentrations of the various species assumed to be proportional to the salinity (the concentrations of phosphate and silicate may vary and are input by the user):
These values have been determined by many different investigators in many ways.
Most assume values of temperature and salinity within ranges normally found in the oceans,
 so the use of values outside these ranges may result in fits being
extrapolated beyond the region where data were collected.
There are eight choices for the constants used in this program.
They differ mostly in the formulation of K, but there are other
slight differences as well, which are described below. These eight choices are
and concentration scales, if necessary, before calculations are made.
 in seawater, is
from Weiss
(1974), who combined the measurements of Murray and Riley (1971) with some of
his own and fit the resulting data. Estimates of the accuracy of K vary from 0.2%
(Weiss 1974) to 0.5% (Dickson and Riley 1978). The virial coefficients of
CO-air are from Weiss (1974). The vapor pressure of
HO above seawater
is from Weiss and Price (1980). The concentrations of sulfate and fluoride
are from Morris and Riley (1966) and Riley (1965), respectively. The value of
 is from either Khoo et al. (1977)
 or Dickson (1990a) (this is a choice the
user makes). Both of these are given in units of mol/kg-HO and both are (inherently)
on the free pH scale. K is from Dickson and Riley (1979). It is also (inherently)
on the free pH scale and is given in units of mol/kg-HO. Sulfate and fluoride
contribute almost nothing to the alkalinity under most circumstances, but
their concentrations and dissociation constants are important in converting
between the various . The value used for
, the activity coefficient
of the hydrogen ion (also necessary in converting between pH scales) is from
the fit given in Takahashi et al. (1982), except for the  1 represent conditions of oversaturation.
], is assumed to be proportional
to the salinity, and the carbonate concentration, [CO], is calculated
from
TCO for carbonic acid.
 For ,
 the calcium concentration used is from
Riley and Tongudai (1967). The values of K for calcite and aragonite
are from Mucci (1983). The pressure correction for K for calcite is from
Ingle (1975) and that for aragonite is from Millero (1979).
 and the
 , the concentration of calcium
is from Culkin (1965). The value of K for calcite is from Ingle (1975).
[GEOSECS had referenced Ingle et al. (1973), but this is incorrect.] The value of K for
aragonite is from Berner (1976). (Berner stated that K for aragonite is
1.48 times K for calcite; GEOSECS gave and used the value 1.45 instead of
1.48. The program CO2SYS also uses 1.45.) The pressure corrections to these
constants are from Takahashi et al. (1982). [The original reference given for
the pressure corrections is not valid, and the fit used appears to be new to
Takahashi et al. (1982).]
The equilibrium constants depend on pressure as well as on temperature
and salinity. Data are scarce on the effects of pressure on these constants
in seawater, and most values are estimated from molal volume data. Few
measurements have been made for K (of
boric acid) at only a few combinations of temperature, salinity, and pressure
in seawater (mostly in artificial seawater). All of the work assumed that ,
the activity coefficient of H (including liquid junction effects), is
independent of pressure. Some of the 
conversions do depend on pressure, however. Values of the constants should be (1) converted
to the seawater or NBS pH scale WITHOUT pressure-corrected pH scale conversions, (2)
then corrected for pressure, and (3) then converted to the desired pH scale WITH
pressure-corrected pH scale conversions. Measurements have also been made
for the effects of pressure on the solubility of calcite and aragonite in
seawater.
Depth in meters and pressure in decibars are used interchangeably
in this program. They differ by only 3% at 10,000 dbar and less at lower
pressures-well within the uncertainties of the pressure effects on the
constants. No salinity dependence of the pressure corrections is used in this
program.
, the effects
 of pressure on K
Peng et al. (1987) did not consider the effects of pressure, but they are
included in the program CO2SYS for the . For
 and
the , the effects of pressure
on the values of K,
and K was in
 Millero (1995), where it is stated that the values have been estimated from the values
of boric acid, but they are not listed in the table. In the program CO2SYS, the values used
are the same as those for the pressure effects on K given in Millero
(1995). For the effects of pressure on K, the fit given in Millero (1983) is
used. 
did not include the effects of OH, phosphate, or silicate, so
these are irrelevant for that choice.
 and the
 , the effects of pressure on
K are those given in the GEOSECS report (Takahashi et al. 1982).
The reference given there is Culberson and Pytkowicz (1968), but the fits are
actually those from Edmond and Gieskes (1970) who in turn quote Li (personal
communication). In the fit for the correction for K due to pressure, the
GEOSECS report had the value 26.4, but the value 16.4 was used, which was
consistent with their calculations as well as with the fit given in Edmond and
Gieskes (1970). The effects of pressure on the solubility of calcite and
aragonite are also those from Takahashi et al. (1982). [The original reference given
in that work for the pressure corrections is not valid and the fit used
appears to be new to Takahashi et al. (1982)].
and K are from Millero (1979) but
without the salinity dependence. These fits are from the data of Culberson
and Pytkowicz (1968). The effects of pressure on K
and K
 in Millero (1995)
include a factor of 1000 left out of the definition of Kappa and an incorrect
value and incorrect units for the gas constant R. The pressure correction for
K
 is the activity coefficient
 of the H ion
(this includes liquid junction effects),
 TS and TF are the concentrations of SO
 are the dissociation constants of
HSO
The conversions depend on temperature, salinity, and pressure.
At 20&#176;C, salinity 35, and 1 atm, pH values on the total scale are (about)
 on the NBS scale are
 mol/kg-HO. The
concentration units used in the program CO2SYS for [H] on the other scales are
mol/kg-SW (note that
the free scale was originally defined in units of mol/kg-HO). The difference
between mol/kg-SW and mol/kg-HO is about 0.015 pH units at salinity 35 (the
difference is nearly proportional to salinity). The seawater scale was
formerly referred to as the total scale, and each scale is still sometimes
referred to as the other in the literature.
 used in this program is valid from salinities 20
 to 40.
 has been found to be electrode-dependent, and does NOT equal 1 at
salinity 0 due to the liquid junction potential.
Values on the NBS pH scale are only accurate to (at best) 0.005.
 on pH has assumed
 that 
For discussions of the various pH scales see Dickson (1984, 1993),
 Millero et al. (1993), Butler (1992), or Culberson (1981). Attention
is required because in some of these references the distinction between the total and the
seawater pH scales was not made.
An information section that may be accessed from several places in the
program provides on-screen help for the following topics:
Ernie Lewis
Atmospheric Sciences Division
Environmental Sciences Department
Building 815E
Brookhaven National Laboratory
Upton, NY 11973
Tel: 631-344-7406
FAX: 631-344-2887
Douglas Wallace
Department of Oceanography
 Dalhousie University
 1355 Oxford Street
 PO BOX 15000
 Halifax NS&#194;&#160; B3H 4R2
Phone: (902) 494-4132
 system in seawater is the
Handbook of Methods for the Analysis of the Various Parameters of the Carbon
Dioxide System in Sea Water (DOE 1994). The web site for information on this reference
is: 
http://andrew.ucsd.edu/co2qc/.
A listing of the errata in this handbook is also available at this site.
A copy of the printed report may be obtained from the Carbon Dioxide Information
Analysis Center at no charge while supplies last. Requests should be addressed
to:
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
Oak Ridge National Laboratory
Post Office Box 2008
Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831-6290, U.S.A.
Telephone: (865) 574-0390 or (865) 574-3645
Fax: (865) 574-2232
Other particularly useful references are Park (1969), Skirrow (1975), Butler (1991),
Millero and Sohn (1992), and Millero (1995) (see the Appendix for a listing of some
of the errata in this paper).
The Appendix to this report lists some typographical errors found in the references for
this report as well as in other papers on this topic.
system in seawater were supplied by Dr. Andrew Dickson of Scripps Institution
of Oceanography. Many helpful comments were supplied by Dr. Rik Wanninkof of
NOAA/AOML/OCD and Dr. Dave Chipman of Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory. We would also like to
acknowledge Dr. Frank Millero of the Rosenstiel School of Marine and Atmospheric Sciences at
the University of Miami for his numerous contributions to this field.
This work was supported by the U.S. Department of Energy Office of Biological and
Enviromental Research under contract DE-ACO2-76CH00016, through a project
entitled `Inorganic Carbon for the World Ocean Circulation Experiment - World
Hydrographic Program' (D.W.R. Wallace and K.M. Johnson, PIs).
Berner, R. A. 1976. The solubility of calcite and aragonite in seawater in
atmospheric pressure and 34.5&#176;/ salinity.
Butler, J. N. 1991. Carbon Dioxide Equilibria and Their Applications. Lewis
Publishers, Inc., Chelsea, Mich. 
Butler, J. N. 1992. Alkalinity titration in seawater: How accurately can the data
be fitted by an equilibrium model? 
Culberson, C. H. 1981. Direct potentiometry. pp. 187-261. In
M. Whitfield and D. Jagner (eds.),
. John Wiley and Sons,
New York. 
Culberson, C. H., and R. M. Pytkowicz. 1968. Effect of pressure on carbonic acid,
boric acid, and the pH of seawater. 
13:403-417. 
Culkin, F. 1965. The major constituents of sea water. pp. 121-161. In J. P. Riley and
G. Skirrow (eds.), 
Dickson, A. G. 1981. An exact definition of total alkalinity and a procedure
for the estimation of alkalinity and total inorganic carbon from
titration data. 
Dickson, A. G. 1984. pH scales and proton-transfer reactions in saline media such
as sea water. 
(g) =
Ag(s) + HCl(aq), and the standard acidity constant of the ion
HSO
in synthetic seawater from 273.15 to 318.15 K. Journal of Chemical
Thermodynamics
Dickson, A. G. 1990b. Thermodynamics of the dissociation of boric acid in synthetic
seawater from 273.15 to 318.15 K. 
Dickson, A. G. 1993. pH buffers for sea water media based on the total hydrogen
concentration scale. 
Dickson, A. G., and F. J. Millero. 1987. A comparison of the equilibrium constants
for the dissociation of carbonic acid in seawater media. Deep-Sea
Research
--. 1989. Corrigenda. 
Dickson, A. G., and J. P. Riley. 1978. The effect of analytical error on the
evaluation of the components of the aquatic carbon-dioxide system.
Dickson, A. G., and J. P. Riley. 1979. The estimation of acid dissociation constants
in seawater media from potentiometric titrations with strong base.
I. The ionic product of water - K
Handbook of methods for the analysis of the
various parameters of
the carbon dioxide system in sea water. Version 2. ORNL/CDIAC-74.
A. G. Dickson and C. Goyet (eds.), Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center,
Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, Tenn. 
Edmond, J. M., and J. M. T. M. Gieskes. 1970. On the calculation of the degree of
saturation of seawater with respect to calcium carbonate under conditions.
Goyet, C., and A. Poisson. 1989. New determination of carbonic acid dissociation
constants in seawater as a function of temperature and salinity.
Hansson, I. 1973a. A new set of acidity constants for carbonic acid and boric acid
in sea water. 
Hansson, I. 1973b. The determination of dissociation constants of carbonic acid in
synthetic sea water in the salinity range of
20 - 40&#176;/ and
temperature range of 5 - 30&#176;C. 
27:931-944.
Harned, H. S., and R. Davis, Jr. 1943. The ionization constant of carbonic acid in
water and the solubility of carbon dioxide in water and aqueous salt
solutions from 0 to 50&#176;. 
65:2030-2037. 
Harned, H. S., and B. B. Owen. 1958. The Physical Chemistry of Electrolyte Solutions.
American Chemical Society Monograph Series. Reinhold Pub. Corp., New York.
from 0 to 50&#176;. 
Ingle, S. E., C. H. Culberson, J. E. Hawley, and R. M. Pytkowicz. 1973. The
solubility of calcite in seawater at atmospheric pressure
and 35&#176;/
salinity. 
Kester, D. R., and R. M. Pytkowicz. 1967. Determination of the apparent dissociation
constants of phosphoric acid in seawater. 
12:243-252. 
Khoo, K. H., R. W. Ramette, C. H. Culberson, and R. G. Bates. 1977.
Determination of hydrogen ion concentrations in seawater from 5 to
40&#176;C: standard potentials at salinities from 20 to
45&#176;/.
in the oceans. 
Mehrbach, C., C. H. Culberson, J. E. Hawley, and R. M. Pytkowicz. 1973.
Measurement of the apparent dissociation constants of carbonic acid
in seawater at atmospheric pressure. 
18:897-907.
Millero, F. J. 1979. The thermodynamics of the carbonate system in seawater.
Millero, F. J. 1983. Influence of pressure on chemical processes in the sea.
pp. 1-88. In J. P. Riley and R. Chester (eds.), .
Academic Press, New York. 
Millero, F. J. 1995. Thermodynamics of the carbon dioxide system in the oceans.
Millero, F. J., and M. L. Sohn. 1992. Chemical Oceanography. CRC Press,
Boca Raton, Fla.
Millero, F. J., J. Z. Zhang, S. Fiol, S. Sotolongo, R. N. Roy, K. Lee,
and S. Mane. 1993. The use of buffers to measure the pH of seawater.
Morris, A. W., and J. P. Riley. 1966. The bromide/chlorinity and sulphate/
chlorinity ratio in sea water. 13:699-705.
Mucci, A. 1983. The solubility of calcite and aragonite in seawater at various
salinities, temperatures, and one atmosphere total pressure.
Murray, C. N., and J. P. Riley. 1971. The solubility of gases in distilled water
and seawater - IV. Carbon dioxide. 18:533-541.
 system: an evaluation of ten methods of
investigation. 
Peng, T. H., T. Takahashi, W. S. Broecker, and J. Olafsson. 1987. Seasonal
variability of carbon dioxide, nutrients and oxygen in the northern
North Atlantic surface water: Observations and model.
Riley, J. P. 1965. The occurrence of anomalously high fluoride concentrations in
the North Atlantic. 
Riley, J. P., and M. Tongudai. 1967. The major cation/chlorinity ratios in sea
water. 
Roy, R. N., L. N. Roy, K. M. Vogel, C. Porter-Moore, T. Pearson,
C. E. Good, F. J. Millero, and D. M. Campbell. 1993. The dissociation
constants of carbonic acid in seawater at salinities 5 to 45 and
temperatures 0 to 45&#176;C. 
Sillen, L. G., A. E. Martell, and J. Bjerrum. 1964. Stability constants of metal-ion complexes,
2nd ed. Special Publication no. 17. Chemical Society (Great Britain), London.
[Referenced in Takahashi et al. 1982 as Sillen and Martel (1964).]
Skirrow, G. 1975. The dissolved gases - carbon dioxide. pp. 1-192. In
J. P. Riley and G. Skirrow (eds.), .
Academic Press, New York. 
Takahashi, T., R. T. Williams, and D. L. Bos. 1982. Carbonate chemistry.
pp. 77-83. In W. S. Broecker, D. W. Spencer, and H. Craig,
National Science Foundation, Washington, D.C. 
Uppstrom, L. R. 1974. The boron/chloronity ratio of deep-sea water from the
Pacific Ocean. 
Weiss, R. F. 1974. Carbon dioxide in water and seawater: the solubility of a
non-ideal gas. 
Weiss, R. F., and B. A. Price. 1980. Nitrous oxide solubility in water and
seawater. 
The Appendix lists errors that have been found in references for the program documentation
as well as in other papers related to this topic; however, the listing is not meant to be
 comprehensive.
 Although many corrections are extremely minor, it is hoped that this compilation will save
both time and effort for those who use it.
Campbell, D. M., F. J. Millero, R. Roy, L. Roy, M. Lawson, K. M. Vogel,
and C. Porter-Moore. 1993. The standard potential for the hydrogen-silver,
silver chloride electrode in synthetic seawater. 
44:221-233.
" should be
"log
Chen, H., R. Wanninkhof, R. A. Feely, and D. Greeley. 1995. Measurement of
fugacity of carbon dioxide in seawater: an evaluation of a method
based on infrared analysis. NOAA Technical Memorandum ERL AOML-85.
Atlantic Oceanographic and Meteorological Laboratory, Miami.
On p. 15, Table 2 states: "1. In our work (expressed in terms of the
seawater hydrogen scale):..."; however, the formula for K given is
on the total scale and the formulae for K,
and K
are on the NBS scale. It is unclear whether these formulae were converted.
On pp. 15 and 16: The formulae for Total Borate (TB) are incorrect.
They should read: "Total Borate (TB) = 0.00001188 * S" for
cases 1 and 3, and "Total Borate (TB) = 0.00001173 * S" for case 2.
/dT"
should be "d(lnXCO
Clayton, T. D., and R. H. Byrne. 1993. Spectrophotometric seawater pH measurements:
 total hydrogen ion concentration scale calibration of m-cresol
 purple and at-sea results. 
********************
Clayton, T. D., R. H. Byrne, J. A. Breland, R. A. Feely, F. J. Millero,
 D. M. Campbell, P. P. Murphy, and M. F. Lamb. 1995. The role of pH
 measurements in modern oceanic CO-system characterization: Precision
 and thermodynamic consistency. 
(g) =
 Ag(s) + HCl(aq), and the standard acidity constant of the ion
 HSO
 in synthetic seawater from 273.15 to 318.15 K. Journal of Chemical
 Thermodynamics
Dickson, A. G. 1990b. Thermodynamics of the dissociation of boric acid in synthetic
seawater from 273.15 to 318.15 K. 
."
Dickson, A. G., and F. J. Millero. 1987. A comparison of the equilibrium constants
for the dissociation of carbonic acid in seawater media.
 36:983.
*
for Hansson, the value "0.000116 *S
Also, on p. 1740 in Table 5: The second equation should read
"pK
Also, in the third equation in Table 5 on p. 1740: The term "0.00668 S" should
 be "0.0068 S."
Dickson, A. G., and J. P. Riley. 1979a. The estimation of acid dissociation constants
in seawater media from potentiometric titrations with strong base.
I. The ionic product of water - K
Dickson, A. G., and J. P. Riley. 1979b. The estimation of acid dissociation constants
in seawater media from potentiometric titrations with strong base. II.
The dissociation of phosphoric acid. 
 in
the abstract and in Table II on p. 109: The number "4.176" should be "4.196."
O."
Goyet, C., and E. Peltzer. 1994. Comparison of the August-September 1991 and 1979
surface partial pressure of CO distribution in the Equatorial
Pacific Ocean near 150&#176; W. 
Also, the reference given (UNESCO. 1987. Thermodynamics of the
carbon dioxide system in seawater. UNESCO Technical Papers
in Marine Science 51.) does not discuss this equation or the
one above it.
Goyet, C., and A. Poisson. 1989. New determination of carbonic acid dissociation
constants in seawater as a function of temperature and salinity.
On p. 1645 in Table 4: The fits which allow "extrapolation to S = 0"
contain a constant term and thus do not match the "S = 0" values.
Hansson, I. 1973a. A new set of acidity constants for carbonic acid and boric
acid in seawater. 
Lee, K., and F. J. Millero. 1995. Thermodynamic studies of the carbonate system in
seawater. 
should be proportional to "S/35," not "35/S."
 and F should be
proportional to "S/35," not "35/S."
On p. 2056, two lines up: The statement "The calculated values of
pK (S = 35)..." should NOT have the expression "(S = 35)",
as the fit has a salinity dependence.
On p. 2058: The actual title for the reference of Clayton and Byrne
is: "Spectrophotometric seawater pH measurements: total
hydrogen ion concentration scale calibration of m-cresol
purple and at-sea results."
: The expression
"log {[H}"
should be "ln {[H
: The value "114.273" should
be "114.723"
and the expression "2968/T" should be "2698/T."
, F, and B
should be proportional to "S/35," not "35/S."
Mehrbach, C., C. H. Culberson, J. E. Hawley, and R. M. Pytkowicz. 1973.
Measurement of the apparent dissociation constants of carbonic acid
in seawater at atmospheric pressure. 
18:897-907.
"
in Eq. 6.
Millero, F. 1979. The thermodynamics of the carbonate system in seawater.
Millero, F. J. 1983. Influence of pressure on chemical processes in the sea.
Chapter 43. In J. P. Riley and R. Chester (eds.), .
Academic Press, New York.
On p. 51, for Table 43.29 to be correct:
Millero, F. J. 1995. Thermodynamics of the carbon dioxide system in the oceans.
(Khoo et al. 1977), but on p. 667 it is
stated that Khoo's value is unreliable and should not be used.
This is unclear.
On p. 667: In the first full paragraph it is stated that the values of
K were determined from Eq. 30 after Roy's constants
were converted to the SWS pH scale. The value of K
is needed to convert pH scales and cannot be found from Eq. 30.
On p. 668: It is stated that the total pH scale should be used, but in
the next paragraph Roy's constants are converted to the
seawater scale, and this scale is used for most of the rest
of the paper.
On p. 669, in the title for Fig. 10: The equations are misnumbered.
Equations 46 and 47 should be Eqs. 48 and
49, and Eqs. 48 and 49 should be Eqs. 50 and 51.
 is on the total pH scale (this was not
stated but can be determined from the reference).
 is on the seawater pH scale (this wasn't
stated but is consistent with programs of Millero).
On p. 670: The given check value after Eq. 64 of "1.6 &#181;mol/kg" should be
"6.2 &#181;mol/kg." There is no easy way to see how 1.6 was obtained.
On p. 670, Eqs. 65, 66, and 67: These are on the seawater pH scale
(this was not stated, but can be determined from the DOE
Handbook).
On p. 671, after Eq. 71: The check values "0.792" and "0.204' should be
"0.852" and "0.140." If pH = 8.2 is used, or if K is increased by
a factor of 1.55, the given check values are close.
 is on the seawater pH scale (this was not stated
but can be determined from the DOE Handbook).
On p. 671, after Eq. 73: For the given values "I = .7 and "t = 25&#176;C," the value of
pK is given
as "9.47" (molality). However, when these two values are used, the actual
resultant value of
pK is "9.365" (molality) which corresponds to
"9.380" in mol/kg-soln. Two scenarios would explain the
discrepancy: (1) either "t" is incorrect (plugging in the value t = 20&#176;C
would give the value of pK as 9.47), or (2) the pH scale
is incorrect (the value of pK of 9.38 on the total pH scale
 = 9.47 on the seawater scale in the same concentration units.
 = 9.47
and pH = 7.5 yields "0.0106 [Si]," rather than
".0127 [Si]
 is given is not stated.
From the original reference, it was determined in artificial
seawater without F, so it must be on the total pH scale.
 at t = 25&#176;C
and S = 35 is incorrectly given as "6.98" and should be "6.51." The value
"6.98" can be obtained, however, by plugging in t = 25&#176;C and S = 0.
On p. 671, after Eq. 75: The value of "0.768" is consistent with the
value for pK of "6.98" (which is incorrect). The correct value
should be "0.9071."
 is given is not stated.
From the original reference it is on the seawater scale.
 of "9.19" is incorrect and
should be "9.26." It is not clear how the incorrect
value was obtained.
On p. 671, after Eq. 77: The value "0.020" is consistent with "9.19"
(which is incorrect). It should be "0.017."
." Note that
Goyet et al. (1993) in a paper on a similar topic (Goyet, C., F. J. Millero,
A. Poisson, and D. Shafer. 1993.
Temperature dependence of CO fugacity in seawater.
/TA." This
difference could cause confusion.
 at ANY temp
can be calculated exactly! The only way to know X is to know
TA AND TCO at 20&#176;C
is also sufficient to find fCO
On p. 675, after Eq. 90: The value and the units for R are incorrect.
The true value is "R = 83.145 bar-cm
On p. 675, column 1: The reference to Millero (1989) should probably
be Millero (1983b).
 in Table 9. Probably they
are equal to 0; this would be consistent with previous work.
On p. 675: The left-hand side of Equation 92 should be "(1000)* deltaK,"
or the last two columns in Table 9 should be "1000*b" and
"1000*b
for HS
are the FRESHWATER values given in Millero (1983).
. Before
the heading "Conclusions" on the same page it is stated that
they are "estimated" from those of boric acid. It is unclear whether or not it
is meant that they are assumed to be equal to those for boric acid.
 should be "+0.1622"
to agree with Millero (1979).
 for calcite and aragonite
should be "+0.5304" to agree with Millero (1979).
 for aragonite should be
"-46.0" (or "-45.96") to agree with Millero (1979).
 for calcite should be "+0.3692"
to agree with Millero (1979).
On p. 677, in column 2: There is a problem with the reference
"Millero, F. J. (1982). The thermodynamics of seawater at one
atmosphere. 
It should probably read:
Millero, F. J. (1976). The thermodynamics of seawater at one
atmosphere. 
Millero, F. J. (1982). Thermodynamics of seawater: the PVT
properties. 
Millero, F. J., T. Plese, and M. Fernandez. 1988. The dissociation of hydrogen
sulfide in seawater. 
On p. 271 just before Eq. 7: It is stated that the NBS and the
total pH scales are related by "
* [H," but this
does not include fluoride. The relation usually used is
"]
," which does include fluoride. This means that
the used in this equation is the activity coefficient
for seawater containing no fluoride.
 combines data that were taken in seawater
(artificial and actual) containing fluoride with values which were
done in artificial seawater without fluoride.
Millero, F. J., and M. L. Sohn. 1992. The carbonate system. pp. 267-319. In F. J. Millero
and M. L. Sohn, 
On p. 275: There is ambiguity and inconsistency in the definitions and
distinctions between the total and the seawater pH scales.
On p. 276: Equation 36 is incorrect in several places:
the denominator in the first expression should be squared,
and the terms CH and COH should not be in the numerator but
rather by themselves.
This expression also makes the approximation that K
 K
On p. 279: The right-hand side of Eq. 52 should read:
"pK
On p. 286: Equation 96 has brackets and parentheses missing in several
places. 
Fits for the constants are from the following sources:
 are from Dickson and Millero
(1987) from the combined data of Hansson (1973 a,b) and Mehrbach et al. (1973).
are from Millero (1979).
These are the source references:
 34:1733-1743;
see also Dickson, A. G., and F. J. Millero. 1989. 
Millero, F. J. 1983. Influence of pressure on chemical processes in the sea.Chapter 43.
In J. P. Riley and R. Chester (eds.),
Millero, F. J., J. Z. Zhang, S. Fiol, S. Sotolongo, R. N. Roy, K. Lee,
and S. Mane. 1993. The use of buffers to measure the pH of seawater.
On p. 149, Eq. 23, and on p. 150, Eqs. 25 and 27:
The multiplication sign (x) should be a division sign (/).
Millero, F. J., J. Z. Zhang, K. Lee, and D. M. Campbell. 1993. Titration
alkalinity of seawater. 
On p. 156, column 2, about 10 lines down: The expression "14&#177;1 mM" should
be "14 &#177; 1 &#181;M."
Peng, T. H., T. Takahashi, W. S. Broecker, and J. Olafsson. 1987. Seasonal
variability of carbon dioxide, nutrients and oxygen in the North
Atlantic surface water: observations and a model. 
 is NOT the same as the one in GEOSECS, as
claimed, but rather is rounded off. It is about 1% higher
(this results in a change of 0.004 in pH).
 does not match the fit given
in that paper or the GEOSECS fit.
NOTE: On p. 455, Eq. A3: This definition of TA is different from that
of Dickson; it is higher by an amount equal to the total
phosphate.
Roy, R. N., L. N. Roy, K. M. Vogel, C. Porter-Moore, T. Pearson, C. E. Good,
F. J. Millero, and D. M. Campbell. 1993. The dissociation constants
of carbonic acid in seawater at salinities 5 to 45 and temperatures 0
to 45&#176;C. 
)" should be
"2m(CO
 and "0.006"
in pK. From Andrew Dickson (personal communication, 1997)
these should be "0.008" in pK
, not Dickson's, but
reference Dickson earlier (p. 252)
 45:337.
This replaces tables 3 and 4.
 52:183.
This fixes a typographic error in the Abstract on p. 249: In the equation for lnK*: The
last term should have S raised to the power 1.5.
It also fixes a typographic error in Eq. 34 on p. 256: The value "310.48919" should be
"2310.48919."
Takahashi, T., R. T. Williams, and D. L. Bos. 1982. Carbonate chemistry. pp. 77-83.
In W. S. Broecker, D. W. Spencer, and H. Craig, GEOSECS Pacific Expedition,
Volume 3, Hydrographic Data 1973-1974. National Science Foundation,
Washington, D.C.
&#180;(P), the value "26.4"
should be "16.4."
On p. 79:The reference in No. 6. in the list of constants should actually be
Ingle, S. E. 1975.
&#180;(aragonite): The value "1.45" should be
"1.48" [this is what Berner uses on p. 722 of Berner (1976)].
On p. 79 in No. 8. in the list of constants: Reference [20] is not
correct; that Culberson reference is only indirectly related to the topic under discussion.
&#180;(calcite,P): The plus sign should be
an equals sign.
&#180;: The expression "C/lnT"
should be "C*lnT."
UNESCO. 1987. UNESCO Technical papers in marine science 51: Thermodynamics of the carbon
dioxide system in seawater. 
Weiss, R. F., and B. A. Price. 1980. Nitrous oxide solubility in water and
seawater. 
respectively, below our results."
&#239;&#187;&#191;
&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;maintained by &#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;Last modified: 28 Nov 2016]]></Text>
    </Documentation_Link>
    <OME_Software_Version>Version 4.7.2e, Revision Date: 19 Jul 2005</OME_Software_Version>
    <OME_DTD_Version>metadata10.dtd</OME_DTD_Version>
    <Temporal_Resolution></Temporal_Resolution>
    <enddate_blank></enddate_blank>
    <Harvest_Date>2017-09-01</Harvest_Date>
    <File_ID>Created 20050808 152403 by 160.91.18.40</File_ID>
    <Spatial_Extent></Spatial_Extent>
    <Metadata_URL><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/xml/cdp/metadata/Alex_Kozyr/CDIAC_105.xml]]></Metadata_URL>
    <CDIAC>
      <Product_number><![CDATA[CDIAC-105]]></Product_number>
      <Product_title><![CDATA[Program Developed for CO2 System Calculations]]></Product_title>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Lewis, E. R.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[Brookhaven National Laboratory]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[Department of Applied Science]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Wallace, D. W. R.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[Institut fuer Meereskunde]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[Abteilung Meereschemie]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Thematic_area><![CDATA[Oceanic Trace Gases]]></Thematic_area>
      <Site_info>
        <Site_name><![CDATA[Ocean]]></Site_name>
        <Site_URL><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/oceans/co2rprt.html]]></Site_URL>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/co2sys/case1.inp]]></Site_data_file>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/co2sys/case2.inp]]></Site_data_file>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/co2sys/case3.inp]]></Site_data_file>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/co2sys/case4.inp]]></Site_data_file>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/co2sys/case5.inp]]></Site_data_file>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/co2sys/case6.inp]]></Site_data_file>
      </Site_info>
      <Data_site></Data_site>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CO2 system parameters]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[phosphate]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[pressure]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[salinity]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[silicate]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[temperature]]></Variable>
      <Descriptive_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/oceans/co2rprt.html&#239;&#187;&#191;
By
Atmospheric Sciences Division
Brookhaven National Laboratory
Department of Oceanography
 Dalhousie University
 1355 Oxford Street
 PO BOX 15000
Prepared by
Linda J. Allison
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
Oak Ridge National Laboratory
Investigators interested in studying the ocean carbonate system are not
in complete agreement on how to calculate inorganic carbon speciation in
seawater. Over the years there have been many determinations and reviews of
the constants used to describe the dissociation of carbon dioxide (CO) in the
ocean, but no universally accepted set of constants exists. Several subtly
different pH scales remain in common use, as do variations in the definition
of total alkalinity and arguments over the relative merits of reporting the
partial pressure versus the fugacity of CO measurements become
steadily more accurate and investigators seek to evaluate very small changes
in concentrations, these issues grow in importance.
 We recently released a computer program that we hope will be of
general use and perhaps help to clear up some of the confusion. Given any two
of the four measurable carbonate system parameters, this program calculates the
other two, together with the inorganic carbon speciation and the saturation of
calcite and aragonite. The program also allows the user to select from four
different pH scales and several sets of dissociation constants widely cited in
the literature.
Run in "single input" mode, the program reports calculated results
together with the sensitivity of the calculated parameters to uncertainties in
input parameters, constants, and the like. Run in "batch input" mode, the
program can be used to process large data sets, such as cruise data derived
from spreadsheets. In writing the code we spent considerable time
cross-checking the relevant literature and checking units and scales. We are
reasonably confident that the program itself does not introduce any errors and
is consistent with the primary literature.
The program is written in compiled MICROSOFT QuickBASIC and runs under DOS on
almost any personal computer processor. As a result, the user interface is
functional but not flashy. The program includes on-line documentation as well
as a listing of typographical errors and inconsistencies culled from the literature. We may
develop a MICROSOFT Visual Basic for Applications version if the demand for it is
sufficient.
 performs calculations relating parameters of
the carbon dioxide (CO) system in seawater and freshwater. The program uses two
of the four measurable parameters of the CO system
[total alkalinity (),
total inorganic CO),
) or
partial pressure of CO)] to calculate the other
two parameters at a set of input conditions (temperature and pressure) and a set of
output conditions chosen by the user. It replaces and extends the programs
CO2SYSTM.EXE, FCO2TCO2.EXE, PHTCO2.EXE, and CO2BTCH.EXE, which were released
in May 1995. It may be run in 
or and has
a variety of options for the various constants and
parameters
section is available that includes documentation on various topics relevant
to the program. This program may be run on any 80 x 86 computer equipped with
the DOS operating system by simply typing CO2SYS at the prompt after loading
the executable file CO2SYS.EXE.
 system in seawater is characterized by four measurable
parameters: ,
TCO, the carbonate, and the
 bicarbonate),
,
and either .
 in wet (100%
water-saturated) air which is in equilibrium with the sample.
Both 
are proportional to the dissolved CO.
The fugacity is about 0.3% to 0.4% lower than the partial pressure over the
range of interest, due to the nonideality of CO are
independent
of temperature and pressure; fCO, and pH are not. The
 knowledge of any
two of these parameters, along with the temperature, salinity, pressure,
abundances of other constituents of seawater, and the relevant equilibrium
constants, allows the determination of the other two parameters.
Unfortunately, this is not as easy as it sounds. The two
definitions of in current usage differ in how minor species
are treated. Four different 
 [total, seawater, free, and NBS (National Bureau of Standards, now the
 National Institute of Standards and Technology)] are in current usage (it is even
more complicated in the literature where the
distinction between the total scale and the seawater scale has not always
been made). The situation with the equilibrium constants is potentially more
confusing: There are and
K (the first and second dissociation constants of carbonic acid in seawater) and
also several formulations for the other dissociation constants of interest, on various pH and
concentration scales.
Many of these differences are slight, but their importance is in
direct proportion to the desired precision of the calculated values. The
correction for the nonideality of CO, for instance, is only around 0.3%
under most conditions, but this correction is near the precision of some measurements
systems. The difference in the definitions of 
consists mainly in the treatment of phosphate. This difference may seem minor, but a modest phosphate
concentration, such as 3 micro-moles per kilogram of seawater
(&#181;mol/kg-SW), can result in a difference in fCO
(or pCO,
depending on the definition of alkalinity. This difference, therefore, is quite significant.
We evaluated several other programs that performed calculations
relating the seawater CO system parameters. These programs differed in the values of the
constants used and in what contributions to the alkalinity were considered. To get an
idea of the differences, we ran three programs
with the following inputs: TA = 2300 &#181;mol/kg-SW;
TCO = 2000 &#181;mol/kg-SW; no
phosphate or silicate (two of the programs did not have an option to include
these); and temperature (&#176;C), salinity [on the Practical Salinity Scale (PSS)],
and pressure (in dbar) equal to 20, 35, and 0,
respectively. The results were as follows:
 and thus are difficult
to compare. The values for pCO, though, should be the same regardless of pH
scale, as should the values for the concentrations of HCO and
CO
Closer inspection (this means looking at the codes) reveals some of
the reasons for the differences. Program 1 did not include the contribution
of OH to the alkalinity (which would be about 5 &#181;mol/kg-SW),
nor did it
include the contributions of phosphate and silicate. It used the K
values from Goyet and Poisson (1989) and the value of K from data of Khoo et al.
(1977) but refit by other investigators. It did not include a correction for the
nonideality of CO, but did include pressure corrections. Program 2 did not
include the contributions of phosphate and silicate, but did include pressure corrections and a
correction for the nonideality of CO. The values
of K were those of Roy et al. (1993), and the value of
 K was that of
Dickson (1990a). Program 3 did include the contributions of phosphate and
silicate, but had no corrections for the nonideality of CO or for pressure.
The values of K used were from Mehrbach et al. (1973). Each of the
programs used a different value for K
It can thus be seen how different programs, with no coding errors,
can yield very different results. Because of this, we decided to provide a
single program that encompassed a wide variety of system
constants, etc. in order to facilitate the assessment of the
CO
single-input mode,
and allows for a variety of options, including
,
two distinct formulations for 
(Dickson 1990a; Khoo et al. 1977), the choice of four 
 (free, total, seawater, or NBS), and the
 use of either or
 or
 pCO, and pH) may be chosen as the inputs from which the other two parameters
will be calculated. Contributions to the alkalinity from phosphate, silicate,
and OH are included, as are the 
and the nonideality of
CO section is available
 that includes discussions of the
various options and provides for the values
used and for other topics that are
relevant to the program. Every effort has been made to make this program as
correct, complete, and user-friendly as possible. However, the program is not
fail-safe, and some familiarity with the CO system in seawater is assumed.
Most of the fits to the constants are valid only over a restricted range of
salinities (mostly 20 to 40). Values outside of this range should not be
expected to yield correct results.
The units used for the variables in this program are
micro-moles per kilogram of seawater (&#181;mol/kg-SW) for concentrations of TA,
TCO, etc.;
micro-atmospheres (&#181;atm) for pCO; and parts per million (ppm) for
the mole ratio of CO in dry air. All temperatures are in &#176;C, all
salinities are on the PSS, and all pressures are in
dbar. Depth in meters may be used instead of pressure; these parameters differ by
only 3% at
10,000 dbar and less at lower pressures, well within the uncertainties of the
 on the equilibrium constants. In this program, units for the
 concentration of
[H], necessary to clearly define the pH scale, are mol/kg-SW for the total,
seawater, and free 
 (note that the original definition
in the literature for the free pH scale was in molal units), and mol/kg-HO
(molal) for the NBS scale (by definition).
Because the equilibrium constants given in the literature are on various
pH scales and in various concentration units (molar, molal, or mol/kg-SW),
it is imperative that they be converted correctly to the desired scale. In
developing this program, much work was done to ensure that these conversions were made correctly.
Data are sparse for many of the constants. The values used in this program
were those we chose to be the best from the available data. Many errors
and inconsistencies were found in the literature. In writing this program, a
list of these was compiled. This list is included as an
Appendix to this report because it may be of interest to those
involved in calculations for the carbonate system. Although most of the errors are very minor, it is
 hoped
that the use of this list will save time and effort for anyone wishing to delve further
into the topic.
 or
pCO, the
system has no solution for the given input conditions. If this situation arises in
single-input mode, the user is notified and the parameters may be re-entered.
If this occurs in batch-input mode, -999 is printed for TA, pH, and the other
calculated parameters for that sample.
The programs CO2SYSTM.EXE, FCO2TCO2.EXE, PHTCO2.EXE, and CO2BTCH.EXE were
released in May 1995. To the best of our knowledge, no serious errors have been found in these
programs. One possible problem is that the fits for the
constants are not valid for extrapolation to salinity 0.
Version 0.00, from February 1997, was only preliminary and should not be used
for calculations. The pressure corrections to the carbonate solubilities
were incorrect.
Version 1.02 was released in March 1997. The pressure corrections to the
pH scale conversions were done incorrectly. These errors had a very
minor effect in most cases.
It differs from version 1.03 only cosmetically (typographical errors were corrected, etc.).
No differences should exist between calculations performed using this version
and version 1.03.
Version 1.05 was released in October 1997.
It differs from version 1.04 cosmetically (e.g., typographical errors were corrected) and in that
some different code was used for better efficiency (no code errors were found).
No differences should exist between calculations performed using this version
and versions 1.03 and 1.04.
In single-input mode, after selection of the various options for the
values of the constants, etc., the user is prompted for the following:
system parameters are given, may be those at which measurements were performed
in the laboratory, for example, while the output conditions may refer to 
conditions. The program will use "default" values for a variable (i.e., the last value
occurring for that particular
variable, given in parentheses) when the user hits the "enter" key. These default values
may be useful for comparing the effects that various formulations of the
constants have on the calculated parameters.
 system parameters
at the input conditions. TA and TCO, which do not vary with temperature and
pressure, are used to calculate the pH and fCO at the output
conditions. Also calculated for both the input and the output conditions are:
The user may scroll forward or backwards through the various screens.
Information is available for the various
options and can be accessed while running the program.
 and the 2S (two
standard deviation) precision of the constants K to allow an estimate
to be made of the uncertainty of the final answer due to the uncertainty in
the equilibrium constants.
Batch-input mode is designed to be used with large data sets such as
files created by MICROSOFT EXCEL or other spreadsheet programs. In this mode,
data are read from an input file and results are calculated and printed to an
output file. After the various options are chosen, the user is prompted for:
 that the input data be in the correct format and that
the correct order of the CO
Units used are &#181;mol/kg-SW and &#181;atm.
 Six example data files, CASE1.INP - CASE6.INP, are included with the
program; there is one data file for each of the choices of CO system input parameters.
 Following
 is the sample data file CASE1.INP: 
 This is CASE1.INP, a test program for CO2SYS. It works for case 1.
 line1, 35., 3., 55., 20., 0, 5, 1000, 2400., 2200.
 line2, 35., 0, 0, 20, 0, 5, 1000, 2400., 2300.
 line3, 33., 2., 122., 15, 0, 5, 0, 2300., 2200.
 line4, 35., 0, 0, 20, 0, 15, 0, 2300., 2100.
 line5, 33., 3., 2., 25, 0, 10, 100, 2200., 2100.
In this example, the input data are comma-separated (this is recommended),
but they
 may also be space-separated. For space-separated data, the
ID fields be within double quotes; for comma-separated data, this is
not required. (Note that MICROSOFT EXCEL puts double quotes around each double quote
when importing a CSV file).
 It can occur that for certain inputs of TCO
 (or pCO), the
system has no solution for the given input conditions. If this occurs, -999
is printed for the TA, pH, and the other calculated parameters.
the user may define a numeric value to be the missing-value designator (MVD).
If an MVD is not defined by the user, the default value -9 will be used. IT IS
IMPERATIVE THAT A VALUE BE PROVIDED IN EACH OF THE INPUT DATA FIELDS; therefore,
unknown values should always be set equal to the MVD.
 system parameters, no
calculations will be made and each output variable will be given the value of the MVD.
If the MVD is input for one of the non-CO system parameters, a default value
will be used in calculations and that sample will be flagged (if that option has been
chosen). HOWEVER, the MVD will be printed in the output file for that
variable. OBVIOUSLY, CAUTION SHOULD BE USED IN INTERPRETING THE RESULTS WHEN
THERE ARE MISSING VALUES IN THE INPUT FILE.
The output data are comma-separated with one line per sample. Each line contains the
same fields as the input data plus the following calculated values:
, an extra field will be appended.
 This field will contain the
MVD value if there are missing data or a zero if there are no missing data.
 The pH values are reported
on the scale chosen by the user. To load the output file into MICROSOFT EXCEL, simply
open it as comma-separated with the extension "CSV".
the various dissociation constants:
the concentrations of the various species assumed to be proportional to the salinity (the concentrations of phosphate and silicate may vary and are input by the user):
These values have been determined by many different investigators in many ways.
Most assume values of temperature and salinity within ranges normally found in the oceans,
 so the use of values outside these ranges may result in fits being
extrapolated beyond the region where data were collected.
There are eight choices for the constants used in this program.
They differ mostly in the formulation of K, but there are other
slight differences as well, which are described below. These eight choices are
and concentration scales, if necessary, before calculations are made.
 in seawater, is
from Weiss
(1974), who combined the measurements of Murray and Riley (1971) with some of
his own and fit the resulting data. Estimates of the accuracy of K vary from 0.2%
(Weiss 1974) to 0.5% (Dickson and Riley 1978). The virial coefficients of
CO-air are from Weiss (1974). The vapor pressure of
HO above seawater
is from Weiss and Price (1980). The concentrations of sulfate and fluoride
are from Morris and Riley (1966) and Riley (1965), respectively. The value of
 is from either Khoo et al. (1977)
 or Dickson (1990a) (this is a choice the
user makes). Both of these are given in units of mol/kg-HO and both are (inherently)
on the free pH scale. K is from Dickson and Riley (1979). It is also (inherently)
on the free pH scale and is given in units of mol/kg-HO. Sulfate and fluoride
contribute almost nothing to the alkalinity under most circumstances, but
their concentrations and dissociation constants are important in converting
between the various . The value used for
, the activity coefficient
of the hydrogen ion (also necessary in converting between pH scales) is from
the fit given in Takahashi et al. (1982), except for the  1 represent conditions of oversaturation.
], is assumed to be proportional
to the salinity, and the carbonate concentration, [CO], is calculated
from
TCO for carbonic acid.
 For ,
 the calcium concentration used is from
Riley and Tongudai (1967). The values of K for calcite and aragonite
are from Mucci (1983). The pressure correction for K for calcite is from
Ingle (1975) and that for aragonite is from Millero (1979).
 and the
 , the concentration of calcium
is from Culkin (1965). The value of K for calcite is from Ingle (1975).
[GEOSECS had referenced Ingle et al. (1973), but this is incorrect.] The value of K for
aragonite is from Berner (1976). (Berner stated that K for aragonite is
1.48 times K for calcite; GEOSECS gave and used the value 1.45 instead of
1.48. The program CO2SYS also uses 1.45.) The pressure corrections to these
constants are from Takahashi et al. (1982). [The original reference given for
the pressure corrections is not valid, and the fit used appears to be new to
Takahashi et al. (1982).]
The equilibrium constants depend on pressure as well as on temperature
and salinity. Data are scarce on the effects of pressure on these constants
in seawater, and most values are estimated from molal volume data. Few
measurements have been made for K (of
boric acid) at only a few combinations of temperature, salinity, and pressure
in seawater (mostly in artificial seawater). All of the work assumed that ,
the activity coefficient of H (including liquid junction effects), is
independent of pressure. Some of the 
conversions do depend on pressure, however. Values of the constants should be (1) converted
to the seawater or NBS pH scale WITHOUT pressure-corrected pH scale conversions, (2)
then corrected for pressure, and (3) then converted to the desired pH scale WITH
pressure-corrected pH scale conversions. Measurements have also been made
for the effects of pressure on the solubility of calcite and aragonite in
seawater.
Depth in meters and pressure in decibars are used interchangeably
in this program. They differ by only 3% at 10,000 dbar and less at lower
pressures-well within the uncertainties of the pressure effects on the
constants. No salinity dependence of the pressure corrections is used in this
program.
, the effects
 of pressure on K
Peng et al. (1987) did not consider the effects of pressure, but they are
included in the program CO2SYS for the . For
 and
the , the effects of pressure
on the values of K,
and K was in
 Millero (1995), where it is stated that the values have been estimated from the values
of boric acid, but they are not listed in the table. In the program CO2SYS, the values used
are the same as those for the pressure effects on K given in Millero
(1995). For the effects of pressure on K, the fit given in Millero (1983) is
used. 
did not include the effects of OH, phosphate, or silicate, so
these are irrelevant for that choice.
 and the
 , the effects of pressure on
K are those given in the GEOSECS report (Takahashi et al. 1982).
The reference given there is Culberson and Pytkowicz (1968), but the fits are
actually those from Edmond and Gieskes (1970) who in turn quote Li (personal
communication). In the fit for the correction for K due to pressure, the
GEOSECS report had the value 26.4, but the value 16.4 was used, which was
consistent with their calculations as well as with the fit given in Edmond and
Gieskes (1970). The effects of pressure on the solubility of calcite and
aragonite are also those from Takahashi et al. (1982). [The original reference given
in that work for the pressure corrections is not valid and the fit used
appears to be new to Takahashi et al. (1982)].
and K are from Millero (1979) but
without the salinity dependence. These fits are from the data of Culberson
and Pytkowicz (1968). The effects of pressure on K
and K
 in Millero (1995)
include a factor of 1000 left out of the definition of Kappa and an incorrect
value and incorrect units for the gas constant R. The pressure correction for
K
 is the activity coefficient
 of the H ion
(this includes liquid junction effects),
 TS and TF are the concentrations of SO
 are the dissociation constants of
HSO
The conversions depend on temperature, salinity, and pressure.
At 20&#176;C, salinity 35, and 1 atm, pH values on the total scale are (about)
 on the NBS scale are
 mol/kg-HO. The
concentration units used in the program CO2SYS for [H] on the other scales are
mol/kg-SW (note that
the free scale was originally defined in units of mol/kg-HO). The difference
between mol/kg-SW and mol/kg-HO is about 0.015 pH units at salinity 35 (the
difference is nearly proportional to salinity). The seawater scale was
formerly referred to as the total scale, and each scale is still sometimes
referred to as the other in the literature.
 used in this program is valid from salinities 20
 to 40.
 has been found to be electrode-dependent, and does NOT equal 1 at
salinity 0 due to the liquid junction potential.
Values on the NBS pH scale are only accurate to (at best) 0.005.
 on pH has assumed
 that 
For discussions of the various pH scales see Dickson (1984, 1993),
 Millero et al. (1993), Butler (1992), or Culberson (1981). Attention
is required because in some of these references the distinction between the total and the
seawater pH scales was not made.
An information section that may be accessed from several places in the
program provides on-screen help for the following topics:
Ernie Lewis
Atmospheric Sciences Division
Environmental Sciences Department
Building 815E
Brookhaven National Laboratory
Upton, NY 11973
Tel: 631-344-7406
FAX: 631-344-2887
Douglas Wallace
Department of Oceanography
 Dalhousie University
 1355 Oxford Street
 PO BOX 15000
 Halifax NS&#194;&#160; B3H 4R2
Phone: (902) 494-4132
 system in seawater is the
Handbook of Methods for the Analysis of the Various Parameters of the Carbon
Dioxide System in Sea Water (DOE 1994). The web site for information on this reference
is: 
http://andrew.ucsd.edu/co2qc/.
A listing of the errata in this handbook is also available at this site.
A copy of the printed report may be obtained from the Carbon Dioxide Information
Analysis Center at no charge while supplies last. Requests should be addressed
to:
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
Oak Ridge National Laboratory
Post Office Box 2008
Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831-6290, U.S.A.
Telephone: (865) 574-0390 or (865) 574-3645
Fax: (865) 574-2232
Other particularly useful references are Park (1969), Skirrow (1975), Butler (1991),
Millero and Sohn (1992), and Millero (1995) (see the Appendix for a listing of some
of the errata in this paper).
The Appendix to this report lists some typographical errors found in the references for
this report as well as in other papers on this topic.
system in seawater were supplied by Dr. Andrew Dickson of Scripps Institution
of Oceanography. Many helpful comments were supplied by Dr. Rik Wanninkof of
NOAA/AOML/OCD and Dr. Dave Chipman of Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory. We would also like to
acknowledge Dr. Frank Millero of the Rosenstiel School of Marine and Atmospheric Sciences at
the University of Miami for his numerous contributions to this field.
This work was supported by the U.S. Department of Energy Office of Biological and
Enviromental Research under contract DE-ACO2-76CH00016, through a project
entitled `Inorganic Carbon for the World Ocean Circulation Experiment - World
Hydrographic Program' (D.W.R. Wallace and K.M. Johnson, PIs).
Berner, R. A. 1976. The solubility of calcite and aragonite in seawater in
atmospheric pressure and 34.5&#176;/ salinity.
Butler, J. N. 1991. Carbon Dioxide Equilibria and Their Applications. Lewis
Publishers, Inc., Chelsea, Mich. 
Butler, J. N. 1992. Alkalinity titration in seawater: How accurately can the data
be fitted by an equilibrium model? 
Culberson, C. H. 1981. Direct potentiometry. pp. 187-261. In
M. Whitfield and D. Jagner (eds.),
. John Wiley and Sons,
New York. 
Culberson, C. H., and R. M. Pytkowicz. 1968. Effect of pressure on carbonic acid,
boric acid, and the pH of seawater. 
13:403-417. 
Culkin, F. 1965. The major constituents of sea water. pp. 121-161. In J. P. Riley and
G. Skirrow (eds.), 
Dickson, A. G. 1981. An exact definition of total alkalinity and a procedure
for the estimation of alkalinity and total inorganic carbon from
titration data. 
Dickson, A. G. 1984. pH scales and proton-transfer reactions in saline media such
as sea water. 
(g) =
Ag(s) + HCl(aq), and the standard acidity constant of the ion
HSO
in synthetic seawater from 273.15 to 318.15 K. Journal of Chemical
Thermodynamics
Dickson, A. G. 1990b. Thermodynamics of the dissociation of boric acid in synthetic
seawater from 273.15 to 318.15 K. 
Dickson, A. G. 1993. pH buffers for sea water media based on the total hydrogen
concentration scale. 
Dickson, A. G., and F. J. Millero. 1987. A comparison of the equilibrium constants
for the dissociation of carbonic acid in seawater media. Deep-Sea
Research
--. 1989. Corrigenda. 
Dickson, A. G., and J. P. Riley. 1978. The effect of analytical error on the
evaluation of the components of the aquatic carbon-dioxide system.
Dickson, A. G., and J. P. Riley. 1979. The estimation of acid dissociation constants
in seawater media from potentiometric titrations with strong base.
I. The ionic product of water - K
Handbook of methods for the analysis of the
various parameters of
the carbon dioxide system in sea water. Version 2. ORNL/CDIAC-74.
A. G. Dickson and C. Goyet (eds.), Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center,
Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, Tenn. 
Edmond, J. M., and J. M. T. M. Gieskes. 1970. On the calculation of the degree of
saturation of seawater with respect to calcium carbonate under conditions.
Goyet, C., and A. Poisson. 1989. New determination of carbonic acid dissociation
constants in seawater as a function of temperature and salinity.
Hansson, I. 1973a. A new set of acidity constants for carbonic acid and boric acid
in sea water. 
Hansson, I. 1973b. The determination of dissociation constants of carbonic acid in
synthetic sea water in the salinity range of
20 - 40&#176;/ and
temperature range of 5 - 30&#176;C. 
27:931-944.
Harned, H. S., and R. Davis, Jr. 1943. The ionization constant of carbonic acid in
water and the solubility of carbon dioxide in water and aqueous salt
solutions from 0 to 50&#176;. 
65:2030-2037. 
Harned, H. S., and B. B. Owen. 1958. The Physical Chemistry of Electrolyte Solutions.
American Chemical Society Monograph Series. Reinhold Pub. Corp., New York.
from 0 to 50&#176;. 
Ingle, S. E., C. H. Culberson, J. E. Hawley, and R. M. Pytkowicz. 1973. The
solubility of calcite in seawater at atmospheric pressure
and 35&#176;/
salinity. 
Kester, D. R., and R. M. Pytkowicz. 1967. Determination of the apparent dissociation
constants of phosphoric acid in seawater. 
12:243-252. 
Khoo, K. H., R. W. Ramette, C. H. Culberson, and R. G. Bates. 1977.
Determination of hydrogen ion concentrations in seawater from 5 to
40&#176;C: standard potentials at salinities from 20 to
45&#176;/.
in the oceans. 
Mehrbach, C., C. H. Culberson, J. E. Hawley, and R. M. Pytkowicz. 1973.
Measurement of the apparent dissociation constants of carbonic acid
in seawater at atmospheric pressure. 
18:897-907.
Millero, F. J. 1979. The thermodynamics of the carbonate system in seawater.
Millero, F. J. 1983. Influence of pressure on chemical processes in the sea.
pp. 1-88. In J. P. Riley and R. Chester (eds.), .
Academic Press, New York. 
Millero, F. J. 1995. Thermodynamics of the carbon dioxide system in the oceans.
Millero, F. J., and M. L. Sohn. 1992. Chemical Oceanography. CRC Press,
Boca Raton, Fla.
Millero, F. J., J. Z. Zhang, S. Fiol, S. Sotolongo, R. N. Roy, K. Lee,
and S. Mane. 1993. The use of buffers to measure the pH of seawater.
Morris, A. W., and J. P. Riley. 1966. The bromide/chlorinity and sulphate/
chlorinity ratio in sea water. 13:699-705.
Mucci, A. 1983. The solubility of calcite and aragonite in seawater at various
salinities, temperatures, and one atmosphere total pressure.
Murray, C. N., and J. P. Riley. 1971. The solubility of gases in distilled water
and seawater - IV. Carbon dioxide. 18:533-541.
 system: an evaluation of ten methods of
investigation. 
Peng, T. H., T. Takahashi, W. S. Broecker, and J. Olafsson. 1987. Seasonal
variability of carbon dioxide, nutrients and oxygen in the northern
North Atlantic surface water: Observations and model.
Riley, J. P. 1965. The occurrence of anomalously high fluoride concentrations in
the North Atlantic. 
Riley, J. P., and M. Tongudai. 1967. The major cation/chlorinity ratios in sea
water. 
Roy, R. N., L. N. Roy, K. M. Vogel, C. Porter-Moore, T. Pearson,
C. E. Good, F. J. Millero, and D. M. Campbell. 1993. The dissociation
constants of carbonic acid in seawater at salinities 5 to 45 and
temperatures 0 to 45&#176;C. 
Sillen, L. G., A. E. Martell, and J. Bjerrum. 1964. Stability constants of metal-ion complexes,
2nd ed. Special Publication no. 17. Chemical Society (Great Britain), London.
[Referenced in Takahashi et al. 1982 as Sillen and Martel (1964).]
Skirrow, G. 1975. The dissolved gases - carbon dioxide. pp. 1-192. In
J. P. Riley and G. Skirrow (eds.), .
Academic Press, New York. 
Takahashi, T., R. T. Williams, and D. L. Bos. 1982. Carbonate chemistry.
pp. 77-83. In W. S. Broecker, D. W. Spencer, and H. Craig,
National Science Foundation, Washington, D.C. 
Uppstrom, L. R. 1974. The boron/chloronity ratio of deep-sea water from the
Pacific Ocean. 
Weiss, R. F. 1974. Carbon dioxide in water and seawater: the solubility of a
non-ideal gas. 
Weiss, R. F., and B. A. Price. 1980. Nitrous oxide solubility in water and
seawater. 
The Appendix lists errors that have been found in references for the program documentation
as well as in other papers related to this topic; however, the listing is not meant to be
 comprehensive.
 Although many corrections are extremely minor, it is hoped that this compilation will save
both time and effort for those who use it.
Campbell, D. M., F. J. Millero, R. Roy, L. Roy, M. Lawson, K. M. Vogel,
and C. Porter-Moore. 1993. The standard potential for the hydrogen-silver,
silver chloride electrode in synthetic seawater. 
44:221-233.
" should be
"log
Chen, H., R. Wanninkhof, R. A. Feely, and D. Greeley. 1995. Measurement of
fugacity of carbon dioxide in seawater: an evaluation of a method
based on infrared analysis. NOAA Technical Memorandum ERL AOML-85.
Atlantic Oceanographic and Meteorological Laboratory, Miami.
On p. 15, Table 2 states: "1. In our work (expressed in terms of the
seawater hydrogen scale):..."; however, the formula for K given is
on the total scale and the formulae for K,
and K
are on the NBS scale. It is unclear whether these formulae were converted.
On pp. 15 and 16: The formulae for Total Borate (TB) are incorrect.
They should read: "Total Borate (TB) = 0.00001188 * S" for
cases 1 and 3, and "Total Borate (TB) = 0.00001173 * S" for case 2.
/dT"
should be "d(lnXCO
Clayton, T. D., and R. H. Byrne. 1993. Spectrophotometric seawater pH measurements:
 total hydrogen ion concentration scale calibration of m-cresol
 purple and at-sea results. 
********************
Clayton, T. D., R. H. Byrne, J. A. Breland, R. A. Feely, F. J. Millero,
 D. M. Campbell, P. P. Murphy, and M. F. Lamb. 1995. The role of pH
 measurements in modern oceanic CO-system characterization: Precision
 and thermodynamic consistency. 
(g) =
 Ag(s) + HCl(aq), and the standard acidity constant of the ion
 HSO
 in synthetic seawater from 273.15 to 318.15 K. Journal of Chemical
 Thermodynamics
Dickson, A. G. 1990b. Thermodynamics of the dissociation of boric acid in synthetic
seawater from 273.15 to 318.15 K. 
."
Dickson, A. G., and F. J. Millero. 1987. A comparison of the equilibrium constants
for the dissociation of carbonic acid in seawater media.
 36:983.
*
for Hansson, the value "0.000116 *S
Also, on p. 1740 in Table 5: The second equation should read
"pK
Also, in the third equation in Table 5 on p. 1740: The term "0.00668 S" should
 be "0.0068 S."
Dickson, A. G., and J. P. Riley. 1979a. The estimation of acid dissociation constants
in seawater media from potentiometric titrations with strong base.
I. The ionic product of water - K
Dickson, A. G., and J. P. Riley. 1979b. The estimation of acid dissociation constants
in seawater media from potentiometric titrations with strong base. II.
The dissociation of phosphoric acid. 
 in
the abstract and in Table II on p. 109: The number "4.176" should be "4.196."
O."
Goyet, C., and E. Peltzer. 1994. Comparison of the August-September 1991 and 1979
surface partial pressure of CO distribution in the Equatorial
Pacific Ocean near 150&#176; W. 
Also, the reference given (UNESCO. 1987. Thermodynamics of the
carbon dioxide system in seawater. UNESCO Technical Papers
in Marine Science 51.) does not discuss this equation or the
one above it.
Goyet, C., and A. Poisson. 1989. New determination of carbonic acid dissociation
constants in seawater as a function of temperature and salinity.
On p. 1645 in Table 4: The fits which allow "extrapolation to S = 0"
contain a constant term and thus do not match the "S = 0" values.
Hansson, I. 1973a. A new set of acidity constants for carbonic acid and boric
acid in seawater. 
Lee, K., and F. J. Millero. 1995. Thermodynamic studies of the carbonate system in
seawater. 
should be proportional to "S/35," not "35/S."
 and F should be
proportional to "S/35," not "35/S."
On p. 2056, two lines up: The statement "The calculated values of
pK (S = 35)..." should NOT have the expression "(S = 35)",
as the fit has a salinity dependence.
On p. 2058: The actual title for the reference of Clayton and Byrne
is: "Spectrophotometric seawater pH measurements: total
hydrogen ion concentration scale calibration of m-cresol
purple and at-sea results."
: The expression
"log {[H}"
should be "ln {[H
: The value "114.273" should
be "114.723"
and the expression "2968/T" should be "2698/T."
, F, and B
should be proportional to "S/35," not "35/S."
Mehrbach, C., C. H. Culberson, J. E. Hawley, and R. M. Pytkowicz. 1973.
Measurement of the apparent dissociation constants of carbonic acid
in seawater at atmospheric pressure. 
18:897-907.
"
in Eq. 6.
Millero, F. 1979. The thermodynamics of the carbonate system in seawater.
Millero, F. J. 1983. Influence of pressure on chemical processes in the sea.
Chapter 43. In J. P. Riley and R. Chester (eds.), .
Academic Press, New York.
On p. 51, for Table 43.29 to be correct:
Millero, F. J. 1995. Thermodynamics of the carbon dioxide system in the oceans.
(Khoo et al. 1977), but on p. 667 it is
stated that Khoo's value is unreliable and should not be used.
This is unclear.
On p. 667: In the first full paragraph it is stated that the values of
K were determined from Eq. 30 after Roy's constants
were converted to the SWS pH scale. The value of K
is needed to convert pH scales and cannot be found from Eq. 30.
On p. 668: It is stated that the total pH scale should be used, but in
the next paragraph Roy's constants are converted to the
seawater scale, and this scale is used for most of the rest
of the paper.
On p. 669, in the title for Fig. 10: The equations are misnumbered.
Equations 46 and 47 should be Eqs. 48 and
49, and Eqs. 48 and 49 should be Eqs. 50 and 51.
 is on the total pH scale (this was not
stated but can be determined from the reference).
 is on the seawater pH scale (this wasn't
stated but is consistent with programs of Millero).
On p. 670: The given check value after Eq. 64 of "1.6 &#181;mol/kg" should be
"6.2 &#181;mol/kg." There is no easy way to see how 1.6 was obtained.
On p. 670, Eqs. 65, 66, and 67: These are on the seawater pH scale
(this was not stated, but can be determined from the DOE
Handbook).
On p. 671, after Eq. 71: The check values "0.792" and "0.204' should be
"0.852" and "0.140." If pH = 8.2 is used, or if K is increased by
a factor of 1.55, the given check values are close.
 is on the seawater pH scale (this was not stated
but can be determined from the DOE Handbook).
On p. 671, after Eq. 73: For the given values "I = .7 and "t = 25&#176;C," the value of
pK is given
as "9.47" (molality). However, when these two values are used, the actual
resultant value of
pK is "9.365" (molality) which corresponds to
"9.380" in mol/kg-soln. Two scenarios would explain the
discrepancy: (1) either "t" is incorrect (plugging in the value t = 20&#176;C
would give the value of pK as 9.47), or (2) the pH scale
is incorrect (the value of pK of 9.38 on the total pH scale
 = 9.47 on the seawater scale in the same concentration units.
 = 9.47
and pH = 7.5 yields "0.0106 [Si]," rather than
".0127 [Si]
 is given is not stated.
From the original reference, it was determined in artificial
seawater without F, so it must be on the total pH scale.
 at t = 25&#176;C
and S = 35 is incorrectly given as "6.98" and should be "6.51." The value
"6.98" can be obtained, however, by plugging in t = 25&#176;C and S = 0.
On p. 671, after Eq. 75: The value of "0.768" is consistent with the
value for pK of "6.98" (which is incorrect). The correct value
should be "0.9071."
 is given is not stated.
From the original reference it is on the seawater scale.
 of "9.19" is incorrect and
should be "9.26." It is not clear how the incorrect
value was obtained.
On p. 671, after Eq. 77: The value "0.020" is consistent with "9.19"
(which is incorrect). It should be "0.017."
." Note that
Goyet et al. (1993) in a paper on a similar topic (Goyet, C., F. J. Millero,
A. Poisson, and D. Shafer. 1993.
Temperature dependence of CO fugacity in seawater.
/TA." This
difference could cause confusion.
 at ANY temp
can be calculated exactly! The only way to know X is to know
TA AND TCO at 20&#176;C
is also sufficient to find fCO
On p. 675, after Eq. 90: The value and the units for R are incorrect.
The true value is "R = 83.145 bar-cm
On p. 675, column 1: The reference to Millero (1989) should probably
be Millero (1983b).
 in Table 9. Probably they
are equal to 0; this would be consistent with previous work.
On p. 675: The left-hand side of Equation 92 should be "(1000)* deltaK,"
or the last two columns in Table 9 should be "1000*b" and
"1000*b
for HS
are the FRESHWATER values given in Millero (1983).
. Before
the heading "Conclusions" on the same page it is stated that
they are "estimated" from those of boric acid. It is unclear whether or not it
is meant that they are assumed to be equal to those for boric acid.
 should be "+0.1622"
to agree with Millero (1979).
 for calcite and aragonite
should be "+0.5304" to agree with Millero (1979).
 for aragonite should be
"-46.0" (or "-45.96") to agree with Millero (1979).
 for calcite should be "+0.3692"
to agree with Millero (1979).
On p. 677, in column 2: There is a problem with the reference
"Millero, F. J. (1982). The thermodynamics of seawater at one
atmosphere. 
It should probably read:
Millero, F. J. (1976). The thermodynamics of seawater at one
atmosphere. 
Millero, F. J. (1982). Thermodynamics of seawater: the PVT
properties. 
Millero, F. J., T. Plese, and M. Fernandez. 1988. The dissociation of hydrogen
sulfide in seawater. 
On p. 271 just before Eq. 7: It is stated that the NBS and the
total pH scales are related by "
* [H," but this
does not include fluoride. The relation usually used is
"]
," which does include fluoride. This means that
the used in this equation is the activity coefficient
for seawater containing no fluoride.
 combines data that were taken in seawater
(artificial and actual) containing fluoride with values which were
done in artificial seawater without fluoride.
Millero, F. J., and M. L. Sohn. 1992. The carbonate system. pp. 267-319. In F. J. Millero
and M. L. Sohn, 
On p. 275: There is ambiguity and inconsistency in the definitions and
distinctions between the total and the seawater pH scales.
On p. 276: Equation 36 is incorrect in several places:
the denominator in the first expression should be squared,
and the terms CH and COH should not be in the numerator but
rather by themselves.
This expression also makes the approximation that K
 K
On p. 279: The right-hand side of Eq. 52 should read:
"pK
On p. 286: Equation 96 has brackets and parentheses missing in several
places. 
Fits for the constants are from the following sources:
 are from Dickson and Millero
(1987) from the combined data of Hansson (1973 a,b) and Mehrbach et al. (1973).
are from Millero (1979).
These are the source references:
 34:1733-1743;
see also Dickson, A. G., and F. J. Millero. 1989. 
Millero, F. J. 1983. Influence of pressure on chemical processes in the sea.Chapter 43.
In J. P. Riley and R. Chester (eds.),
Millero, F. J., J. Z. Zhang, S. Fiol, S. Sotolongo, R. N. Roy, K. Lee,
and S. Mane. 1993. The use of buffers to measure the pH of seawater.
On p. 149, Eq. 23, and on p. 150, Eqs. 25 and 27:
The multiplication sign (x) should be a division sign (/).
Millero, F. J., J. Z. Zhang, K. Lee, and D. M. Campbell. 1993. Titration
alkalinity of seawater. 
On p. 156, column 2, about 10 lines down: The expression "14&#177;1 mM" should
be "14 &#177; 1 &#181;M."
Peng, T. H., T. Takahashi, W. S. Broecker, and J. Olafsson. 1987. Seasonal
variability of carbon dioxide, nutrients and oxygen in the North
Atlantic surface water: observations and a model. 
 is NOT the same as the one in GEOSECS, as
claimed, but rather is rounded off. It is about 1% higher
(this results in a change of 0.004 in pH).
 does not match the fit given
in that paper or the GEOSECS fit.
NOTE: On p. 455, Eq. A3: This definition of TA is different from that
of Dickson; it is higher by an amount equal to the total
phosphate.
Roy, R. N., L. N. Roy, K. M. Vogel, C. Porter-Moore, T. Pearson, C. E. Good,
F. J. Millero, and D. M. Campbell. 1993. The dissociation constants
of carbonic acid in seawater at salinities 5 to 45 and temperatures 0
to 45&#176;C. 
)" should be
"2m(CO
 and "0.006"
in pK. From Andrew Dickson (personal communication, 1997)
these should be "0.008" in pK
, not Dickson's, but
reference Dickson earlier (p. 252)
 45:337.
This replaces tables 3 and 4.
 52:183.
This fixes a typographic error in the Abstract on p. 249: In the equation for lnK*: The
last term should have S raised to the power 1.5.
It also fixes a typographic error in Eq. 34 on p. 256: The value "310.48919" should be
"2310.48919."
Takahashi, T., R. T. Williams, and D. L. Bos. 1982. Carbonate chemistry. pp. 77-83.
In W. S. Broecker, D. W. Spencer, and H. Craig, GEOSECS Pacific Expedition,
Volume 3, Hydrographic Data 1973-1974. National Science Foundation,
Washington, D.C.
&#180;(P), the value "26.4"
should be "16.4."
On p. 79:The reference in No. 6. in the list of constants should actually be
Ingle, S. E. 1975.
&#180;(aragonite): The value "1.45" should be
"1.48" [this is what Berner uses on p. 722 of Berner (1976)].
On p. 79 in No. 8. in the list of constants: Reference [20] is not
correct; that Culberson reference is only indirectly related to the topic under discussion.
&#180;(calcite,P): The plus sign should be
an equals sign.
&#180;: The expression "C/lnT"
should be "C*lnT."
UNESCO. 1987. UNESCO Technical papers in marine science 51: Thermodynamics of the carbon
dioxide system in seawater. 
Weiss, R. F., and B. A. Price. 1980. Nitrous oxide solubility in water and
seawater. 
respectively, below our results."
&#239;&#187;&#191;
&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;&#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;maintained by &#160;
&#160;|&#160;
&#160;Last modified: 28 Nov 2016]]></Descriptive_file>
      <Data_file></Data_file>
      <Data_IO_file><![CDATA[co2sys.exe]]></Data_IO_file>
      <Initial_date_of_data_publication><![CDATA[19980101]]></Initial_date_of_data_publication>
      <Most_recent_date_of_data_publication><![CDATA[19980101]]></Most_recent_date_of_data_publication>
      <Data_file_location><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/co2sys]]></Data_file_location>
      <Total_size_of_all_files><![CDATA[271 KB]]></Total_size_of_all_files>
      <Distribution><![CDATA[external]]></Distribution>
      <CDIAC_contact><![CDATA[Alex Kozyr; email: kozyra@ornl.gov]]></CDIAC_contact>
      <Notes><![CDATA[ The program CO2SYS performs calculations relating parameters of the carbon dioxide (CO2) system in seawater and freshwater. The program uses two of the four measurable parameters of the CO2 system [total alkalinity (TA), total inorganic CO2 (TCO2), pH, and either fugacity (fCO2) or partial pressure of CO2 (pCO2)] to calculate the other two parameters at a set of input conditions (temperature and pressure) and a set of output conditions chosen by the user. It replaces and extends the programs CO2SYSTM.EXE, FCO2TCO2.EXE, PHTCO2.EXE, and CO2BTCH.EXE, which were released in May 1995. It may be run in single-input mode or batch-input mode and has a variety of options for the various constants and parameters used. An on-screen information section is available that includes documentation on various topics relevant to the program. This program may be run on any 80 x 86 computer equipped with the DOS operating system by simply typing CO2SYS at the prompt after loading the executable file CO2SYS.EXE.]]></Notes>
    </CDIAC>
  </mercury>
</metadata>
