<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin><![CDATA[Hahn, C. J.]]></origin>
        <origin><![CDATA[Warren, S. G.]]></origin>
        <origin><![CDATA[London, J.]]></origin>
        <title><![CDATA[Edited Synoptic Cloud Reports From Ships and Land Stations over the Globe, 1982-1991 (NDP-026B)]]></title>
        <geoform></geoform>
        <onlink><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/xml/cdp/metadata/Dale_Kaiser/NDP_026b.xml]]></onlink>
        <onlink><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp026b/]]></onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract><![CDATA[Edited Synoptic Cloud Reports From Ships and Land Stations over the Globe, 1982-1991 (NDP-026B)]]></abstract>
      <supplinf></supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate><![CDATA[19811201]]></begdate>
          <enddate><![CDATA[19911130]]></enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress></progress>
      <update> As appropriate</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc><![CDATA[1.000]]></westbc>
        <eastbc><![CDATA[-1.000]]></eastbc>
        <northbc><![CDATA[80.620]]></northbc>
        <southbc><![CDATA[-75.490]]></southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>CDIAC</themekt>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Change Code]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Cloud Amount]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Cloud Base Height]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Cloud Type]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Day]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Hour]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Land/Ocean Indicator]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Latitude]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Longitude]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Month]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Present Weather]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Relative Lunar Illuminance]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Sky Brightness Indicator]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Solar Altitude]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Source Deck]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Station Number]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Total Cloud Cover]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Year]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[NDP-026B]]></themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Thematic Area</themekt>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Place Keywords</placekt>
        <placekey></placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Dale Kaiser; email: kaiserdp@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntfax></cntfax>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg></cntorg>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Dale Kaiser; email: kaiserdp@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice></cntvoice>
        <cntfax></cntfax>
        <cntemail></cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc></resdesc>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/]]></computer>
            <accinstr></accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20120924 165006</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Dale Kaiser; email: kaiserdp@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice></cntvoice>
        <cntemail></cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  </metainfo>
  <Local-Control-Number>Created 20050808 163356 by 160.91.18.40</Local-Control-Number>
  <mercury>
    <begdate></begdate>
    <enddate></enddate>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Change Code]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Cloud Amount]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Cloud Base Height]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Cloud Type]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Day]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Hour]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Land/Ocean Indicator]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Latitude]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Longitude]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Month]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Present Weather]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Relative Lunar Illuminance]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Sky Brightness Indicator]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Solar Altitude]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Source Deck]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Station Number]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Total Cloud Cover]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Year]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[NDP-026B]]></Keywords>
    <Documentation_Link>
      <Text><![CDATA[
Download the of NDP-026B
Download 
 of NDP-026B
FROM SHIPS AND LAND STATIONS OVER THE GLOBE, 1982-1991
Carole J. Hahn
Department of Atmospheric Sciences
Tucson, AZ 85721
Stephen G. Warren
Department of Atmospheric Sciences
Seattle, WA 98195
Julius London
Department of Astrophysical, Planetary and
Atmospheric Sciences
Boulder, CO 80309
Publication No. 4367
Date Published: February 1996
Printed for the
Global Change Research Program
Environmental Sciences Division
Office of Health and Environmental Research
(KP 05 02 00 0)
Printed by the
Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831-6290
managed by
for the
U.S. DEPARTMENT OF ENERGY
under contract DE-AC05-96OR22464
2b. Frequency distribution of extended code values for indicated cloud variables
 in edited light 
, Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center,
Oak Ridge National Laboratory,
 Surface synoptic weather reports for the entire globe for the 10-year period from December 1981
through November 1991 have been processed, edited, and rewritten to provide a data set designed for use
in cloud analyses. The information in these reports relating to clouds, including the present weather
information, was extracted and put through a series of quality control checks. Reports not meeting certain
quality control standards were rejected, as were reports from buoys and automatic weather stations.
Correctable inconsistencies within reports were edited for consistency, so that the "edited cloud report" can
be used for cloud analysis without further quality checking. Cases of "sky obscured" were interpreted by
reference to the present weather code as to whether they indicated fog, rain or snow and were given
appropriate cloud type designations. Nimbostratus clouds, which are not specifically coded for in the
standard synoptic code, were also given a special designation. Changes made to an original report are
indicated in the edited report so that the original report can be reconstructed if desired. While low cloud
amount is normally given directly in the synoptic report, the edited cloud report also includes the amounts,
either directly reported or inferred, of middle and high clouds, both the non-overlapped amounts and the
"actual" amounts (which may be overlapped). Since illumination from the moon is important for the
adequate detection of clouds at night, both the relative lunar illuminance and the solar altitude are given, as
well as a parameter that indicates whether our recommended illuminance criterion was satisfied.
This data set contains 124 million reports from land stations and 15 million reports from ships.
Each report is 56 characters in length. The archive consists of 240 files, one file for each month of data for
land and ocean separately. With this data set a user can develop a climatology for any particular cloud type
or group of types, for any geographical region and any spatial and temporal resolution desired.
 Surface synoptic weather reports are readily available in data sets such as those prepared by the
National Meteorological Center (NMC) and the U. S. Navy Fleet Numerical Oceanography Center
(FNOC). For marine reports there is also the Comprehensive Ocean-Atmosphere Data Set (COADS).
Those data sets are archived at the (NCDC) in Asheville, North Carolina,
and at the (NCAR) in Boulder, Colorado. The data set
described here includes only the information from the synoptic weather report that directly relates to
clouds, as well as some derived quantities that aid in cloud analysis. It was developed as an intermediate
stage in our own global analysis of total cloud cover (Hahn et al., 1994a) and cloud types, but should be
useful to other researchers who wish to compare individual surface cloud reports to concurrent satellite-derived cloud data for example, or who wish to obtain averages over time or space scales not already
provided in existing archives.
 The cloud report provided in this data set, referred to as the "edited cloud report" (ECR, or ECRA
when referring to the archive of all reports), has several features that make it desirable and easy to use in
cloud analyses:
 Synoptic weather reports contain information in addition to clouds, such as air temperature,
pressure, winds, humidity, visibility, past weather and, for ships, sea surface temperature and ocean wave
parameters. The ECR excludes these data, thus reducing the data volume.
 Data sets of synoptic weather reports include reports that do not contain cloud information,
such as those from automated weather stations on land and buoys in the oceans. These are not included in
the ECRA.
The cloud portion of the synoptic report occasionally contains obvious errors or inconsistencies
which must be checked for to avoid inclusion of detectably erroneous data in an analysis. Quality control
procedures developed over years of analyzing surface cloud reports have been applied so that erroneous or
inconsistent reports have either been excluded or, if possible, corrected before inclusion in the archive.
While the amount of low cloud is directly coded in the synoptic report, the amounts of middle
and high clouds are not, but may often be inferred. Where possible for upper level clouds, the ECR
includes both the "actual" cloud amount (sometimes requiring use of the random-overlap assumption) and
the non-overlapped amount, which is simply that portion of the cloud that is visible from below and
requires no assumptions.
Although all reports that meet the above criteria are included in the ECRA, it has been shown
that many of the nighttime reports are made under conditions of insufficient (moon) light for adequate
detection of clouds. Use of such reports results in an underestimate of nighttime cloudiness by about 4%
globally and has a profound influence on computed diurnal cycles in cloudiness (Hahn et al., 1994b).
Reports made under conditions that satisfy the criterion for adequate illumination specified by Hahn et al.
(1994b) are flagged in the ECR, and both the relative lunar illuminance and the solar altitude are given for
each report.
 The edited cloud report archive described here covers the ten-year period December 1981 to
November 1991. These beginning and ending months were chosen to coincide with the boundaries of the
traditionally-defined seasons December-January-February (DJF), March-April-May (MAM), June-July-August (JJA) and September-October-November (SON). Since December 1981 is considered to be part of
DJF 1982, the 10-year period is referred to as 1982-1991. This particular 10-year period was selected to
coincide with the International Satellite Cloud Climatology Project (ISCCP; Rossow and Schiffer, 1991)
and to extend our previous climatologies (Hahn et al., 1988; Warren et al., 1986 {hereafter referred to as
W86}; Warren et al., 1988 {hereafter referred to as W88}), which terminated in (November) 1981.
 Non-standard terms used in the following discussions are defined in the glossary of terms and abbreviations in 
The NMC data set (obtained from NCAR) was the source of the synoptic weather reports used for
land stations. About 144 million reports (22 gigabytes of data) were processed. Only those stations assigned official station numbers by the (WMO) were used. Synoptic
reporting hours are 00, 03, 06, 09, 12, 15, 18, 21 Greenwich Mean Time (GMT). In the NCAR archive the
6-hourly reports (00,06,12,18 GMT) are stored in separate files from the intermediate 3-hourly reports
(03,09,15,21 GMT) and we processed them in tandem for each month. Within each of these two groups the reports are sorted by time.
 The COADS Interim Product CMR5 Reports (Woodruff et al., 1987) were the source of the ship
data used (also obtained from NCAR). About 22 million reports (540 megabytes of data in packed binary
format) were processed. Many of these reports are from buoys, however, and do not contain cloud
information. For an individual month these data are sorted first by 2-degree latitude x longitude boxes and
then by day and hour. COADS merges a dozen or so subsets of ship data and, as such, is the most
extensive record of climatic data for the sea surface. However, the Interim Products available at the time
of our analysis lack much of the digitized ship logbook data from foreign countries which may be delayed
2 - 5 years (Woodruff et al., 1992). Thus future releases of COADS will contain more data than were utilized here.
 Synoptic weather reports are coded according to the system given by the World Meteorological
Organization (WMO, 1988). The information in these reports that relates to cloud analysis is summarized
in . All other parameters were ignored in our processing. A more detailed breakdown of the
definitions of the cloud and weather types, as used here, is given in . The table shows the synoptic
codes that correspond to various precipitation types (ww codes) as well as the codes that correspond to the various cloud types defined within each of the three reporting levels: low, middle and high (C).
 We give special consideration to the cloud type nimbostratus (Ns), which is not specifically
defined in the synoptic code. Codes C= 2 or 7 may signify Ns but may also signify As or Ac,
respectively. We consider these codes to signify Ns when there is concurrent precipitation in the form of
drizzle, rain, or snow as indicated in the present weather code ww (symbolized in Table 2 as D, R and S,
respectively). To distinguish Ns from As/Ac we "extend" the synoptic code for CM to include the values
12 and 11 to represent these cases of C= 2 and 7, respectively. The extended code values (shown in
Table 2) are entered in the edited cloud report (Section 4) without loss of the information content in the original report.
 Nimbostratus is also considered to be present when C= / and specified combinations of
precipitation and low cloud types are present (Table 2). These cases are given the extended code C= 10.
This definition for nimbostratus has been simplified from that used in our previous work (W86, W88).
Cases of C=/ with low stratus and drizzle are no longer defined to be Ns. This will cause a slight
reduction in computed Ns amounts (Section 5C).
Special consideration is also given to the case of N=9 (sky obscured). If ww indicates that the sky
was obscured due to F, Ts, or DRS (symbols defined in Table 2), the cloud type is considered to be Fg,
Cb, or Ns, respectively, and is given the extended code C=10, respectively, and the
value of N is set to 8 oktas.
 All the changes described here are coded in a parameter called "the change code" (Section 3C
below) which is also included in the edited cloud report (Section 4), so that unchanged reports could be
reconstructed if desired.
 A cloud report may be suitable for total cloud analysis even if cloud type information is
incomplete. Certain inconsistencies within the cloud type portion of the report may, however, make the
whole report suspect and cause it to be rejected even for total cloud analysis. The processing and quality
control checks performed on each weather report read from the original archives (NMC or COADS) and
designed to ensure suitability for total cloud analysis are shown in the flow chart in . The
percentage of reports discarded at each stage of the processing, which is discussed in the following
paragraphs, is indicated.
 In the early stages of processing, land and ship reports required slightly different checks (upper
portion of Figure 1). A land station that did not have a WMO station number was discarded (most of these
were from the United States), thus ensuring more uniformity in reporting procedures. A ship report known
to be from a buoy (by the "deck" number in the COADS data) was discarded. Any report that had no
cloud information (N=/) was discarded.
 In 1982 WMO introduced several changes in the coding procedure (WMO, 1988). One of these
changes now instructs observers to set ww=/ if present weather was either "not available" or "observed
phenomena were not of significance" (ww codes 00-03 are considered to represent phenomena without
significance). The present weather indicator, I, is used to distinguish these cases. Land station reports
with I=3 (data
not available) were also discarded because without ww it is not possible to interpret cases of N=9 (see
W86) or to evaluate the occurrence of precipitation. I=2 indicates that observed phenomena were not of
significance, while Ix is coded as "1" when ww is given. Occasionally I=1 when ww=/; these inconsistent
reports were also discarded.
 Examination of the NMC data set showed that while land stations adopted this new coding
procedure almost immediately, I was not consistently coded in ship reports until 1985, as ship observers
tended to continue reporting ww in accordance with the old rules. The COADS data set does not even
contain I.
 At the upper horizontal dashed line in Figure 1, 125 million land reports and 15.8 million ship
reports remained. The discard fractions below the line are fractions of these numbers. If the reported
latitude and longitude of a land station put the station on water (rare) or if reported latitude and longitude
of a ship put the ship on land (0.3%), the report was discarded. A land station was considered to be on
water (or a ship on land) if the 5x5 degree latitude x longitude box in which it was reported to reside was
100% ocean (or land) as defined in W86. Exceptions to this are that a number of boxes with small islands
were allowed to contribute to the land data and reports from the Great Lakes and the Caspian Sea were
allowed to contribute to the ship data.
 If the sky was obscured (N=9) by fog (ww=F; 1.1% land, 2.7% ship), thunderstorms-showers
(ww=Ts, abbreviated as T in the figure; 0.05% land, 0.1% ship), or drizzle-rain-snow (ww=DRS,
abbreviated here as R; 0.4% land, 0.9% ship), the sky was considered to be overcast (N=8). This source
of "cloudiness" contributed about 1% to the total cloud cover globally, and much more in some locations
and seasons (Hahn et al., 1992). Clouds could not be inferred if the sky was obscured for other reasons,
such as blowing dust or snow, and such reports were discarded. The change code, IC=1 (discussed in
Section 3C below), signifies that a report came through the N=9 branch of the processing. Thus 1.5% of
the land reports and 3.7% of the ship reports had N=9 with the ww codes D, R, S, F or Ts.
 Other data consistency checks indicated in Figure 1 ensure that the low cloud amount is not greater
than the total cloud cover, that precipitation (as defined in Table 2) is not reported with a clear sky, and
that if cloud is present (and types are reported), some cloud type must be indicated in at least one of the
three possible levels (this test actually discards a report if N&#62;0 and C&#60;/=0). The re-coding indicated in the lower left box in the figure is necessary because of a 1982 code change (WMO,
1988) that instructs observers to set C=/ when N=0 (this requires special attention in cloud type
analysis and will be discussed in Section 4).
 The number of reports that survive these tests and are suitable for total cloud analysis (referred to
as "total reports") is 124.2 million for land and 14.7 million for ships. Of these, 90.3 million and 11.1
million, respectively, were made under sufficient solar or lunar illuminance (referred to as "light reports")
to meet the established illuminance criterion for adequate cloud visibility (Hahn et al., 1994b).
 The ability of surface observers to adequately detect clouds at night has been questioned for many
years (e.g. Riehl, 1947; Schneider et al., 1989). In an attempt to find a practical solution to this "night-detection-bias", Hahn et al. (1994b) analyzed ten years of nighttime data for the zone 0-50&amp;$176; N and plotted
reported cloud cover as a function of the illumination due to moonlight, which depends on the phase and
altitude (angle above or below the horizon) of the moon and on the distance of the moon from the earth.
The amount of total cloud reported at night increased as the lunar illuminance increased up to a certain
threshold, after which the reported cloud cover leveled off. This threshold is referred to as "the
illuminance criterion" and corresponds to the twilight produced by the sun at an altitude of about 9 degrees below the horizon. Thus the illuminance criterion is met when either the sun is at an altitude greater than -9&#176; or the position of the moon is such that its illuminance exceeds the threshold. These conditions were
determined for each report with the use of an ephemeris and the latitude, longitude, date and time of the
report.
 This illuminance criterion was applied in analyses of total cloud cover and clear-sky frequency
(Hahn et al., 1994a). (Fog and precipitation frequencies were also analyzed in that study but their
detection does not depend on illumination). Application of the illuminance criterion increased the
computed global average total cloud cover at night by about 4% and thus increased the daily average
computed cloud cover by about 2%. Diurnal cycles of total cloud cover over land, which typically show
daytime maxima, were reduced in amplitude when compared to previous studies which did not use the
illuminance criterion (W86). Over the oceans, the increased computed nighttime cloud cover was often
sufficient to result in nighttime maxima, in contrast to the daytime maxima previously reported (W88).
Preliminary surveys conducted in conjunction with the present work suggest that we should expect
similarly dramatic effects on analyses of middle and high clouds but little effect on low clouds.
 Because of the importance of moonlight in the detection of clouds at night, parameters relating to
the illuminance criterion are included in the edited cloud report (Section 4). Reports for which the
illuminance criterion is met are referred to as "light reports", as opposed to "dark reports" (for which the
criterion is not met) or "all reports" (which includes both light and dark).
 The reports that failed the cloud type consistency checks shown in Figure 1 were discarded. Other
inconsistencies are possible which may be correctable or may provide cause simply to reject the report for
cloud type analysis. As the synoptic reports were processed, any inconsistency encountered required a
change to be made in the existing code before the report was entered into the edited cloud report archive.
Any changes thus made are noted by assigning a "change code" (IC) to that report. This change code (with
values 0 to 9) is preserved in the ECR (Section 4) so that modifications made to the original report can be
identified.
 Details of the cloud type processing following the total cloud stage shown in Figure 1 are
presented in the form of the FORTRAN code in . Each segment of the table (delineated by a
change code heading) describes the processing of a particular type of inconsistency or change. The
changes associated with particular coded cases are described briefly in along with the frequency of
occurrence of each change type. (The changes referred to by IC=1 were discussed in section 3B.) Most of
the inconsistencies under consideration have been discussed previously (W86, W88) but are summarized
here.
 For a report to provide useful cloud type information, both Nh and CL must be given. If either is
missing (and not correctable) then the report cannot be used for cloud type analysis and all cloud type
variables are set to -1 for consistency (see segment IC_5 in Table 3). Thus if any inconsistency is
discovered that cannot be corrected, simply setting Nh=-1 will result in exclusion of the report from cloud
type analyses. For example, the IC_2,4 segment in Table 3 examines the case in which there is middle
cloud but no low cloud. In such a case Nh should give the middle cloud amount. In some reports Nh was
improperly set to 0 (W86). If there is also no high cloud then it must be that Nh=N and the report can be
corrected (IC=2). But if high cloud is present, then the value of Nh is indeterminate, and set to -1 (IC=4),
and the report cannot be used for cloud types (in such cases all cloud type variables are set to -1 in segment
IC_5).
 The situation is similar in segment IC_3,4. If only high cloud is present, Nh should properly be 0
but is sometimes given the value of N by an observer. This is readily corrected (IC=3). But if Nh&#60;N in
such a case, the report is irreconcilably inconsistent and must be rejected for cloud type analysis (set Nh=-1
and IC=4).
 Segments IC_6 and IC_9 simply correct cases of sloppy reporting of middle and high clouds, such
as reporting C=/ when the sky is overcast with low cloud.
 Segments IC_7 and IC_8 merely set C to represent our definition of Ns as a convenience for
future cloud type analyses. As is usually the case, the original report can be reconstructed if desired.
 The order in which some of these consistency checks is performed is also important to the
outcome. For example, if segment IC_8 were performed before segment IC_6, then some cases of Ns
would go undetected. Also, segment IC_9 must be performed after IC_8 for the same reason. However
since it is not desirable to have the change code IC=8 overwritten by the relatively trivial change IC=9, this
latter code is only entered in IC (although the change is made) if no previous change has been made
(second part of segment IC_9 in Table 3). This co-occurrence of change codes should be rare since N is
usually large when Ns is present.
 From Table 4 we see that some change is made in 12% of land reports and 16% of ship reports,
but that roughly half of the changes just represent classifying an observation as Ns, Cb or fog. Thus less
than 5% of land reports and less than 9% of ship reports have been changed due to inconsistencies and
most of these are due to the relatively trivial cases with IC=6 (and IC=9 for ships).
 After passing the cloud type consistency checks, the number of light reports available for cloud
type analysis for 1982-91 is 88 million for land and 9.4 million for the ocean (). Reports suitable
for cloud type analysis (C and Nh &#62; -1) are referred to as "type reports".
 The synoptic code contains two cloud amount variables, N and Nh. The amount of low cloud, if
present, is directly specified by Nh. While the amounts of upper level clouds are not directly specified,
they may often be inferred. Thus when C=0, the amount of middle cloud is given by Nh, and when
C=0, the amount of high cloud is given by N. If all three levels are present there are too few known
variables to determine the upper cloud amounts. If two levels are present, the amount in the upper level
may be estimated if the extent of overlap is assumed.
 In the ECR we provide amounts that utilize the random overlap assumption, where necessary, in
order to best represent the actual cloud amounts (the fraction of the sky covered by a cloud type, whether
visible or not). We also provide the non-overlapped amounts which require no assumptions but which
indicate only the amount of the upper level cloud visible from below. (Satellite-derived cloud amounts are
typically given as the non-overlapped amounts visible from above.) Tian and Curry (1989) tested the
minimum, maximum and random overlap assumptions and found the maximum overlap assumption to be
best for adjacent cloud layers, while the random overlap assumption was best for vertically separated
layers.
 gives our method, in the form of FORTRAN code, for determining the actual and non-overlapped amounts of middle and high clouds from a synoptic weather report. A few points should be
noted. The random overlap equation (lines 17 and 38) is invoked only when Nh&#60;7. , which gives
the outcomes of the possible combinations of N and Nh in the equation, shows that only 2 outcomes are
possible for the upper cloud amount when Nh=7, namely 0 and 8 oktas, making this a highly inaccurate
determination (W86). In such cases the upper cloud amount is left undetermined. If the upper cloud in
question is Ns, however, the maximum overlap assumption is employed and the Ns amount is assigned the
value of N (lines 13-14, Table 6). In this case the nimbostratus cloud layer is likely to be adjacent to or
continuous with the low cloud, so the maximum overlap assumption is more appropriate (Tian and Curry,
1989). Also, certain arbitrary decisions are sometimes required, such as our choice, in line 7 of Table 6, toallow middle cloud to be computed when C=/. This choice is justifiable since such a case tends to occur
with large N so that any error induced by this situation would be small.
 The number of times reports were processed through the possible paths in Table 6 are listed in
. Light reports (for which the illuminance criterion was met) and dark reports (for which the
illuminance criterion was not met) are both shown, where possible, for comparison. Land and ocean data
were processed separately. Non-overlapped (NOL) amounts were computable in more than 90% of the
cloud type reports since one can know that a cloud cannot be seen even if one does not know whether it is
present. Thus the non-overlapped amount of an upper level cloud is frequently zero.
 Percentages are not explicitly shown in the table but it can be seen that upper level clouds are
reported more frequently in the set of light reports than in the set of dark reports (38% and 30%,
respectively, for land middle clouds, and 44% and 29%, respectively, for ocean middle clouds, for
example). When upper clouds are present, they are more frequently computable within the set of dark
reports and random overlap (ROL) is less often required. Comparing land and ocean, upper level clouds,
when observed to be present, are less likely to be computable from ocean data and are more likely to
require ROL because of the predominance of low level clouds over the oceans. (The percentages given
here merely represent the fractions of reports within the data set and are not area-weighted global
averages.)
 shows the variables included in the ECR, the number of characters allocated for each, and
the maximum and minimum values allowed. Each item in the table is discussed briefly below. Sample
reports selected from ship and land data for 1981 December and 1982 January are provided in .
These reports are in the order in which they appear in their respective files (see next section) though these
selections are not consecutive within the file. The reports are numbered in the table for convenience.
 Item 1: The first item in the report gives the year, month, day and GMT hour of the report, with 2
characters allotted for each. There are no spaces ("3", for example, is given as "03") so that the entire item
can be read as a single integer. Only the last 2 digits of the year (1900's) are given. Months are coded as
01 through 12, representing January through December.
 Item 2: The IB variable indicates whether the illuminance criterion of Hahn et al. (1994b) was
satisfied (IB=1) at the time and place of the report or not (IB=0). This variable can be checked in lieu of
SA and RI (items 19 and 20 below) if one accepts the criterion specified in Hahn et al. (1994b).
Item 3: The latitude (in degrees north and south) is given to 2 decimal places and written as a 5-digit integer, and thus must be divided by 100 to obtain actual latitude. Actual values range from +90 to -90 for 90N to 90S, respectively.
 Item 4: The longitude (in degrees east) is given to 2 decimal places and written as a 5-digit
integer, and thus must be divided by 100 to obtain actual longitude. Actual values range from 0 to 360E.
 Item 5: For land stations, ID is the WMO station number (WMO, 1977). For ships, ID is the card
deck assignment (Slutz et al., 1985).
 Item 6: This parameter indicates whether a report is from a land station (LO=1) or a ship (LO=2).
 Items 7-13: These weather and cloud variables are coded as specified by WMO (1988) except that
items 11 and 12 have been "extended" as described in Section 3A (Table 2). Also, cases of N=9 (item 8)
that were not discarded have been converted to N=8. Any such conversion is coded in the "change code"
(item 18 below). The value "-1" indicates missing data. Item 8 (N) does not obtain a value of -1 in this
data set since all such reports were discarded during processing. Item 10 (h) may have a value of 9 only
when a cloud is present since h was set to -1 in cases of N=0 (Figure 1).
 Items 14-15: These variables give the "actual" cloud amounts of middle and high clouds and
utilize the random overlap equation where necessary (Section 3D). Values are given in oktas to 2 decimal
places and written as 3-digit integers, so they must be divided by 100 to obtain the actual values. An
actual value of 9 (coded value 900) indicates missing data.
 Items 16-17: These variables give the non-overlapped cloud amounts of middle and high clouds
and represent the amount of cloud visible from below (Section 3D). Values are given in oktas. A value of
9 indicates missing data.
 Item 18: The change code indicates whether a change was made to the original report during
processing. Code values are defined briefly in Table 4 and in detail in Figure 1 and Table 3 (Section 3C).
A change code of 0 means that no change was made other than the trivial change of converting /'s to 0's in
the case of N=0. Examples of reports with each change code are provided in Table 10.
 Items 19-20: These variables give the solar and lunar parameters needed to determine the
illuminance provided by the sun or moon for the date, time and location of the report (Section 3B1). SA is
the altitude of the sun above the horizon, given to a tenth of a degree (divide the coded value by 10 to
obtain the actual value). RI is the lunar relative illuminance defined by Hahn et al., (1994b). RI= PHI sin(A)
(R), where A is the lunar altitude, r is the earth-moon distance, R is the mean earth-moon distance, and
PHI is the lunar phase function which varies from 0 to 1 in a concave shape such that a full moon is 10 times
as bright as a half moon (Hapke, 1971). The illuminance criterion of Hahn et al. (1994b) is met (IB=1,
item 2) when SA&#62;/=-9&#176; or RI&#62;0.11. (A negative value of RI means the moon was below the horizon.)
 The data are divided into 240 files, one for each month for ten years for land and ocean separately.
These files range in size from 5.0 to 8.4 MB for the ocean data and from 49.8 to 63.5 MB for the land data.
 In the NMC data set archived at NCAR, the 6-hourly reports and 3-hourly reports (Section 2) are
stored on separate files. Each of these subsets is sorted first by time and then by latitude and longitude.
Each land data file of the ECRA was formed by merging the 6-hourly and the 3-hourly data so that for
each month the reports appear in time order.
 The sort used in the COADS Interim Product (Section 2) was first by 2-degree box, then by time,
and finally by latitude and longitude for each month. For the ECRA files, the reports were re-sorted by
time and then by latitude and longitude.
 Figure 1 and Tables 4, 5 and 8 showed the number of reports processed, deleted and changed, as
well as the number of light reports, the number suitable for cloud type analysis, and the number of times
upper level cloud amounts were computable. shows how the reports are distributed over the
synoptic reporting times. Land stations usually report 8 times per day but some do not (notably in the
United States and Australia), so that 59% of all reports are made during the 6-hourly times. Ships,
however, tend to report at the 6-hourly times and only about 10% of the ship reports are for the
intermediate 3-hourly times. Having only 4 reports per day, rather than 8, limits the resolution possible in
computations of the phase and amplitude of the diurnal cycle. It was also noted (W88) that regionalaverages formed from 6-hourly ship data may be uniformly different from averages formed from 3-hourly
data, consistent with a tendency for some ships to give a 3-hourly report only in unusually stormy weather.
A bias is also possible when averaging over a land grid box that has more than one station if stations
within one climatic region report 8 times per day while stations within a different climatic region report 4
times per day.
 The histograms in for ocean show the frequency of occurrence of the
extended code values for the six cloud variables for light reports in the archive of edited cloud reports. [In
these figures N=9 is shown separate from N=8 although N=9 appears as N=8 (with IC=1) in the ECR.]
The shaded areas show the occurrence of precipitation (DRSTs, Table 2). Numerical values for the data
shown in these figures are provided in . Several interesting features are evident in these
figures. The distribution of codes for total cloud cover N is nearly U-shaped for land but strongly skewed
towards the higher amounts for oceans. 96.5% of all precipitation occurs with N&#62;/=7 over land and with
N&#62;/=6 over oceans. About 75% of precipitation occurs with Nh&#62;/=6. The reports with Nh=-1 are not usable
for cloud type analysis. The most commonly occurring cloud base height code is h=5 (600-1000m) over
land and h=4 (300-600m) over oceans. The high frequency of h=9 over land is a consequence of the high
occurrence of C=0 so that h=9 often refers to the middle cloud level.
 The lower panels in Figures 2a and 2b show the occurrences of various cloud types within the
three reporting levels. The occurrence of C=-1 is the same as Nh=-1 due to the processing procedure and
is the fraction of reports that do not contain information relating to cloud types (2.6% for land data, 15.3%
for ocean data). A larger fraction of the reports have C=-1 (33.2% for land, 50.9% for ocean) because of lower overcast. Thus 97.4% of the land reports have
information about cloud types but only 82% of those have information about the middle cloud level and
66% about high clouds. For the oceans, 84.7% of the reports have low cloud information but only 57% of
those have middle cloud information and 40% have high cloud information.
 The low cloud type most commonly reported over land is stratocumulus (C=5). While this type
is also relatively common over the oceans, it is exceeded by the cumulus types C= 1 and 2. About 25%
of all precipitation occurs with the stratus cloud C=7 is reported over land, precipitation is
present in 67% of the reports. Precipitation occurs in 34% of the ship reports of C=7.
 While 58% (land) and 46% (ocean) of all precipitation occurs with the middle clouds defined to be
nimbostratus (C= 10,11,12), 25% and 38%, respectively, of precipitation occurs when the middle cloud
level is not given in the report (typically because of low overcast). Because of our definition of Ns shown
in Table 2, most of these latter cases must have ww= D or Ts. In the high cloud level, 90% of all
precipitation occurs in reports with C=-1 (high cloud level not reported, usually because of lower
overcast).
 The occurrence of reports of sky-obscured (N=9) due to fog or precipitation is 1.5% for land and
3.5% for ocean, with fog (C=11) accounting for more than two thirds of these values for both land and
ocean (Figure 2 and Appendix A). These cases of sky-obscured due to fog make up 14% (land) and 48%
(ocean) of all reported cases (light) of fog. Cases of thunderstorms or showers (C=10) account for onlyabout 3.5% of the reports of sky obscured, and sky-obscured due to thunderstorms or showers make up
only 1.6% (land) and 5.8% (ocean) of the light reports of thunderstorms and showers. The remaining
contribution to the reports of sky obscured (about one quarter) is due to drizzle, rain or snow. Sky-obscured due to drizzle, rain or snow make up 5.1% (land) and 12.9% (ocean) of the light reports of
drizzle, rain and snow.
 A report of sky-obscured due to drizzle, rain or snow is considered to indicate nimbostratus cloud
and is given the extended code value C=10 with IC=1 (Tables 2 and 4). Two other sets of circumstances
are considered to indicate Ns as well. shows the contributions of the three major paths to the
frequency of Ns within the light type reports. (Frequencies based on light reports are slightly higher
than the frequencies quoted in the last paragraph which were based on the total set of light reports.) The
largest contributor to Ns in the land data is the path through C=2,7 (with ww=DRS). For both land and
ocean C=11,12 in Appendix A). The largest contributor to
Ns in the ocean data comes through the C=/ path, which has several contributors itself, the largest being
the case of C=7 with DRS.
 Excluded from the definition of Ns are the cases of C=4,5,6,8 and ww=D (more than
half of these cases are due to C=6 alone). These cases were considered to indicate Ns in our previous
climatologies (W86, W88) but after subsequent consideration and discussions with colleagues we
concluded that since drizzle could occur from these low cloud types, the additional inference of Ns above
them was inappropriate. Thus the frequencies of occurrence of Ns computed under the current definition
will be reduced to about 97% (land) and 90% (ocean) of the frequencies given in W86 and W88.
 Another change associated with the simplification of our previous definition of Ns involves cases
of C 6,7 in these cases were previously reassigned as
Ns, but are left unchanged in the present, simplified definition. This results in a further reduction in
computed Ns frequency by factors comparable to those in the last paragraph. Thus the Ns frequencies
computed under the present definition may be about 94% (land) and 81% (ocean) of those computed under
the previous definition. Note that these percentages refer to the number of reports in the data set which
contains a disproportionate contribution of reports from the densely populated northern mid-latitudes and
thus do not represent the area-weighted global averages. Note also that the user of this data set is not
restricted to the definitions assigned here since all the information necessary for any other interpretation is
contained in the edited cloud reports. The definitions discussed above apply only if the reports are used
exactly as written.
 The cases of C=/ and ww=DRS are not considered to indicate nimbostratus
cloud.
 To show the global distribution of the reports, numbers (shown as log10) of light type reports are
displayed on a 5c grid (see Glossary in Appendix B) in (ocean). Numbers from
1-9 appear as 0, numbers from 10-99 appear as 1, etc. Grid boxes with no light type reports are blank.
 A number of biases which can affect analyses of clouds from surface observations are summarized
in W88. Four biases which we can measure and possibly correct for are described in more detail here.
 The is largely eliminated by using only data for which the illuminance
criterion is met (Section 3B1). This, however, enhances the unless precautions are
taken since less than half as many nighttime observations will be available compared to the number of
daytime observations. Thus Hahn et al. (1994a) prepared nighttime and daytime averages separately and
averaged the two together to obtain the average cloud cover.
 Another potential bias for cloud type analyses was introduced by the synoptic code change in 1982
which allowed observers to record a "/" for cloud types when N=0. Previously a report with N=0 and C
or Nh =/ would indicate a station that never reports cloud types and the report would be omitted from the
cloud type analysis. Now every occurrence of N=0 must be treated as C=0 and Nh=0. Thus a report
from a station or ship which never reports cloud types would contribute to a cloud type analysis only when
the sky was clear, producing a : the frequency of occurrence of clear sky computed from the
cloud type reports would be too high and the frequencies of occurrence of the various cloud types would be
too low. The magnitude of this bias can be estimated by counting the number of times observers within a
grid box omit cloud types (Nh=/ or C=/) when N&#62;0 and assuming that the same fraction of the cases of
N=0 would be from stations or ships that do not report cloud types, and thus should be excluded from the
denominator when determining the frequency of occurrence of a cloud type.
 =/
(or Nh=/) in light reports with N&#62;0 (this bias fraction is referred to as fb). (Note that when computing
these fractions using the ECRA, reports of Nh=-1 with IC=4 must not be counted in fb since these values
were set during data processing and not by the observer.) In the land data, extremely large values occur
only in northern Alaska (87%, underlined in Figure 4a) and in northeast Greenland (72%). Ship data show
large values in the Great Lakes region of North America where values exceed 90% and in some European
waters where values are as great as 82%. Values of fb average about 3% for land data and about 10% for
ship data.
 To determine how much effect this bias would have on computed cloud type frequencies, the
"clear-sky adjustment factor" (AF0) was defined such that Fa = AF0 &#183; Fr, where Fa is the adjusted
frequency of occurrence of some cloud type and Fr is the frequency that would be computed using the
potentially biased cloud type reports. Since Fr = Nt / Nr, where Nt is the number of occurrences of a
particular cloud type and Nr is the number of reports contributing to the cloud type analysis, and Fa = Nt /
(Nr - fb &#183; N0), where N0 is the number of occurrences of N=0 and fb is the fraction of N0 that should be
discounted, then, using f0 = N0 / Nr, Fa can be represented as Fa = Nt / (Nr - fb &#183; f0 &#183; Nr) = Nt / (Nr &#183; (1 -
fb &#183; f0)) = Fr / (1 - fb &#183; f0). Thus AF0 = 1 / (1 - fb &#183; f0) and is equal to one if either fb or f0 is zero.
 show the global distribution of AF0 {displayed as 100 x (AF0-1)} over land and
ocean, respectively. This analysis shows that, on average, cloud type frequencies, if uncorrected, would be
reduced only to about 99.5% of their correct values by this bias (average AF0 = 1.003 for land and 1.007
for ocean) and that most regions of the globe are essentially unaffected. However a few regions are greatly
affected, namely northern Alaska, northeastern Greenland, the Great Lakes, and some seas around Europe.
These are the regions with high values of fb (Figures 4a and 4b). The two most extreme regions, the Great
Lakes and northern Alaska, have biased values 41% and 27% of their correct values. Other than the AF0
values of 3.68 in Alaska and 1.31 in Greenland, no land box has a value greater than 1.08. In the ocean
data, moderate values of AF0 (around 1.10) occur in the Middle East where clear-sky frequencies are high
(W88), and several higher values are seen in the seas of Europe and in the Great Lakes of North America.
While it may be desirable to apply this adjustment factor to regions of moderately large AF0 values,
practical application of this correction will be complicated by the fact that AF0 values vary from year to
year, season to season, and day to night. Fortunately correction is unnecessary over most regions of the
globe and the regions noted in Figures 5a and 5b for large adjustment factors can simply be eliminated
from a cloud type analysis.
 Note that while cloud type frequencies are subject to the clear-sky bias because of the coding
instructions and practices for cloud type reports, the frequency of occurrence of clear sky itself (and also
the frequency of fog) can be computed without this bias by using the total cloud data set to which this bias
does not pertain (as was done in Hahn et al., 1994a).
 Our recognition of certain cases of N=9 as overcast cloud (Section 3B) is important in obtaining
accurate estimates of the amounts of fog and nimbostratus cloud, but may introduce the ,
which is similar in principle to the clear-sky bias discussed above. Since C=/ whenever N=9, it is not
possible to distinguish stations or ships that normally report cloud types from those that do not. Thus the
latter stations will contribute to the cloud type analysis only when the sky is obscured (aside from the case
of clear sky which was discussed above). This will tend to cause the computed frequencies of fog and
nimbostratus cloud to be too large and the frequencies of other cloud types to be reduced. The fraction fb
shown in Figures 4a and 4b is again a measure of the potential of this bias. A "sky-obscured adjustment
factor" (AF9) is defined in a manner similar to that for AF0 defined above such that Fa = AF9 &#183; Fr and
AF9 = 1 / (1 - fb &#183; f9), where f9 is the frequency of occurrence of N=9 in cloud type reports.
The global distribution of f9 is given in . The box in northern Alaska
(underlined), which was shown previously to have fb=0.87 (Figure 4a), also has the relatively large value
of 0.16 for f9 which gives AF9=1.16. Inspection of Figures 4a and 6a together shows that this is the
largest AF9 value for land data and that in most regions the value of AF9 is near 1.00. Ship data have
larger fb values (Figure 4b) and larger f9 values (Figure 6b) than land data. Also the large values are
distributed over larger regions. The largest f9 values occur, again, in the Great Lakes region where they
combine with fb to produce AF9 values that approach 2. In the North Pacific, where large amounts of fog
occur during the summer season (W88), moderately large f9 values (&#126;0.20) occur with moderate fb values
(&#126;0.11), giving AF9=1.02 which is a relatively small bias. The global average values for AF9 are 1.0003
for land and 1.003 for the ocean. Thus, aside from the few regions specially noted to be removed from
cloud type analysis, the sky-obscured bias is generally small. Any bias in the frequency of fog itself can be
eliminated by computing it from the total cloud reports, as mentioned above. Any bias towards increasing
the nimbostratus frequency will be small since N=9 contributes only a small portion of the total
nimbostratus (Table 12) and will be compensated somewhat by the tendency towards reducing the
frequency of Ns contributed by the C=/ paths.
 The determination of the average cloud amounts and frequencies of occurrence from surface
observations requires some special considerations to avoid various potential biases and to obtain
representative values. Upper level clouds present special problems because they are sometimes partially or
completely hidden from the view of the observer by lower clouds. These issues are discussed in detail in
W86 and W88 but will be highlighted here.
 Total cloud cover is basically the sum of the values of N in the synoptic code (converted to percent
if desired) divided by the number of contributing reports. However, to avoid the day-night bias discussed
above, some method of equalizing the contribution of reports between day and night is necessary. In W86,
averages were obtained by first forming averages for the 8 synoptic hours and then averaging these 8
numbers. For oceans, where data are less plentiful, this method will result in significant loss of data
because the 3-hourly times often do not have a sufficient number of reports to obtain a statistically reliable
average. Therefore, Hahn et al. (1994a) divided the day into two 12-hour periods, 0600-1800 local time
("day") and 1800-0600 local time ("night"), and averaged these two numbers. Note that when using only
the light reports (to avoid the night-detection bias) to form monthly averages, only about two weeks of data
will contribute to the nighttime average in any single month. Due to this "monthly-sampling error" there
will be more scatter in monthly averages from year to year although multi-year averages should become
more statistically representative of climatological means as the number of contributing years is increased.
Similarly, seasonal averages should be more representative of an individual season than monthly averages
are of an individual month.
 These considerations of the day-night bias, night-detection bias, and monthly-sampling error apply
equally well to cloud type analyses discussed below. However, for quantities such as fog and precipitation,
whose detection does not depend on illumination, all observations may be used, minimizing all three of
these biases.
 Of the 90.3 million light reports suitable for total cloud analysis for land (Figure 1), 88.0 million
have cloud type information (Table 5). For the ocean these numbers are 11.1 million and 9.4 million. In
the type reports, the amount of a low cloud type (if present) is always given in the Nh variable of the
report. The average amount for a particular low cloud type can be obtained, in a manner similar to that for
total cloud amount, by summing the Nh values when the type is present and dividing by the number of
contributing reports (using the precautions against the day-night bias discussed above and adjusting for the
small clear-sky and sky-obscured biases if desired). The contributing reports consist of those with C&#62;/=0
and Nh&#62;/=0 and include reports of N=0. An alternative, but equivalent, method for obtaining the average is
to compute the frequency of occurrence (f) of the type (the number of occurrences of the type divided by
the number of contributing reports) and the amount-when-present (awp; sum of Nh's divided by the
number of occurrences of the type) separately. Then the average amount is avg = f awp. This latter
method is described because it is often of interest to know the frequency of occurrence of a type in addition to its amount, because awp tends to be characteristic of a cloud type, and because this is the method used
in computing upper level cloud type amounts.
 Cloud type reports do not always contain information about upper level clouds because they may
be hidden by an overcast or near-overcast layer of lower clouds. Thus, of the 88.0 million light type
reports for land (Table 8), only 74.4 million have information about the middle cloud level (C&#62;/=0) and
60.3 million have information about the high level (C&#62;/=0). Of the 9.4 million light type reports for the
oceans, 7.1 million have C&#62;/=0.
 The average amounts of upper level cloud types are obtained as described in the last section: avg
= f x awp. Since we want the actual frequency of occurrence of a cloud type, and not just the frequency
with which it is visible, f is computed as the number of times the type was observed divided by the number
of reports of C). For land, middle and high cloud frequencies
are determined from 84.5% and 68.5% of the light type reports, respectively. For the oceans these values
are 75.5% and 58.5%, respectively. The question of the degree to which these portions of the data set
represent the whole data set for types is discussed in W86 and W88. Based on a study of the frequency of
occurrence of As/Ac [f(As,Ac)] versus low cloud amount, Warren et al. (W88) applied an adjustment to
f(As,Ac) which assigned to the cases of C=/ (15.5% of the type reports for land and 24.5% for ocean) a
value that is the average of f(As,Ac) of the reports that have low cloud amounts of 3 to 7 oktas. For high
clouds, f was computed only from reports with Nh&#60;7 in order to reduce the partial-undercast bias (W88).
 The amount-when-present of an upper cloud type can be determined, when it is reported present
(C&#62;0), only if there are at most 2 cloud levels present. In addition, amounts are not computed for an
upper cloud if it is undercast by a layer which covers 7 oktas or more of the sky (Section 3D). Therefore
awp is computed from an even smaller pool of data than that used for frequency computations. Table 8
shows that, for land, 78% of the observed (light) occurrences of middle clouds and 75% of the observed
occurrences of high clouds are computable. For the ocean data these values are 61% and 43%,
respectively. Nevertheless, awp computed from these data is probably fairly representative of the actual
awp (W86 and W88) and any error in awp results in a smaller error in avg by the factor f. Any systematic
error inherent in the random-overlap assumption would produce a smaller error in computed a mounts since
this assumption is used for only a fraction of the computable observations. Table 8 shows that the random-overlap assumption is used in 39% of the computable observations (light) of middle cloud and in 55% for
high cloud over land. These fractions are larger for ocean data with random overlap used for 60% of the
computable middle clouds and 70% of the computable high clouds.
 Special note about Ns: Because Ns is defined on the basis of the occurrence of precipitation
(Table 2) which does not depend on the visibility of the middle cloud level for its detection, its presence or
absence is known for every type report. Thus the number of contributing reports for f(Ns) is the same as
that for low cloud types (C&#62;/=0 and Nh&#62;/=0). However, when present, its amount is not always known and a
separate tally (which will be different from that for the As/Ac clouds) must be kept for determining its
awp.
This documentation and the data described herein are available from:
 Oak Ridge National Laboratory
 Post Office Box 2008
 Oak Ridge, TN 37831-6290, U.S.A.
 Telephone (865) 574-3645 or (865) 574-0390
 or
 Data Support Section
 Boulder, CO 80307, U.S.A.
 Telephone (303) 497-1215.
The following should be used for referencing this archive and/or this documentation report:
 Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, TN. (Also available from Data Support Section,
National Center for Atmospheric Research, Boulder, CO.)
The archive of our earlier climatology (Hahn et al., 1988) and the accompanying atlases (Warren
et al., 1986, 1988) are also available from the same sources listed above.
 This work was supported by NASA Grant NAG-1-998 and by Battelle Pacific Northwest
Laboratories, Atmospheric Radiation Measurement Program (Contract 144806-A-Q1). We also acknowledge the long term cooperation and provision of computing facilities by the Scientific Computing Division of the National Center for Atmospheric Research.]]></Text>
    </Documentation_Link>
    <OME_Software_Version>Version 4.7.5, Revision Date: 04 Apr 2006</OME_Software_Version>
    <OME_DTD_Version>metadata10.dtd</OME_DTD_Version>
    <Temporal_Resolution></Temporal_Resolution>
    <enddate_blank></enddate_blank>
    <Harvest_Date>2017-09-01</Harvest_Date>
    <File_ID>Created 20050808 163356 by 160.91.18.40</File_ID>
    <Spatial_Extent></Spatial_Extent>
    <Metadata_URL><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/xml/cdp/metadata/Dale_Kaiser/NDP_026b.xml]]></Metadata_URL>
    <CDIAC>
      <Product_number><![CDATA[doi 10.3334/CDIAC/cli.ndp026.b]]></Product_number>
      <Product_title><![CDATA[Edited Synoptic Cloud Reports From Ships and Land Stations over the Globe, 1982-1991 (NDP-026B)]]></Product_title>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Hahn, C. J.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[Department of Atmospheric Sciences]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Warren, S. G.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[Department of Atmospheric Sciences]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[London, J.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[University of Colorado]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[Department of Astrophysical, Planetary and Atmospheric Sciences]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Thematic_area><![CDATA[Climate]]></Thematic_area>
      <Site_info>
        <Site_name><![CDATA[Global]]></Site_name>
        <Site_URL><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/epubs/ndp/ndp026b/ndp026b.htm]]></Site_URL>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp026b/]]></Site_data_file>
      </Site_info>
      <Data_site></Data_site>
      <Variable><![CDATA[AH]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[AM]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CH]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CL]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CM]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[IB]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[IC]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[ID]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[LAT]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[LO]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[LON]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[N]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[Nh]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[RI]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SA]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[UH]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[UM]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[dy]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[h]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[hr]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[mn]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[ww]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[yr]]></Variable>
      <Descriptive_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/epubs/ndp/ndp026b/ndp026b.htm
Download the of NDP-026B
Download 
 of NDP-026B
FROM SHIPS AND LAND STATIONS OVER THE GLOBE, 1982-1991
Carole J. Hahn
Department of Atmospheric Sciences
Tucson, AZ 85721
Stephen G. Warren
Department of Atmospheric Sciences
Seattle, WA 98195
Julius London
Department of Astrophysical, Planetary and
Atmospheric Sciences
Boulder, CO 80309
Publication No. 4367
Date Published: February 1996
Printed for the
Global Change Research Program
Environmental Sciences Division
Office of Health and Environmental Research
(KP 05 02 00 0)
Printed by the
Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831-6290
managed by
for the
U.S. DEPARTMENT OF ENERGY
under contract DE-AC05-96OR22464
2b. Frequency distribution of extended code values for indicated cloud variables
 in edited light 
, Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center,
Oak Ridge National Laboratory,
 Surface synoptic weather reports for the entire globe for the 10-year period from December 1981
through November 1991 have been processed, edited, and rewritten to provide a data set designed for use
in cloud analyses. The information in these reports relating to clouds, including the present weather
information, was extracted and put through a series of quality control checks. Reports not meeting certain
quality control standards were rejected, as were reports from buoys and automatic weather stations.
Correctable inconsistencies within reports were edited for consistency, so that the "edited cloud report" can
be used for cloud analysis without further quality checking. Cases of "sky obscured" were interpreted by
reference to the present weather code as to whether they indicated fog, rain or snow and were given
appropriate cloud type designations. Nimbostratus clouds, which are not specifically coded for in the
standard synoptic code, were also given a special designation. Changes made to an original report are
indicated in the edited report so that the original report can be reconstructed if desired. While low cloud
amount is normally given directly in the synoptic report, the edited cloud report also includes the amounts,
either directly reported or inferred, of middle and high clouds, both the non-overlapped amounts and the
"actual" amounts (which may be overlapped). Since illumination from the moon is important for the
adequate detection of clouds at night, both the relative lunar illuminance and the solar altitude are given, as
well as a parameter that indicates whether our recommended illuminance criterion was satisfied.
This data set contains 124 million reports from land stations and 15 million reports from ships.
Each report is 56 characters in length. The archive consists of 240 files, one file for each month of data for
land and ocean separately. With this data set a user can develop a climatology for any particular cloud type
or group of types, for any geographical region and any spatial and temporal resolution desired.
 Surface synoptic weather reports are readily available in data sets such as those prepared by the
National Meteorological Center (NMC) and the U. S. Navy Fleet Numerical Oceanography Center
(FNOC). For marine reports there is also the Comprehensive Ocean-Atmosphere Data Set (COADS).
Those data sets are archived at the (NCDC) in Asheville, North Carolina,
and at the (NCAR) in Boulder, Colorado. The data set
described here includes only the information from the synoptic weather report that directly relates to
clouds, as well as some derived quantities that aid in cloud analysis. It was developed as an intermediate
stage in our own global analysis of total cloud cover (Hahn et al., 1994a) and cloud types, but should be
useful to other researchers who wish to compare individual surface cloud reports to concurrent satellite-derived cloud data for example, or who wish to obtain averages over time or space scales not already
provided in existing archives.
 The cloud report provided in this data set, referred to as the "edited cloud report" (ECR, or ECRA
when referring to the archive of all reports), has several features that make it desirable and easy to use in
cloud analyses:
 Synoptic weather reports contain information in addition to clouds, such as air temperature,
pressure, winds, humidity, visibility, past weather and, for ships, sea surface temperature and ocean wave
parameters. The ECR excludes these data, thus reducing the data volume.
 Data sets of synoptic weather reports include reports that do not contain cloud information,
such as those from automated weather stations on land and buoys in the oceans. These are not included in
the ECRA.
The cloud portion of the synoptic report occasionally contains obvious errors or inconsistencies
which must be checked for to avoid inclusion of detectably erroneous data in an analysis. Quality control
procedures developed over years of analyzing surface cloud reports have been applied so that erroneous or
inconsistent reports have either been excluded or, if possible, corrected before inclusion in the archive.
While the amount of low cloud is directly coded in the synoptic report, the amounts of middle
and high clouds are not, but may often be inferred. Where possible for upper level clouds, the ECR
includes both the "actual" cloud amount (sometimes requiring use of the random-overlap assumption) and
the non-overlapped amount, which is simply that portion of the cloud that is visible from below and
requires no assumptions.
Although all reports that meet the above criteria are included in the ECRA, it has been shown
that many of the nighttime reports are made under conditions of insufficient (moon) light for adequate
detection of clouds. Use of such reports results in an underestimate of nighttime cloudiness by about 4%
globally and has a profound influence on computed diurnal cycles in cloudiness (Hahn et al., 1994b).
Reports made under conditions that satisfy the criterion for adequate illumination specified by Hahn et al.
(1994b) are flagged in the ECR, and both the relative lunar illuminance and the solar altitude are given for
each report.
 The edited cloud report archive described here covers the ten-year period December 1981 to
November 1991. These beginning and ending months were chosen to coincide with the boundaries of the
traditionally-defined seasons December-January-February (DJF), March-April-May (MAM), June-July-August (JJA) and September-October-November (SON). Since December 1981 is considered to be part of
DJF 1982, the 10-year period is referred to as 1982-1991. This particular 10-year period was selected to
coincide with the International Satellite Cloud Climatology Project (ISCCP; Rossow and Schiffer, 1991)
and to extend our previous climatologies (Hahn et al., 1988; Warren et al., 1986 {hereafter referred to as
W86}; Warren et al., 1988 {hereafter referred to as W88}), which terminated in (November) 1981.
 Non-standard terms used in the following discussions are defined in the glossary of terms and abbreviations in 
The NMC data set (obtained from NCAR) was the source of the synoptic weather reports used for
land stations. About 144 million reports (22 gigabytes of data) were processed. Only those stations assigned official station numbers by the (WMO) were used. Synoptic
reporting hours are 00, 03, 06, 09, 12, 15, 18, 21 Greenwich Mean Time (GMT). In the NCAR archive the
6-hourly reports (00,06,12,18 GMT) are stored in separate files from the intermediate 3-hourly reports
(03,09,15,21 GMT) and we processed them in tandem for each month. Within each of these two groups the reports are sorted by time.
 The COADS Interim Product CMR5 Reports (Woodruff et al., 1987) were the source of the ship
data used (also obtained from NCAR). About 22 million reports (540 megabytes of data in packed binary
format) were processed. Many of these reports are from buoys, however, and do not contain cloud
information. For an individual month these data are sorted first by 2-degree latitude x longitude boxes and
then by day and hour. COADS merges a dozen or so subsets of ship data and, as such, is the most
extensive record of climatic data for the sea surface. However, the Interim Products available at the time
of our analysis lack much of the digitized ship logbook data from foreign countries which may be delayed
2 - 5 years (Woodruff et al., 1992). Thus future releases of COADS will contain more data than were utilized here.
 Synoptic weather reports are coded according to the system given by the World Meteorological
Organization (WMO, 1988). The information in these reports that relates to cloud analysis is summarized
in . All other parameters were ignored in our processing. A more detailed breakdown of the
definitions of the cloud and weather types, as used here, is given in . The table shows the synoptic
codes that correspond to various precipitation types (ww codes) as well as the codes that correspond to the various cloud types defined within each of the three reporting levels: low, middle and high (C).
 We give special consideration to the cloud type nimbostratus (Ns), which is not specifically
defined in the synoptic code. Codes C= 2 or 7 may signify Ns but may also signify As or Ac,
respectively. We consider these codes to signify Ns when there is concurrent precipitation in the form of
drizzle, rain, or snow as indicated in the present weather code ww (symbolized in Table 2 as D, R and S,
respectively). To distinguish Ns from As/Ac we "extend" the synoptic code for CM to include the values
12 and 11 to represent these cases of C= 2 and 7, respectively. The extended code values (shown in
Table 2) are entered in the edited cloud report (Section 4) without loss of the information content in the original report.
 Nimbostratus is also considered to be present when C= / and specified combinations of
precipitation and low cloud types are present (Table 2). These cases are given the extended code C= 10.
This definition for nimbostratus has been simplified from that used in our previous work (W86, W88).
Cases of C=/ with low stratus and drizzle are no longer defined to be Ns. This will cause a slight
reduction in computed Ns amounts (Section 5C).
Special consideration is also given to the case of N=9 (sky obscured). If ww indicates that the sky
was obscured due to F, Ts, or DRS (symbols defined in Table 2), the cloud type is considered to be Fg,
Cb, or Ns, respectively, and is given the extended code C=10, respectively, and the
value of N is set to 8 oktas.
 All the changes described here are coded in a parameter called "the change code" (Section 3C
below) which is also included in the edited cloud report (Section 4), so that unchanged reports could be
reconstructed if desired.
 A cloud report may be suitable for total cloud analysis even if cloud type information is
incomplete. Certain inconsistencies within the cloud type portion of the report may, however, make the
whole report suspect and cause it to be rejected even for total cloud analysis. The processing and quality
control checks performed on each weather report read from the original archives (NMC or COADS) and
designed to ensure suitability for total cloud analysis are shown in the flow chart in . The
percentage of reports discarded at each stage of the processing, which is discussed in the following
paragraphs, is indicated.
 In the early stages of processing, land and ship reports required slightly different checks (upper
portion of Figure 1). A land station that did not have a WMO station number was discarded (most of these
were from the United States), thus ensuring more uniformity in reporting procedures. A ship report known
to be from a buoy (by the "deck" number in the COADS data) was discarded. Any report that had no
cloud information (N=/) was discarded.
 In 1982 WMO introduced several changes in the coding procedure (WMO, 1988). One of these
changes now instructs observers to set ww=/ if present weather was either "not available" or "observed
phenomena were not of significance" (ww codes 00-03 are considered to represent phenomena without
significance). The present weather indicator, I, is used to distinguish these cases. Land station reports
with I=3 (data
not available) were also discarded because without ww it is not possible to interpret cases of N=9 (see
W86) or to evaluate the occurrence of precipitation. I=2 indicates that observed phenomena were not of
significance, while Ix is coded as "1" when ww is given. Occasionally I=1 when ww=/; these inconsistent
reports were also discarded.
 Examination of the NMC data set showed that while land stations adopted this new coding
procedure almost immediately, I was not consistently coded in ship reports until 1985, as ship observers
tended to continue reporting ww in accordance with the old rules. The COADS data set does not even
contain I.
 At the upper horizontal dashed line in Figure 1, 125 million land reports and 15.8 million ship
reports remained. The discard fractions below the line are fractions of these numbers. If the reported
latitude and longitude of a land station put the station on water (rare) or if reported latitude and longitude
of a ship put the ship on land (0.3%), the report was discarded. A land station was considered to be on
water (or a ship on land) if the 5x5 degree latitude x longitude box in which it was reported to reside was
100% ocean (or land) as defined in W86. Exceptions to this are that a number of boxes with small islands
were allowed to contribute to the land data and reports from the Great Lakes and the Caspian Sea were
allowed to contribute to the ship data.
 If the sky was obscured (N=9) by fog (ww=F; 1.1% land, 2.7% ship), thunderstorms-showers
(ww=Ts, abbreviated as T in the figure; 0.05% land, 0.1% ship), or drizzle-rain-snow (ww=DRS,
abbreviated here as R; 0.4% land, 0.9% ship), the sky was considered to be overcast (N=8). This source
of "cloudiness" contributed about 1% to the total cloud cover globally, and much more in some locations
and seasons (Hahn et al., 1992). Clouds could not be inferred if the sky was obscured for other reasons,
such as blowing dust or snow, and such reports were discarded. The change code, IC=1 (discussed in
Section 3C below), signifies that a report came through the N=9 branch of the processing. Thus 1.5% of
the land reports and 3.7% of the ship reports had N=9 with the ww codes D, R, S, F or Ts.
 Other data consistency checks indicated in Figure 1 ensure that the low cloud amount is not greater
than the total cloud cover, that precipitation (as defined in Table 2) is not reported with a clear sky, and
that if cloud is present (and types are reported), some cloud type must be indicated in at least one of the
three possible levels (this test actually discards a report if N&#62;0 and C&#60;/=0). The re-coding indicated in the lower left box in the figure is necessary because of a 1982 code change (WMO,
1988) that instructs observers to set C=/ when N=0 (this requires special attention in cloud type
analysis and will be discussed in Section 4).
 The number of reports that survive these tests and are suitable for total cloud analysis (referred to
as "total reports") is 124.2 million for land and 14.7 million for ships. Of these, 90.3 million and 11.1
million, respectively, were made under sufficient solar or lunar illuminance (referred to as "light reports")
to meet the established illuminance criterion for adequate cloud visibility (Hahn et al., 1994b).
 The ability of surface observers to adequately detect clouds at night has been questioned for many
years (e.g. Riehl, 1947; Schneider et al., 1989). In an attempt to find a practical solution to this "night-detection-bias", Hahn et al. (1994b) analyzed ten years of nighttime data for the zone 0-50&amp;$176; N and plotted
reported cloud cover as a function of the illumination due to moonlight, which depends on the phase and
altitude (angle above or below the horizon) of the moon and on the distance of the moon from the earth.
The amount of total cloud reported at night increased as the lunar illuminance increased up to a certain
threshold, after which the reported cloud cover leveled off. This threshold is referred to as "the
illuminance criterion" and corresponds to the twilight produced by the sun at an altitude of about 9 degrees below the horizon. Thus the illuminance criterion is met when either the sun is at an altitude greater than -9&#176; or the position of the moon is such that its illuminance exceeds the threshold. These conditions were
determined for each report with the use of an ephemeris and the latitude, longitude, date and time of the
report.
 This illuminance criterion was applied in analyses of total cloud cover and clear-sky frequency
(Hahn et al., 1994a). (Fog and precipitation frequencies were also analyzed in that study but their
detection does not depend on illumination). Application of the illuminance criterion increased the
computed global average total cloud cover at night by about 4% and thus increased the daily average
computed cloud cover by about 2%. Diurnal cycles of total cloud cover over land, which typically show
daytime maxima, were reduced in amplitude when compared to previous studies which did not use the
illuminance criterion (W86). Over the oceans, the increased computed nighttime cloud cover was often
sufficient to result in nighttime maxima, in contrast to the daytime maxima previously reported (W88).
Preliminary surveys conducted in conjunction with the present work suggest that we should expect
similarly dramatic effects on analyses of middle and high clouds but little effect on low clouds.
 Because of the importance of moonlight in the detection of clouds at night, parameters relating to
the illuminance criterion are included in the edited cloud report (Section 4). Reports for which the
illuminance criterion is met are referred to as "light reports", as opposed to "dark reports" (for which the
criterion is not met) or "all reports" (which includes both light and dark).
 The reports that failed the cloud type consistency checks shown in Figure 1 were discarded. Other
inconsistencies are possible which may be correctable or may provide cause simply to reject the report for
cloud type analysis. As the synoptic reports were processed, any inconsistency encountered required a
change to be made in the existing code before the report was entered into the edited cloud report archive.
Any changes thus made are noted by assigning a "change code" (IC) to that report. This change code (with
values 0 to 9) is preserved in the ECR (Section 4) so that modifications made to the original report can be
identified.
 Details of the cloud type processing following the total cloud stage shown in Figure 1 are
presented in the form of the FORTRAN code in . Each segment of the table (delineated by a
change code heading) describes the processing of a particular type of inconsistency or change. The
changes associated with particular coded cases are described briefly in along with the frequency of
occurrence of each change type. (The changes referred to by IC=1 were discussed in section 3B.) Most of
the inconsistencies under consideration have been discussed previously (W86, W88) but are summarized
here.
 For a report to provide useful cloud type information, both Nh and CL must be given. If either is
missing (and not correctable) then the report cannot be used for cloud type analysis and all cloud type
variables are set to -1 for consistency (see segment IC_5 in Table 3). Thus if any inconsistency is
discovered that cannot be corrected, simply setting Nh=-1 will result in exclusion of the report from cloud
type analyses. For example, the IC_2,4 segment in Table 3 examines the case in which there is middle
cloud but no low cloud. In such a case Nh should give the middle cloud amount. In some reports Nh was
improperly set to 0 (W86). If there is also no high cloud then it must be that Nh=N and the report can be
corrected (IC=2). But if high cloud is present, then the value of Nh is indeterminate, and set to -1 (IC=4),
and the report cannot be used for cloud types (in such cases all cloud type variables are set to -1 in segment
IC_5).
 The situation is similar in segment IC_3,4. If only high cloud is present, Nh should properly be 0
but is sometimes given the value of N by an observer. This is readily corrected (IC=3). But if Nh&#60;N in
such a case, the report is irreconcilably inconsistent and must be rejected for cloud type analysis (set Nh=-1
and IC=4).
 Segments IC_6 and IC_9 simply correct cases of sloppy reporting of middle and high clouds, such
as reporting C=/ when the sky is overcast with low cloud.
 Segments IC_7 and IC_8 merely set C to represent our definition of Ns as a convenience for
future cloud type analyses. As is usually the case, the original report can be reconstructed if desired.
 The order in which some of these consistency checks is performed is also important to the
outcome. For example, if segment IC_8 were performed before segment IC_6, then some cases of Ns
would go undetected. Also, segment IC_9 must be performed after IC_8 for the same reason. However
since it is not desirable to have the change code IC=8 overwritten by the relatively trivial change IC=9, this
latter code is only entered in IC (although the change is made) if no previous change has been made
(second part of segment IC_9 in Table 3). This co-occurrence of change codes should be rare since N is
usually large when Ns is present.
 From Table 4 we see that some change is made in 12% of land reports and 16% of ship reports,
but that roughly half of the changes just represent classifying an observation as Ns, Cb or fog. Thus less
than 5% of land reports and less than 9% of ship reports have been changed due to inconsistencies and
most of these are due to the relatively trivial cases with IC=6 (and IC=9 for ships).
 After passing the cloud type consistency checks, the number of light reports available for cloud
type analysis for 1982-91 is 88 million for land and 9.4 million for the ocean (). Reports suitable
for cloud type analysis (C and Nh &#62; -1) are referred to as "type reports".
 The synoptic code contains two cloud amount variables, N and Nh. The amount of low cloud, if
present, is directly specified by Nh. While the amounts of upper level clouds are not directly specified,
they may often be inferred. Thus when C=0, the amount of middle cloud is given by Nh, and when
C=0, the amount of high cloud is given by N. If all three levels are present there are too few known
variables to determine the upper cloud amounts. If two levels are present, the amount in the upper level
may be estimated if the extent of overlap is assumed.
 In the ECR we provide amounts that utilize the random overlap assumption, where necessary, in
order to best represent the actual cloud amounts (the fraction of the sky covered by a cloud type, whether
visible or not). We also provide the non-overlapped amounts which require no assumptions but which
indicate only the amount of the upper level cloud visible from below. (Satellite-derived cloud amounts are
typically given as the non-overlapped amounts visible from above.) Tian and Curry (1989) tested the
minimum, maximum and random overlap assumptions and found the maximum overlap assumption to be
best for adjacent cloud layers, while the random overlap assumption was best for vertically separated
layers.
 gives our method, in the form of FORTRAN code, for determining the actual and non-overlapped amounts of middle and high clouds from a synoptic weather report. A few points should be
noted. The random overlap equation (lines 17 and 38) is invoked only when Nh&#60;7. , which gives
the outcomes of the possible combinations of N and Nh in the equation, shows that only 2 outcomes are
possible for the upper cloud amount when Nh=7, namely 0 and 8 oktas, making this a highly inaccurate
determination (W86). In such cases the upper cloud amount is left undetermined. If the upper cloud in
question is Ns, however, the maximum overlap assumption is employed and the Ns amount is assigned the
value of N (lines 13-14, Table 6). In this case the nimbostratus cloud layer is likely to be adjacent to or
continuous with the low cloud, so the maximum overlap assumption is more appropriate (Tian and Curry,
1989). Also, certain arbitrary decisions are sometimes required, such as our choice, in line 7 of Table 6, toallow middle cloud to be computed when C=/. This choice is justifiable since such a case tends to occur
with large N so that any error induced by this situation would be small.
 The number of times reports were processed through the possible paths in Table 6 are listed in
. Light reports (for which the illuminance criterion was met) and dark reports (for which the
illuminance criterion was not met) are both shown, where possible, for comparison. Land and ocean data
were processed separately. Non-overlapped (NOL) amounts were computable in more than 90% of the
cloud type reports since one can know that a cloud cannot be seen even if one does not know whether it is
present. Thus the non-overlapped amount of an upper level cloud is frequently zero.
 Percentages are not explicitly shown in the table but it can be seen that upper level clouds are
reported more frequently in the set of light reports than in the set of dark reports (38% and 30%,
respectively, for land middle clouds, and 44% and 29%, respectively, for ocean middle clouds, for
example). When upper clouds are present, they are more frequently computable within the set of dark
reports and random overlap (ROL) is less often required. Comparing land and ocean, upper level clouds,
when observed to be present, are less likely to be computable from ocean data and are more likely to
require ROL because of the predominance of low level clouds over the oceans. (The percentages given
here merely represent the fractions of reports within the data set and are not area-weighted global
averages.)
 shows the variables included in the ECR, the number of characters allocated for each, and
the maximum and minimum values allowed. Each item in the table is discussed briefly below. Sample
reports selected from ship and land data for 1981 December and 1982 January are provided in .
These reports are in the order in which they appear in their respective files (see next section) though these
selections are not consecutive within the file. The reports are numbered in the table for convenience.
 Item 1: The first item in the report gives the year, month, day and GMT hour of the report, with 2
characters allotted for each. There are no spaces ("3", for example, is given as "03") so that the entire item
can be read as a single integer. Only the last 2 digits of the year (1900's) are given. Months are coded as
01 through 12, representing January through December.
 Item 2: The IB variable indicates whether the illuminance criterion of Hahn et al. (1994b) was
satisfied (IB=1) at the time and place of the report or not (IB=0). This variable can be checked in lieu of
SA and RI (items 19 and 20 below) if one accepts the criterion specified in Hahn et al. (1994b).
Item 3: The latitude (in degrees north and south) is given to 2 decimal places and written as a 5-digit integer, and thus must be divided by 100 to obtain actual latitude. Actual values range from +90 to -90 for 90N to 90S, respectively.
 Item 4: The longitude (in degrees east) is given to 2 decimal places and written as a 5-digit
integer, and thus must be divided by 100 to obtain actual longitude. Actual values range from 0 to 360E.
 Item 5: For land stations, ID is the WMO station number (WMO, 1977). For ships, ID is the card
deck assignment (Slutz et al., 1985).
 Item 6: This parameter indicates whether a report is from a land station (LO=1) or a ship (LO=2).
 Items 7-13: These weather and cloud variables are coded as specified by WMO (1988) except that
items 11 and 12 have been "extended" as described in Section 3A (Table 2). Also, cases of N=9 (item 8)
that were not discarded have been converted to N=8. Any such conversion is coded in the "change code"
(item 18 below). The value "-1" indicates missing data. Item 8 (N) does not obtain a value of -1 in this
data set since all such reports were discarded during processing. Item 10 (h) may have a value of 9 only
when a cloud is present since h was set to -1 in cases of N=0 (Figure 1).
 Items 14-15: These variables give the "actual" cloud amounts of middle and high clouds and
utilize the random overlap equation where necessary (Section 3D). Values are given in oktas to 2 decimal
places and written as 3-digit integers, so they must be divided by 100 to obtain the actual values. An
actual value of 9 (coded value 900) indicates missing data.
 Items 16-17: These variables give the non-overlapped cloud amounts of middle and high clouds
and represent the amount of cloud visible from below (Section 3D). Values are given in oktas. A value of
9 indicates missing data.
 Item 18: The change code indicates whether a change was made to the original report during
processing. Code values are defined briefly in Table 4 and in detail in Figure 1 and Table 3 (Section 3C).
A change code of 0 means that no change was made other than the trivial change of converting /'s to 0's in
the case of N=0. Examples of reports with each change code are provided in Table 10.
 Items 19-20: These variables give the solar and lunar parameters needed to determine the
illuminance provided by the sun or moon for the date, time and location of the report (Section 3B1). SA is
the altitude of the sun above the horizon, given to a tenth of a degree (divide the coded value by 10 to
obtain the actual value). RI is the lunar relative illuminance defined by Hahn et al., (1994b). RI= PHI sin(A)
(R), where A is the lunar altitude, r is the earth-moon distance, R is the mean earth-moon distance, and
PHI is the lunar phase function which varies from 0 to 1 in a concave shape such that a full moon is 10 times
as bright as a half moon (Hapke, 1971). The illuminance criterion of Hahn et al. (1994b) is met (IB=1,
item 2) when SA&#62;/=-9&#176; or RI&#62;0.11. (A negative value of RI means the moon was below the horizon.)
 The data are divided into 240 files, one for each month for ten years for land and ocean separately.
These files range in size from 5.0 to 8.4 MB for the ocean data and from 49.8 to 63.5 MB for the land data.
 In the NMC data set archived at NCAR, the 6-hourly reports and 3-hourly reports (Section 2) are
stored on separate files. Each of these subsets is sorted first by time and then by latitude and longitude.
Each land data file of the ECRA was formed by merging the 6-hourly and the 3-hourly data so that for
each month the reports appear in time order.
 The sort used in the COADS Interim Product (Section 2) was first by 2-degree box, then by time,
and finally by latitude and longitude for each month. For the ECRA files, the reports were re-sorted by
time and then by latitude and longitude.
 Figure 1 and Tables 4, 5 and 8 showed the number of reports processed, deleted and changed, as
well as the number of light reports, the number suitable for cloud type analysis, and the number of times
upper level cloud amounts were computable. shows how the reports are distributed over the
synoptic reporting times. Land stations usually report 8 times per day but some do not (notably in the
United States and Australia), so that 59% of all reports are made during the 6-hourly times. Ships,
however, tend to report at the 6-hourly times and only about 10% of the ship reports are for the
intermediate 3-hourly times. Having only 4 reports per day, rather than 8, limits the resolution possible in
computations of the phase and amplitude of the diurnal cycle. It was also noted (W88) that regionalaverages formed from 6-hourly ship data may be uniformly different from averages formed from 3-hourly
data, consistent with a tendency for some ships to give a 3-hourly report only in unusually stormy weather.
A bias is also possible when averaging over a land grid box that has more than one station if stations
within one climatic region report 8 times per day while stations within a different climatic region report 4
times per day.
 The histograms in for ocean show the frequency of occurrence of the
extended code values for the six cloud variables for light reports in the archive of edited cloud reports. [In
these figures N=9 is shown separate from N=8 although N=9 appears as N=8 (with IC=1) in the ECR.]
The shaded areas show the occurrence of precipitation (DRSTs, Table 2). Numerical values for the data
shown in these figures are provided in . Several interesting features are evident in these
figures. The distribution of codes for total cloud cover N is nearly U-shaped for land but strongly skewed
towards the higher amounts for oceans. 96.5% of all precipitation occurs with N&#62;/=7 over land and with
N&#62;/=6 over oceans. About 75% of precipitation occurs with Nh&#62;/=6. The reports with Nh=-1 are not usable
for cloud type analysis. The most commonly occurring cloud base height code is h=5 (600-1000m) over
land and h=4 (300-600m) over oceans. The high frequency of h=9 over land is a consequence of the high
occurrence of C=0 so that h=9 often refers to the middle cloud level.
 The lower panels in Figures 2a and 2b show the occurrences of various cloud types within the
three reporting levels. The occurrence of C=-1 is the same as Nh=-1 due to the processing procedure and
is the fraction of reports that do not contain information relating to cloud types (2.6% for land data, 15.3%
for ocean data). A larger fraction of the reports have C=-1 (33.2% for land, 50.9% for ocean) because of lower overcast. Thus 97.4% of the land reports have
information about cloud types but only 82% of those have information about the middle cloud level and
66% about high clouds. For the oceans, 84.7% of the reports have low cloud information but only 57% of
those have middle cloud information and 40% have high cloud information.
 The low cloud type most commonly reported over land is stratocumulus (C=5). While this type
is also relatively common over the oceans, it is exceeded by the cumulus types C= 1 and 2. About 25%
of all precipitation occurs with the stratus cloud C=7 is reported over land, precipitation is
present in 67% of the reports. Precipitation occurs in 34% of the ship reports of C=7.
 While 58% (land) and 46% (ocean) of all precipitation occurs with the middle clouds defined to be
nimbostratus (C= 10,11,12), 25% and 38%, respectively, of precipitation occurs when the middle cloud
level is not given in the report (typically because of low overcast). Because of our definition of Ns shown
in Table 2, most of these latter cases must have ww= D or Ts. In the high cloud level, 90% of all
precipitation occurs in reports with C=-1 (high cloud level not reported, usually because of lower
overcast).
 The occurrence of reports of sky-obscured (N=9) due to fog or precipitation is 1.5% for land and
3.5% for ocean, with fog (C=11) accounting for more than two thirds of these values for both land and
ocean (Figure 2 and Appendix A). These cases of sky-obscured due to fog make up 14% (land) and 48%
(ocean) of all reported cases (light) of fog. Cases of thunderstorms or showers (C=10) account for onlyabout 3.5% of the reports of sky obscured, and sky-obscured due to thunderstorms or showers make up
only 1.6% (land) and 5.8% (ocean) of the light reports of thunderstorms and showers. The remaining
contribution to the reports of sky obscured (about one quarter) is due to drizzle, rain or snow. Sky-obscured due to drizzle, rain or snow make up 5.1% (land) and 12.9% (ocean) of the light reports of
drizzle, rain and snow.
 A report of sky-obscured due to drizzle, rain or snow is considered to indicate nimbostratus cloud
and is given the extended code value C=10 with IC=1 (Tables 2 and 4). Two other sets of circumstances
are considered to indicate Ns as well. shows the contributions of the three major paths to the
frequency of Ns within the light type reports. (Frequencies based on light reports are slightly higher
than the frequencies quoted in the last paragraph which were based on the total set of light reports.) The
largest contributor to Ns in the land data is the path through C=2,7 (with ww=DRS). For both land and
ocean C=11,12 in Appendix A). The largest contributor to
Ns in the ocean data comes through the C=/ path, which has several contributors itself, the largest being
the case of C=7 with DRS.
 Excluded from the definition of Ns are the cases of C=4,5,6,8 and ww=D (more than
half of these cases are due to C=6 alone). These cases were considered to indicate Ns in our previous
climatologies (W86, W88) but after subsequent consideration and discussions with colleagues we
concluded that since drizzle could occur from these low cloud types, the additional inference of Ns above
them was inappropriate. Thus the frequencies of occurrence of Ns computed under the current definition
will be reduced to about 97% (land) and 90% (ocean) of the frequencies given in W86 and W88.
 Another change associated with the simplification of our previous definition of Ns involves cases
of C 6,7 in these cases were previously reassigned as
Ns, but are left unchanged in the present, simplified definition. This results in a further reduction in
computed Ns frequency by factors comparable to those in the last paragraph. Thus the Ns frequencies
computed under the present definition may be about 94% (land) and 81% (ocean) of those computed under
the previous definition. Note that these percentages refer to the number of reports in the data set which
contains a disproportionate contribution of reports from the densely populated northern mid-latitudes and
thus do not represent the area-weighted global averages. Note also that the user of this data set is not
restricted to the definitions assigned here since all the information necessary for any other interpretation is
contained in the edited cloud reports. The definitions discussed above apply only if the reports are used
exactly as written.
 The cases of C=/ and ww=DRS are not considered to indicate nimbostratus
cloud.
 To show the global distribution of the reports, numbers (shown as log10) of light type reports are
displayed on a 5c grid (see Glossary in Appendix B) in (ocean). Numbers from
1-9 appear as 0, numbers from 10-99 appear as 1, etc. Grid boxes with no light type reports are blank.
 A number of biases which can affect analyses of clouds from surface observations are summarized
in W88. Four biases which we can measure and possibly correct for are described in more detail here.
 The is largely eliminated by using only data for which the illuminance
criterion is met (Section 3B1). This, however, enhances the unless precautions are
taken since less than half as many nighttime observations will be available compared to the number of
daytime observations. Thus Hahn et al. (1994a) prepared nighttime and daytime averages separately and
averaged the two together to obtain the average cloud cover.
 Another potential bias for cloud type analyses was introduced by the synoptic code change in 1982
which allowed observers to record a "/" for cloud types when N=0. Previously a report with N=0 and C
or Nh =/ would indicate a station that never reports cloud types and the report would be omitted from the
cloud type analysis. Now every occurrence of N=0 must be treated as C=0 and Nh=0. Thus a report
from a station or ship which never reports cloud types would contribute to a cloud type analysis only when
the sky was clear, producing a : the frequency of occurrence of clear sky computed from the
cloud type reports would be too high and the frequencies of occurrence of the various cloud types would be
too low. The magnitude of this bias can be estimated by counting the number of times observers within a
grid box omit cloud types (Nh=/ or C=/) when N&#62;0 and assuming that the same fraction of the cases of
N=0 would be from stations or ships that do not report cloud types, and thus should be excluded from the
denominator when determining the frequency of occurrence of a cloud type.
 =/
(or Nh=/) in light reports with N&#62;0 (this bias fraction is referred to as fb). (Note that when computing
these fractions using the ECRA, reports of Nh=-1 with IC=4 must not be counted in fb since these values
were set during data processing and not by the observer.) In the land data, extremely large values occur
only in northern Alaska (87%, underlined in Figure 4a) and in northeast Greenland (72%). Ship data show
large values in the Great Lakes region of North America where values exceed 90% and in some European
waters where values are as great as 82%. Values of fb average about 3% for land data and about 10% for
ship data.
 To determine how much effect this bias would have on computed cloud type frequencies, the
"clear-sky adjustment factor" (AF0) was defined such that Fa = AF0 &#183; Fr, where Fa is the adjusted
frequency of occurrence of some cloud type and Fr is the frequency that would be computed using the
potentially biased cloud type reports. Since Fr = Nt / Nr, where Nt is the number of occurrences of a
particular cloud type and Nr is the number of reports contributing to the cloud type analysis, and Fa = Nt /
(Nr - fb &#183; N0), where N0 is the number of occurrences of N=0 and fb is the fraction of N0 that should be
discounted, then, using f0 = N0 / Nr, Fa can be represented as Fa = Nt / (Nr - fb &#183; f0 &#183; Nr) = Nt / (Nr &#183; (1 -
fb &#183; f0)) = Fr / (1 - fb &#183; f0). Thus AF0 = 1 / (1 - fb &#183; f0) and is equal to one if either fb or f0 is zero.
 show the global distribution of AF0 {displayed as 100 x (AF0-1)} over land and
ocean, respectively. This analysis shows that, on average, cloud type frequencies, if uncorrected, would be
reduced only to about 99.5% of their correct values by this bias (average AF0 = 1.003 for land and 1.007
for ocean) and that most regions of the globe are essentially unaffected. However a few regions are greatly
affected, namely northern Alaska, northeastern Greenland, the Great Lakes, and some seas around Europe.
These are the regions with high values of fb (Figures 4a and 4b). The two most extreme regions, the Great
Lakes and northern Alaska, have biased values 41% and 27% of their correct values. Other than the AF0
values of 3.68 in Alaska and 1.31 in Greenland, no land box has a value greater than 1.08. In the ocean
data, moderate values of AF0 (around 1.10) occur in the Middle East where clear-sky frequencies are high
(W88), and several higher values are seen in the seas of Europe and in the Great Lakes of North America.
While it may be desirable to apply this adjustment factor to regions of moderately large AF0 values,
practical application of this correction will be complicated by the fact that AF0 values vary from year to
year, season to season, and day to night. Fortunately correction is unnecessary over most regions of the
globe and the regions noted in Figures 5a and 5b for large adjustment factors can simply be eliminated
from a cloud type analysis.
 Note that while cloud type frequencies are subject to the clear-sky bias because of the coding
instructions and practices for cloud type reports, the frequency of occurrence of clear sky itself (and also
the frequency of fog) can be computed without this bias by using the total cloud data set to which this bias
does not pertain (as was done in Hahn et al., 1994a).
 Our recognition of certain cases of N=9 as overcast cloud (Section 3B) is important in obtaining
accurate estimates of the amounts of fog and nimbostratus cloud, but may introduce the ,
which is similar in principle to the clear-sky bias discussed above. Since C=/ whenever N=9, it is not
possible to distinguish stations or ships that normally report cloud types from those that do not. Thus the
latter stations will contribute to the cloud type analysis only when the sky is obscured (aside from the case
of clear sky which was discussed above). This will tend to cause the computed frequencies of fog and
nimbostratus cloud to be too large and the frequencies of other cloud types to be reduced. The fraction fb
shown in Figures 4a and 4b is again a measure of the potential of this bias. A "sky-obscured adjustment
factor" (AF9) is defined in a manner similar to that for AF0 defined above such that Fa = AF9 &#183; Fr and
AF9 = 1 / (1 - fb &#183; f9), where f9 is the frequency of occurrence of N=9 in cloud type reports.
The global distribution of f9 is given in . The box in northern Alaska
(underlined), which was shown previously to have fb=0.87 (Figure 4a), also has the relatively large value
of 0.16 for f9 which gives AF9=1.16. Inspection of Figures 4a and 6a together shows that this is the
largest AF9 value for land data and that in most regions the value of AF9 is near 1.00. Ship data have
larger fb values (Figure 4b) and larger f9 values (Figure 6b) than land data. Also the large values are
distributed over larger regions. The largest f9 values occur, again, in the Great Lakes region where they
combine with fb to produce AF9 values that approach 2. In the North Pacific, where large amounts of fog
occur during the summer season (W88), moderately large f9 values (&#126;0.20) occur with moderate fb values
(&#126;0.11), giving AF9=1.02 which is a relatively small bias. The global average values for AF9 are 1.0003
for land and 1.003 for the ocean. Thus, aside from the few regions specially noted to be removed from
cloud type analysis, the sky-obscured bias is generally small. Any bias in the frequency of fog itself can be
eliminated by computing it from the total cloud reports, as mentioned above. Any bias towards increasing
the nimbostratus frequency will be small since N=9 contributes only a small portion of the total
nimbostratus (Table 12) and will be compensated somewhat by the tendency towards reducing the
frequency of Ns contributed by the C=/ paths.
 The determination of the average cloud amounts and frequencies of occurrence from surface
observations requires some special considerations to avoid various potential biases and to obtain
representative values. Upper level clouds present special problems because they are sometimes partially or
completely hidden from the view of the observer by lower clouds. These issues are discussed in detail in
W86 and W88 but will be highlighted here.
 Total cloud cover is basically the sum of the values of N in the synoptic code (converted to percent
if desired) divided by the number of contributing reports. However, to avoid the day-night bias discussed
above, some method of equalizing the contribution of reports between day and night is necessary. In W86,
averages were obtained by first forming averages for the 8 synoptic hours and then averaging these 8
numbers. For oceans, where data are less plentiful, this method will result in significant loss of data
because the 3-hourly times often do not have a sufficient number of reports to obtain a statistically reliable
average. Therefore, Hahn et al. (1994a) divided the day into two 12-hour periods, 0600-1800 local time
("day") and 1800-0600 local time ("night"), and averaged these two numbers. Note that when using only
the light reports (to avoid the night-detection bias) to form monthly averages, only about two weeks of data
will contribute to the nighttime average in any single month. Due to this "monthly-sampling error" there
will be more scatter in monthly averages from year to year although multi-year averages should become
more statistically representative of climatological means as the number of contributing years is increased.
Similarly, seasonal averages should be more representative of an individual season than monthly averages
are of an individual month.
 These considerations of the day-night bias, night-detection bias, and monthly-sampling error apply
equally well to cloud type analyses discussed below. However, for quantities such as fog and precipitation,
whose detection does not depend on illumination, all observations may be used, minimizing all three of
these biases.
 Of the 90.3 million light reports suitable for total cloud analysis for land (Figure 1), 88.0 million
have cloud type information (Table 5). For the ocean these numbers are 11.1 million and 9.4 million. In
the type reports, the amount of a low cloud type (if present) is always given in the Nh variable of the
report. The average amount for a particular low cloud type can be obtained, in a manner similar to that for
total cloud amount, by summing the Nh values when the type is present and dividing by the number of
contributing reports (using the precautions against the day-night bias discussed above and adjusting for the
small clear-sky and sky-obscured biases if desired). The contributing reports consist of those with C&#62;/=0
and Nh&#62;/=0 and include reports of N=0. An alternative, but equivalent, method for obtaining the average is
to compute the frequency of occurrence (f) of the type (the number of occurrences of the type divided by
the number of contributing reports) and the amount-when-present (awp; sum of Nh's divided by the
number of occurrences of the type) separately. Then the average amount is avg = f awp. This latter
method is described because it is often of interest to know the frequency of occurrence of a type in addition to its amount, because awp tends to be characteristic of a cloud type, and because this is the method used
in computing upper level cloud type amounts.
 Cloud type reports do not always contain information about upper level clouds because they may
be hidden by an overcast or near-overcast layer of lower clouds. Thus, of the 88.0 million light type
reports for land (Table 8), only 74.4 million have information about the middle cloud level (C&#62;/=0) and
60.3 million have information about the high level (C&#62;/=0). Of the 9.4 million light type reports for the
oceans, 7.1 million have C&#62;/=0.
 The average amounts of upper level cloud types are obtained as described in the last section: avg
= f x awp. Since we want the actual frequency of occurrence of a cloud type, and not just the frequency
with which it is visible, f is computed as the number of times the type was observed divided by the number
of reports of C). For land, middle and high cloud frequencies
are determined from 84.5% and 68.5% of the light type reports, respectively. For the oceans these values
are 75.5% and 58.5%, respectively. The question of the degree to which these portions of the data set
represent the whole data set for types is discussed in W86 and W88. Based on a study of the frequency of
occurrence of As/Ac [f(As,Ac)] versus low cloud amount, Warren et al. (W88) applied an adjustment to
f(As,Ac) which assigned to the cases of C=/ (15.5% of the type reports for land and 24.5% for ocean) a
value that is the average of f(As,Ac) of the reports that have low cloud amounts of 3 to 7 oktas. For high
clouds, f was computed only from reports with Nh&#60;7 in order to reduce the partial-undercast bias (W88).
 The amount-when-present of an upper cloud type can be determined, when it is reported present
(C&#62;0), only if there are at most 2 cloud levels present. In addition, amounts are not computed for an
upper cloud if it is undercast by a layer which covers 7 oktas or more of the sky (Section 3D). Therefore
awp is computed from an even smaller pool of data than that used for frequency computations. Table 8
shows that, for land, 78% of the observed (light) occurrences of middle clouds and 75% of the observed
occurrences of high clouds are computable. For the ocean data these values are 61% and 43%,
respectively. Nevertheless, awp computed from these data is probably fairly representative of the actual
awp (W86 and W88) and any error in awp results in a smaller error in avg by the factor f. Any systematic
error inherent in the random-overlap assumption would produce a smaller error in computed a mounts since
this assumption is used for only a fraction of the computable observations. Table 8 shows that the random-overlap assumption is used in 39% of the computable observations (light) of middle cloud and in 55% for
high cloud over land. These fractions are larger for ocean data with random overlap used for 60% of the
computable middle clouds and 70% of the computable high clouds.
 Special note about Ns: Because Ns is defined on the basis of the occurrence of precipitation
(Table 2) which does not depend on the visibility of the middle cloud level for its detection, its presence or
absence is known for every type report. Thus the number of contributing reports for f(Ns) is the same as
that for low cloud types (C&#62;/=0 and Nh&#62;/=0). However, when present, its amount is not always known and a
separate tally (which will be different from that for the As/Ac clouds) must be kept for determining its
awp.
This documentation and the data described herein are available from:
 Oak Ridge National Laboratory
 Post Office Box 2008
 Oak Ridge, TN 37831-6290, U.S.A.
 Telephone (865) 574-3645 or (865) 574-0390
 or
 Data Support Section
 Boulder, CO 80307, U.S.A.
 Telephone (303) 497-1215.
The following should be used for referencing this archive and/or this documentation report:
 Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, TN. (Also available from Data Support Section,
National Center for Atmospheric Research, Boulder, CO.)
The archive of our earlier climatology (Hahn et al., 1988) and the accompanying atlases (Warren
et al., 1986, 1988) are also available from the same sources listed above.
 This work was supported by NASA Grant NAG-1-998 and by Battelle Pacific Northwest
Laboratories, Atmospheric Radiation Measurement Program (Contract 144806-A-Q1). We also acknowledge the long term cooperation and provision of computing facilities by the Scientific Computing Division of the National Center for Atmospheric Research.]]></Descriptive_file>
      <Data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp026b/ndp026b.doc]]></Data_file>
      <Data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp026b/ndp026b.txt]]></Data_file>
      <Data_IO_file></Data_IO_file>
      <Initial_date_of_data_publication><![CDATA[19960201]]></Initial_date_of_data_publication>
      <Most_recent_date_of_data_publication><![CDATA[19960201]]></Most_recent_date_of_data_publication>
      <Data_file_location><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp2/ndp026b/]]></Data_file_location>
      <Total_size_of_all_files><![CDATA[2.08 GB]]></Total_size_of_all_files>
      <Distribution><![CDATA[external]]></Distribution>
      <CDIAC_contact><![CDATA[Dale Kaiser; email: kaiserdp@ornl.gov]]></CDIAC_contact>
      <Notes><![CDATA[ Surface synoptic weather reports for the entire globe for the 10-year period from December 1981 through November 1991 have been processed, edited, and rewritten to provide a data set designed for use in cloud analyses. The information in these reports relating to clouds, including the present weather information, was extracted and put through a series of quality control checks. Reports not meeting certain quality control standards were rejected, as were reports from buoys and automatic weather stations. Correctable inconsistencies within reports were edited for consistency, so that the edited cloud report can be used for cloud analysis without further quality checking. Cases of sky obscured were interpreted by reference to the present weather code as to whether they indicated fog, rain or snow and were given appropriate cloud type designations. Nimbostratus clouds, which are not specifically coded for in the standard synoptic code, were also given a special designation. Changes made to an original report are indicated in the edited report so that the original report can be reconstructed if desired. While low cloud amount is normally given directly in the synoptic report, the edited cloud report also includes the amounts, either directly reported or inferred, of middle and high clouds, both the non-overlapped amounts and the actual amounts (which may be overlapped). Since illumination from the moon is important for the adequate detection of clouds at night, both the relative lunar illuminance and the solar altitude are given, as well as a parameter that indicates whether our recommended illuminance criterion was satisfied.
<br><br>
 This data set contains 124 million reports from land stations and 15 million reports from ships. Each report is 56 characters in length. The archive consists of 240 files, one file for each month of data for land and ocean separately. With this data set a user can develop a climatology for any particular cloud type or group of types, for any geographical region and any spatial and temporal resolution desired. ]]></Notes>
    </CDIAC>
  </mercury>
</metadata>
