<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin><![CDATA[Jones, M. H.]]></origin>
        <origin><![CDATA[Curtis, P. S.]]></origin>
        <title><![CDATA[Database of Herbaceous Vegetation Responses to Elevated Atmospheric CO2]]></title>
        <geoform></geoform>
        <onlink><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/xml/cdp/metadata/Tom_Boden/NDP_073.xml]]></onlink>
        <onlink><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/ndp073/]]></onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract><![CDATA[Database of Herbaceous Vegetation Responses to Elevated Atmospheric CO2]]></abstract>
      <supplinf></supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate><![CDATA[1900000]]></begdate>
          <enddate><![CDATA[1900000]]></enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress></progress>
      <update> As appropriate</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc></westbc>
        <eastbc></eastbc>
        <northbc></northbc>
        <southbc></southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>CDIAC</themekt>
        <themekey><![CDATA[atmospheric CO2]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[herbaceous vegetation]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[database ]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[vegetation responses ]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[elevated atmospheric CO2]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[NDP-073]]></themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Thematic Area</themekt>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Place Keywords</placekt>
        <placekey></placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Thomas A. Boden; email: bodenta@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntfax></cntfax>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg></cntorg>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Thomas A. Boden; email: bodenta@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice></cntvoice>
        <cntfax></cntfax>
        <cntemail></cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc></resdesc>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/]]></computer>
            <accinstr></accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20120918 150935</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntper><![CDATA[Thomas A. Boden; email: bodenta@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice></cntvoice>
        <cntemail></cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  </metainfo>
  <Local-Control-Number>Created 20050809 165142 by 160.91.18.40</Local-Control-Number>
  <mercury>
    <begdate></begdate>
    <enddate></enddate>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[atmospheric CO2]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[herbaceous vegetation]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[database ]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[vegetation responses ]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[elevated atmospheric CO2]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[NDP-073]]></Keywords>
    <Documentation_Link>
      <Text><![CDATA[Contributed by
Michael H. Jones
Peter S. Curtis
Department of Evolution, Ecology, and Organismal Biology
Prepared by Robert M. Cushman and Antoinette L. Brenkert
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
Publication No. 4909
Prepared for the
Prepared by the
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831-6290
managed by
LOCKHEED MARTIN ENERGY RESEARCH CORP.
for the
under contract DE-AC05-96OR22464
PAP_NO = 3034
PARAM = PN
SOURCE = F1
X_ELEV = 44.400
SE_ELEV = 0.100
CV*_ELEV = 0.694
and
PAP_NO = 2723
PARAM = PN
SOURCE = F4
X_ELEV = 40.120
SE_ELEV = 0.505
PAP_NO = 2184
PARAM = TILLERS
SOURCE = T2
X_ELEV = 726.000
SE_ELEV = 52.000
CV*_ELEV = 28.203
and
PAP_NO = 2717
PARAM = TILLERS
SOURCE = F1
X_ELEV = 4.590
SE_ELEV = 0.400
 38AGWT G PLANT-1 TRITICUM AESTIVUM ANGIO GRASS_CC3 GRASS
330
660UL L-1 461.45 GC SEED H2O LO 10 ML PL-1 D-1 F4
3.61 -9.99 -9.99 -9.99 10 5.13 -9.99 -9.99 -9.99 10 .
 38AGWT G PLANT-1 TRITICUM AESTIVUM ANGIO GRASS_CC3 GRASS
330
660UL L-1 371.45 GC SEED H2O CTL 40 ML PL-1 D-1 F4
2.98 -9.99 -9.99 -9.99 10 3.97 -9.99 -9.99 -9.99 10 .
 3042PN UMOL M-2 S-1 ZEA MAYS ANGIO GRASS_CC4 GRASS 330
640UBAR 305 GH SEED FERT HI . F2
64.80 2.10 5.94 9.45 8 52.40 0.90 2.55 5.01 8 Y
 3042PN UMOL M-2 S-1 ZEA MAYS ANGIO GRASS_CC4 GRASS 330
640UBAR 305 GH SEED FERT LO . F2
27.90 1.84 5.20 19.24 8 21.90 2.10 5.94 27.97 8 Y
*SAS data retrieval routine to read ndp073.dat;
data ndp073;
infile 'ndp073.dat';
input PAP_NO 6. @7 PARAM $char7. P_UNIT $ 14-27 GENUS $ 28-40
 SPECIES $ 41-53 DIV1 $ 54-59 DIV2 $ 60-66 DIV3 $ 67-71
 DIV4 $ 72-77 AMB $ 78-80 ELEV $ 81-84
 CO2_UNIT $ 85-94 TIME $ 95-99 POT $ 100-112 MTHD $ 113-116
 STOCK $ 117-125 XTRT $ 126-131 LEVEL $ 132-138 QUANT $ 139-155
 SOURCE $ 156-161 X_AMB 162-169 SE_AMB 170-177 SD_AMB 178-185
 CV_AMB 186-192 N_AMB 193-197 X_ELEV 198-206 SE_ELEV 207-213
 SD_ELEV 214-221 CV_ELEV 222-229 N_ELEV 230-235 SDC $ 236-238 ;
* In the above INPUT statement, the variables CV*_AMB and CV*_ELEV have
 been renamed CV_AMB and CV_ELEV, respectively.;
proc print;
run;
C *** Fortran program to read the file "ndp073.dat"
C
 INTEGER PAP_NO, N_AMB, N_ELEV
C
 REAL X_AMB, SE_AMB, SD_AMB, CV_AMB, X_ELEV, SE_ELEV,
 + SD_ELEV, CV_ELEV
C
 CHARACTER PARAM*7, P_UNIT*14, GENUS*13, SPECIES*13, DIV1*6,
 + DIV2*7, DIV3*5, DIV4*6, AMB*3, ELEV*4, CO2_UNIT*10,
 + TIME*5, POT*13, MTHD*4, STOCK*9, XTRT*6, LEVEL*7,
 + QUANT*17, SOURCE*6, SDC*3
C
 OPEN (UNIT=1, FILE='ndp073.dat')
C
C Note that the variables CV*_AMB and CV*_ELEV have
C been renamed CV_AMB and CV_ELEV, respectively
C
 10 READ (1,100,END=99) PAP_NO, PARAM, P_UNIT, GENUS, SPECIES,
 + DIV1, DIV2, DIV3, DIV4, AMB, ELEV, CO2_UNIT, TIME, POT,
 + MTHD, STOCK, XTRT, LEVEL, QUANT, SOURCE, X_AMB, SE_AMB,
 + SD_AMB, CV_AMB, N_AMB, X_ELEV, SE_ELEV, SD_ELEV, CV_ELEV,
 + N_ELEV, SDC
C
 100 FORMAT (I6,A7,A14,2A13,A6,A7,A5,A6,A3,A4,A10,A5,A13,A4,A9,
 + A6,A7,A17,A6,3F8.2,F7.2,I5,F9.2,F7.2,2F8.2,I6,A3)
C
 GO TO 10
 99 CLOSE (UNIT=1)
 STOP
 END
Agropyron caninum
Agropyron smithii
Agrostis capillaris
Andropogon gerardii
Avena barbata
Avena fatua
Avena sativa
Bouteloua curtipendula
Bouteloua eriopoda
Bouteloua gracilis
Briza subaristata
Bromus erectus
Bromus hordaeceus
Bromus willdenowii
Calamagrostis epigejos
Carex curvula
Dactylis glomerata
Digitaria macroblephara
Digitaria sanguinalis
Echinochloa crusgalli
Eleusine indica
Eriophorum vaginatum
Festuca arundinacea
Festuca durviscula
Festuca elatior
Festuca idahoensis
Festuca ovina
Festuca pratense
Festuca rupicola
Festuca vivipara
Hordeum vulgare
Lolium boucheanum
Lolium multiflorum
Lolium perenne
Nardus stricta
Oryza sativa
Panicum antidotale
Panicum laxum
Panicum millioides
Pascopyrum smithii
Paspalum dilatatum
Pennisetum clandestinum
Phalaris aquatica
Phleum pratense
Poa alpina
Poa annua
Poa pratensis
Puccinellia maritima
Rottboellia exaltata
Schizachyrium scoparium
Scirpus olneyi
Setaria faberi
Sorghum bicolor
Sorghum helpense
Spartina patens
Sporobolus kentrophyllus
Stipa occidentalis
Themeda triandra
Triticum aestivum
Vulpia microstachys
38. Andre, M., and H. Du Cloux. 1993. Interaction of CO2 Enrichment and Water
Limitations on Photosynthesis and Water-Use Efficiency in Wheat. Plant
Physiology and Biochemistry 31:103-112.
186. Drake, B. G. 1992. A Field Study of the Effects of Elevated CO2 on
Ecosystem Processes in a Chesapeake Bay Wetland. Australian Journal of Botany
40:579-595.
488. Nie, D., H. He, M. B. Kirkham, and E. T. Kanemasu. 1992. Photosynthesis
of a C3 Grass and a C4 Grass under Elevated CO2. Photosynthetica 26:189-198.
618. Ryle, G. J. A., C. E. Powell, and V. Tewson. 1992. Effect of elevated co2
on photosynthesis, respiration and growth of perennial ryegrass. Journal of
Experimental Botany 43:811-818.
754. Ziska, L. H., and J. A. Bunce. 1993. Inhibition of Whole Plant
Respiration by Elevated CO2 as Modified by Growth Temperature. Physiologia
Plantarum 87:459-466.
765. Baker, J. T., L. H. Allen Jr., and K. J. Boote. 1992. Response of Rice to
Carbon Dioxide and Temperature. Agricultural and Forest Meteorology
60:153-166.
2066. Samarakoon, A. B., W. J. Muller, and R. M. Gifford. 1995. Transpiration
and leaf area under elevated CO2: Effects of soil water status and genotype in
wheat. Australian Journal of Plant Physiology 22:33-44.
2119. Greer, D. H., W. A. Laing, and B. D. Campbell. 1995. Photosynthetic
responses of thirteen pasture species to elevated CO2 and temperature.
Australian Journal of Plant Physiology 22:713-722.
2125. Baxter, R., M. Gantley, T. W. Ashenden, and J. F. Farrar. 1994. Effects
of elevated carbon dioxide on three grass species from montane pasture.
Journal of Experimental Botany 45:1267-1287.
2132. Rao, M. V., B. A. Hale, and D. P. Ormrod. 1995. Amelioration of
ozone-induced oxidative damage in wheat plants grown under high carbon
dioxide. Plant Physiology 109:421-432.
2133. Tuba, Z., K. Szente, and J. Koch. 1994. Response of photosynthesis,
stomatal conductance, water use efficiency and production to long-term
elevated CO2 in winter wheat. Journal of Plant Physiology 144:661-668.
2158. Gloser, J., and M. Bartak. 1994. Net photosynthesis, growth rate and
biomass allocation in a rhizomatous grass Icalamagrostis epigejos grown at
elevated CO2 concentration. Photosynthetica 30(1):143-150.
2159. Ziska, L. H., and J. A. Bunce. 1994. Increasing growth temperature
reduces the stimulatory effect of elevated CO2 on photosynthesis or biomass in
two perennial species. Physiologia Plantarum 91:183-190.
2168. Knapp, A. K., E. P. Hamerlynck, and C. E. Owensby. 1993. Photosynthetic
and water relations responses to elevated CO2 in the C4 grass Andropogon
geradii. International Journal of Plant Science 154(4):459-466.
2184. Saebo, A., and L. M. Mortensen. 1995. Growth and regrowth of Phleum
pratense, Lolium perenne, Trifolium repens and Trifolium pratense at normal
and elevated O2 concentration. Agriculture, Ecosystems and Environment
55:29-35.
2192. Knapp, A. K., J. T. Fahnestock, and C. E. Owensby. 1994. Elevated
atmospheric O2 alters stomatal responses to variable sunlight in a C4 grass.
Plant, Cell and Environment 17:189-195.
2202. Wilsey, B. J., S. J. McNaughton, and J. S. Coleman. 1994. Will increases
in atmospheric O2 affect regrowth following grazing in C4 grasses from
tropical grasslands? Oecologia 99:141-144.
2208. Crush, J. R. 1994. Elevated atmospheric O2 concentration and rhizosphere
nitrogen fixation in four forage plants. New Zealand Journal of Agricultural
Research 37:455-463.
2211. Morgan, J. A., W. G. Knight, L. M. Dudley, and H. W. Hunt. 1994.
Enhanced root system C-sink activity, water relations and aspects fo nutrient
acquisistion in mycotrophic Bouteloua gracilis subjected to CO2 enrichment.
Plant and Soil 165:139-146.
2227. Bowler, J. M., and M. C. Press. 1993. Growth responses of two
contrasting upland grass species to elevated CO2 and nitrogen concentration.
New Phytologist 124:515-522.
2229. Mitchell, R. A. C., V. J. Mitchell, S. P. Driscoll, J. Franklin, and D.
W. Lawlor. 1993. Effects of increased CO2 concentration and temperature on
growth and yield of winter wheat at two levels of nitrogen application. Plant,
Cell and Environment 16:521-529.
2246. Baxter, R., T. W. Ashenden, T. H. Sparks, and J. F. Farrar. 1994.
Effects of elevated carbon dioxide on three montane grass species. Journal of
Experimental Botany 45 (272):305-315.
2300. Bassirirad, H., D. T. Tissue, J. F. Reynolds, and F. S. Chapin. 1996.
Response of Eriophorum vaginatum to CO2 enrichment at different soil
temperature: effects on growth, root respiration and PO-4 uptake kinetics. New
Phytologist 133:423-430.
2312. Wilsey, B. J. 1996. Urea additions and defoliation affect plant
responses to elevated CO2 in a C3 grassland from Yellowstone National Park.
Oecologia 108:321-327.
2315. Casella, E., J. F. Soussana, and P. Loiseau. 1996. Long-term effects of
CO2 enrichment and temperature increase on a temperate grass sward. 1.
Productivity and water use. Plant and Soil 182:83-99.
2316. Soussana, J. F., E. Casella, and P. Loiseau. 1996. Long-term effects of
CO2 enrichment and temperature increase on a temperate grass sward. 2. Plant
nitrogen budgets and root fraction. Plant and Soil 182:101-114.
2329. Jones, M. B., M. Jongen, and T. Doyle. 1996. Effects of elevated carbon
dioxide concentrations on agricultural grassland production. Agricultural and
Forest Meteorology 79:243-252.
2330. Stewart, J., and C. Potvin. 1996. Effects of elevated CO2 on an
artificial grassland community: competition, invasion and neighbourhood area.
Functional Ecology 10:157-166.
2337. Saebo, A., and L. M. Mortensen. 1996. The influence of elevated CO2
concentration on growth of seven grasses and one clover species in a cool
maritime climate. Acta Agriculturae Scandinavia Section B-Sorland Plant
Science 46:49-54.
2341. Schappi, B., and C. Korner. 1996. Growth responses of an alpine
grassland to elevated CO2. Oecologia 105:43-52.
2342. Jackson, R. B., and H. L. Reynolds. 1996. Nitrate and ammonium uptake
for single and mixed species communities grown at elevated CO2. Oecologia
105:74-80.
2345. Hakala, K., and T. Mela. 1996. The effects of prolonged exposure to
elevated temperatures and elevated CO2 leveles on the growth, yield and dry
matter partitioning of filed-sown meadow fescue. Agricultural and Food Science
in Finland 5(3):285-298.
2347. Jackson, R. B., Y. Luo, Z. G. Cardon, O. E. Sala, C. B. Field, and H. A.
Mooney. 1995. Photosynthesis, growth and density for the dominant species in a
CO2 enriched grassland. Journal of Biogeography 22:221-225.
2350. Teughels, H., I. Nijs, P. Van Hecke, and I. Impens. 1995. Competition in
a global change environment: The importance of different plant traits for
competitive success. Journal of Biogeography 22:297-305.
2351. Campbell, B. D., W. A. Laing, D. H. Gree, J. R. Crush, H. Clark, D. Y.
WIlliamson, and M. D. J. Given. 1995. Variation in grassland populations and
species and the implications for community responses to elevated CO2. Journal
of Biogeography 22:315-322.
2357. Chu, C. C., C. B. Field, and H. A. Mooney. 1996. Effects of CO2 and
nutrient enrichment on tissue quality of two California annuals. Oecologia
107:433-440.
2358. Ferris, R., I. Niy, T. Bejaeghe, and I. Impens. 1996. Contrasting CO2
and temperature effects on leaf growth of perennial rye grass in spring and
summer. Journal of Experimental Botany 47:1033-1043.
2362. Wheeler, T. R., G. R. Batts, R. H. Ellis, P. Hadley, and J. J. L.
Morison. 1996. Growth and yield of winter wheat (Triticum aestium) crops in
response to CO2 and temperature. Journal of Agricultural Science 127:37-48.
2363. Volin, J. C., and P. B. Reich. 1996. Interaction of elevated CO2 and O3
on growth, photosynthesis and respiration of three perennial species grown in
low and high nitrogen. Physiologia Plantarum 97:674-684.
2364. Miglietta, F., A. Giuntoli, and M. Bindi. 1996. The effect of free air
carbon dioxide enrichment (FACE) and soil nitrogen availability on the
photosynthetic capacity of wheat. Photosynthesis Research 47:281-290.
2366. Ziska, L. H., W. Weerakoon, O. S. Namuco, and R. Pamplona. 1996.
Influence of nitrogen on the elevated CO2 response in field-grown rice.
Australian Journal of Plant Physiology 23:45-52.
2367. Saebo, A., and L. M. Mortensen. 1996. Growth, morphology and yield of
wheat, barley and oats grown at elevated atmospheric CO2 concentration in a
cool maritime climate. Agriculture, Ecosystems and Environment 57:9-15.
2369. Ziska, L. H., P. A. Manalo, and R. A. Ordonez. 1996. Intraspecific
variaiton in the response of rice (Oryza sativa L) to increased CO2 and
temeprature: growth and yield response of seventeen cultivars. Journal of
Experimental Botany 47:1353-1359.
2372. Nijs, I., H. Teughels, H. Blum, G. Hendrey, and I. Impens. 1996.
Simulation of climate change with infrared heaters reduces the productivity of
Lolium perenne L in summer. Environmental and Experimental Botany 36:271-280.
2379. Veisz, O., N. Harnos, L. Szunies, and T. Tischner. 1996. Overwintering
of winter cereals in Hungary in the case of global warming. Euphytica
92:249-253.
2383. Nijs, I., and I. Impens. 1996. Effects of elevated CO2 concentration and
climate-warming on photosynthesis during winter in Lolium perenne. Journal of
Experimental Botany 47:915-924.
2387. Leadley, P. W., and J. Stocklin. 1996. Effects of elevated CO2 on model
calcareous grasslands: Community, species, and genotype responses. Global
Change Biology 2:389-397.
2395. Tuba, Z., K. Szente, Z. Nagy, Z. Csintalan, and J. Koch. 1996. Responses
of CO2 assimilation, transpiration and water use efficiency to long-term
elevated CO2 in perennial C3 xeric loess steppe species. Journal of Plant
Physiology 148:356-361.
2398. Mortensen, L. M., and A. Saebo. 1996. The effects of elevated CO2
concentration on growth of Phleum pratense L. in different parts of the growth
season. Acta Agriculturaie Scandinavia Section B-Soil and Plant Science
46:128-134.
2401. Jackson, R. B., and A. L. Reynolds. 1996. Nitrate and annomium uptake
for single- and mixed species communities grown at elevated CO2. Oecologia
105:74-80.
2403. Fanymeier, A., U. Geuters, U. Hesstein, H. Sandhagel, A. Hoffmann, B.
Vermebren, and A. J. Jager. 1996. Effects of elevated CO2, nitrogen supply and
tropospheric ozone on spring wheat. 1. Growth and Yields. Environmental
Pollution 91:381-390.
2407. Kinball, B. A., P. J. Pinter, R. L. Garcia, R. L. La Mort, G. W. Wall,
D. J. Hunsaker, G. WEchsung, F. Wechsung, and T. Kartschall. 1995.
Productivity and water use of wheat under free-air CO2 enrichment. Global
Change Biology 1:429-442.
2420. Hunt, H. W., E. T. Elliot, J. K. Detling, J. A. Morgan, and D. X. Chen.
1996. Responses of a C3 and a C4 perennial grass to elevated CO2 and
temperature under different water regimes. Global Change Biology 2:35-47.
2427. Samarakoon, A. B., and R. M. Gifford. 1996. Elevated CO2 effects on
water use and growth of maize in wet and drying soils. Australian Journal of
Plant Physiology 23:53-62.
2430. Ruget, F., O. Bethenod, and L. Combe. 1996. Repercussions of increased
atmospheric CO2 on maize morphogenesis and growth for various temperature and
radiation levels. Maydica 41:181-191.
2440. Frank, A. B., and A. Bauer. 1996. Temperature, nitrogen and carbon
dioxide effects on spring wheat development and spikelet numbers. Crop Science
36:659-665.
2441. Read, J. J., and J. A. Morgan. 1996. Growth and partitioning in
Pascopyrum smithii (C3) and Bouteloua graciles (C4) as influenced by carbon
dioxide and temperature. Annals of Botany 77:487-496.
2443. Polley, H. W., H. B. Johnson, H. S. Mayeux, D. A. Brown, and J. W. C.
White. 1996. Leaf and plant water use efficiency of C4 species grown at
glacial to elevated CO2 concentrations. International Journal of Plant
Sciences 157:164-170.
2444. Bowler, J. M., and M. C. Press. 1996. Effects of elevated CO2 nitrogen
form and concentration on growth and photosynthesis of a fast- adn
slow-growing grass. New Phytologist 132:391-401.
2448. RowlandBamford, A. J., J. T. Baker, H. L. Allen, and G. Bowes. 1996.
Interactions of CO2 enrichment and temperature on carbohydrate accumulation
and partitioning in rice. Environmental and Experimental Botany 36:111-124.
2454. Bagash, D. Z., M. J. Paul, M. A. J. Parry, A. J. Keys, and D. W. Lawlor.
1995. Increased capacity for photosynthesis in wheat grown at elevated CO2.
The relationship between electron-transport and carbon metabolism. Planta
197:482-489.
2468. Rao, M. V., and L. J. Dekok. 1994. Interactive effects of high CO2 and
SO2 on growth and antioxidant levels in wheat. Phyton-Annales Rei Botanicae
34:279-290.
2474. Newbery, R. M., J. Wolfenden, T. A. Mansfield, and A. F. Harrison. 1995.
Nitrogen, phosphorus and potassium uptake and demand Agrostis capillaria. The
influence of elevated CO2 and nutrient supply. New Phytologist 130:565-574.
2480. Lenssen, G. M., W. E. Vandium, P. Jak, and J. Roxema. 1995. The response
of Aster tripolium and Puccinellia maritima to atmospheric carbon dioxide
enrichment and their interaction with flooding and salinity. Aquatic Botany
50:181-192.
2492. Schenk, U., R. Maderscheid, J. Hugen, and H. J. Weigel. 1995. Effects of
CO2 enrichment and intraspecific competition on biomass partitioning, nitrogen
content, and microbial biomass carbon in soil of perennial rye grass and white
clover. Journal of Experimental Botany 46:987-993.
2502. Jacob, J., C. Greitner, and B. G. Drake. 1995. Acclimation of
photosynthesis in relation to Rubisco and non-structural carbohydrate contents
and in-situ carboxylase activity in Scirpus olnei grown at elevated CO2 in the
field. Plant, Cell and Environment 18:875-884.
2503. Jongen, M., M. B. Jones, T. Hebeisen, H. Blum, and G. Hendrey. 1995. The
effects of elevated CO2 concentrations on the root growth of Lolium perenne
and Trifolium repens grown in a FACE system. Global Change Biology 1:361-371.
2504. Kleemola, J., J. Peltonen, and P. Peltonen-Sainio. 1994. Apical
development and growth of Barley under different CO2 and nitrogen regimes.
Journal of Agronomy and Crop Science 173:79-92.
2510. Demothes, M. A. G., and D. Knoppik. 1994. Effects of long term enhanced
CO2 partial pressure on gas exchange parameters and saccharide pools of wheat
leaves. Photosynthetica 30:435-445.
2521. Balaguer, L., J. D. Barnes, A. Panicucci, and A. M. Borland. 1995.
Production and utilization of assimilates in wheat leaves exposed to elevated
O3 and/or CO2. New Phytologist 129:557-568.
2522. Barnes, J. D., J. H. Ollerenshaw, and C. P. Whitfield. 1995. Effects of
elevated CO2 and/or O3 on growth, development and physiology of wheat. Global
Change Biology 1:129-142.
2525. Hattenschwiler, S., and C. Korner. 1996. System-level adjustments to
elevated CO2 in model spruce ecosystems. Global Change Biology 2:377-387.
2531. Owensby, C. E., P. I. Coyne, J. M. Ham, L. M. Avea, and A. K. Knapp.
1993. Biomass production in a tallgrass prairie ecosystem exposed to ambient
and elevated CO2. Ecological Applications 3:644-653.
2541. Jackson, R. B., O. E. Sala, C. B. Field, and H. A. Mooney. 1994. CO2
alters water use, carbon gain, and yield for the dominant species in a natural
grassland. Oecologia 98:257-262.
2547. Baker, J. T., L. H. Allen, and K. J. Boote 1992. Temperature effects on
rice at elevated CO2 concentration. Journal of Experimental Botany 43:959-964.
2579. Billes, G., H. Rouhier, and P. Bottner. 1993. Modifications of the
carbon and nitrogen allocations in the plant Triticum aestivum L. soil system
in response to increased atmospheric CO2 concentration. Plant and Soil
157:215-225.
2580. Baker, J. T., S. L. Albrecht, D. Pan, L. H. Allen, N. B. Pickering, and
K. J. Boote. 1994. Carbon dioxide and temperature effects on rice (Oryza
sativa L., CV 1R-72). Soil and Crop Science Society of Florida, Proceedings
53:90-97.
2595. Santruce, J., H. Santurckova, J. Kueton, M. Simkoua, and K. Rohacek.
1994. The effect of elevated CO2 concentration on photosynthetic CO2 fixation,
respiration and carbon economy of wheat plants. Rostlinna Vyroba 40:689-696.
2597. Ingaurdsen, C., and B. Veierskov. 1994. Response of young barley plants
to CO2 enrichment. Journal of Experimental Botany 45:1373-1378.
2644. Reeves, D. W., H. H. Royers, S. A. Prior, C. W. Wood, and G. B. Runion.
1994. Elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide effects on sorghum and soybean
nutrient status. Journal of Plant Nutrition 17:1939-1954.
2654. Jackson, R. B., Y. Lou, Z. G. Cardon, O. E. Sala, C. B. Field, and H. A.
Mooney. 1995. Photosynthesis, growth and density for the dominant species in a
CO2 enriched grassland. Journal of Biogeography 22:221-225.
2666. Samarakoon, A. B., and R. M. Gifford. 1995. Soil water content under
plants at high CO2 concentrations and interaction with the direct CO2 effects:
A species comparison. Journal of Biogeography 22:193-202.
2669. Schenk, U., A. J. Jager, and H. J. Weigel. 1996. Nitrogen supply
determine responses of yeild and biomass partitioning of perennial rye grass
to elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations. Journal of Plant
Nurtition 19:1423-1440.
2692. Kimball, B. A., P. J. P. Pinter, R. L. Garcia, R. L. LaMorte, G. W.
Wall, D. J. Hunsaker, G. Wechsung, F. Wechsong, and T. Kartschall. 1995.
Productivity and water use of wheat under free-air CO2. Global Change Biology
1:429-442.
2698. Potvin, C., and L. Vasseur. 1997. Long-term CO2 enrichment of a pasture
community: species richness, dominance, and succession. Ecology 78:666-677.
2709. Hebeisen, T., A. Luscher, and J. Nosberger. 1997. Effects of elevated
atmospheric CO2 and nitrogen fertilisation on yield of Trifolium repens and
Lolium perenne. Acta Oecologica/Oecologia Plantarum 18:277-284.
2710. Hebeisen, T., A. Luscher, S. Zanetti, B. U. Fischer, U. A. Hartwig, M.
Frehner, G. R. Hendrey, H. Blum, and J. Nosberger. 1997. Growth response of
Trifolium repens L and Lolium perenne L as monocultures and bi-species mixture
to free air CO2 enrichment and management. Global Change Biology 3:149-160.
2711. Ghannoum, O., S. vonCaemmerer, E. W. R. Barlow, and J. P. Conroy. 1997.
The effect of CO2 enrichment and irradiance on the growth, morphology and gas
exchange of a C3 (Panicum laxum) and a C4 (Panicum antidotale) grass.
Australian Journal of Plant Physiology 24:227-237.
2715. Cotrufo, M. F., and A. Gorissen. 1997. Elevated CO2 enhances
below-ground C allocation in three perennial grass species at different levels
of N availibility. New Phytologist 137:421-431.
2718. Wilsey, B. J., J. S. Coleman, and S. J. McNaughton. 1997. Effects of
elevated CO2 and defoliation of grasses: A comparative ecosystem approach.
Ecological Applications 7:844-853.
2723. Stirling, C. M., P. A. Davey, T. G. Williams, and S. P. Long. 1997.
Acclimation of photosynthesis to elevated CO2 and temperature in five British
native species of contrasting functional type. Global Change Biology
3:237-246.
2735. Nijs, I., and I. Impens. 1997. An analysis of the balance between root
and shoot activity in Lolium perenne cv Melvina. Effects of CO2 concentration
and air temperature. New Phytologist 135:81-91.
2737. Mortensen, L. M. 1997. Effects of carbon dioxide concentrations on three
grass species grown in mixture in two soil types at different ozone
concentrations or temperatures. Acta Agriculturae Scandinavica, Section B,
Soil and Plant Sciences 47:14-19.
2756. Hamerlynck, E. P., C. A. McAllister, A. K. Knapp, J. M. Ham, and C. E.
Owensby. 1997. Photosynthetic gas exchange and water relation responses of
three tallgrass prairie species to elevated carbon dioxide and moderate
drought. International Journal of Plant Sciences 158:608-616.
2758. Stocker, R., P. W. Leadley, and C. Korner. 1997. Carbon and water fluxes
in a calcareous grassland under elevated CO2. Functional Ecology 11:222-230.
2785. Hungate, B. A., J. Canadell, and F. S. Chapin. 1996. Plant species
mediate changes in soil microbial N in response to elevated CO2. Ecology
77:2505-2515.
2793. Fitter, A. H., G. K. Self, J. Wolfenden, M. M. I. vanVuuren, T. K.
Brown, L. Williamson, J. D. Graves, and D. Robinson. 1996. Root production and
mortality under elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide. Plant and Soil
187:299-306.
2802. Casela, E., and J. F. Soussana. 1997. Long-term effects of CO2
enrichment and temperature increase on the carbon balance of a temperate grass
sward. Journal of Experimental Botany 48:1309-1321.
2821. Schapendonk, A. H. C. M., P. Dijkstra, J. Groenwold, C. S. Pot, and S.
C. vandeGeijn. 1997. Carbon balance and water use effciency of frequently cut
Lolium perenne L swards at elevated carbon dioxide. Global Change Biology
3:207-216.
2834. Baxter, R., T. W. Ashenden, and J. F. Farrar. 1997. Effect of elevated
CO2 and nutrient status on growth, dry matter partitioning and nutrient
content of Poa alpina var vivipara L. Journal of Experimental Botany
48:1477-1486.
2835. Bassirirad, H., J. F. Reynolds, R. A. Virginia, and M. H. Brunelle.
1997. Growth and root NO3- and PO43- uptake capacity of three desert species
in response to atmospheric CO2 enrichment. Australian Journal of Plant
Physiology 24:353-358.
2839. Lin, W. H., L. H. Ziska, O. S. Namuco, and K. Bai. 1997. The interaction
of high temperature and elevated CO2 on photosynthetic acclimation of single
leaves of rice in situ. Physiologia Plantarum 99:178-184.
2855. Wolf, J. 1996. Effects of nutrient supply (NPK) on spring wheat response
to elevated atmospheric CO2. Plant and Soil 185:113-123.
2856. Nakamura, T., M. Osaki, T. Koike, Y. T. Hanba, E. Wada, and T. Tadano.
1997. Effect of CO2 enrichment on carbon and nitrogen interaction in wheat and
soybean. Soil Science and Plant Nutrition 43:789-798.
2892. McKee, I. F., J. F. Bullimore, and S. P. Long. 1997. Will elevated CO2
concentrations protect the yield of wheat from O3 damage? . Plant, Cell and
Environment 20:77-84.
2893. Manderscheid, R., and H. J. Weigel. 1997. Photosynthetic and growth
responses of old and modern spring wheat cultivars to atmospheric CO2
enrichment. Agriculture, Ecosystems and Environment 64:65-73.
2895. Sicher, R. C., and J. A. Bunce. 1997. Relationship of photosynthetic
acclimation to changes of Rubisco activity in field-grown winter wheat and
barley during growth in elevated carbon dioxide. Photosynthesis Research
52:27-38.
2911. Mulholland, B. J., J. Craigon, C. R. Black, J. J. Colls, J. Atherton,
and G. Landon. 1997. Impact of elevated atmospheric CO2 and O3 on gas exchange
and chlorophyll content in spring wheat (Triticum aestivum L). Journal of
Experimental Botany 48:1853-1863.
2919. VanVuuren, M. M. I., D. Robinson, A. H. Fitter, S. D. Chasalow, L.
Williamson, and J. A. Raven. 1997. Effects of elevated atmospheric CO2 and
soil water availability on root biomass, root length, and N, P and K uptake by
wheat. New Phytologist 135:455-465.
2924. Vu, J. C. V., L. H. Allen, K. J. Boote, and G. Bowes. 1997. Effects of
elevated CO2 and temperature on photosynthesis and Rubisco in rice and
soybean. Plant, Cell and Environment 20:68-76.
2928. Ziska, L. H., O. Namuco, T. Moya, and J. Quilang. 1997. Growth and yield
response of field-grown tropical rice to increasing carbon dioxide and air
temperature. Agronomy Journal 89:45-53.
2935. Baker, J. T., L. H. Allen, K. J. Boote, and N. B. Pickering. 1997. Rice
responses to drought under carbon dioxide enrichment. 1. Growth and yield.
Global Change Biology 3:119-128.
3033. Patterson, D. T., and E. P. Flint. 1980. Potential effects of global
atmospheric CO2 enrichment on the growth and competitiveness of C3 and C4 weed
and crop plants. Weed Science 28:71-75.
3034. Potvin, C., and B. R. Strain. 1985. Photosynthetic response to growth
temperature and CO2 enrichment in two species of C4 grasses. Canadian Journal
of Botany 63:483-487.
3035. Potvin, C., and B. R. Strain. 1985. Effects of CO2 enrichment and
temperature on growth in two C4 weeds, Enchinochloa crus-galli and Eleusine
indica. Canadian Journal of Botany 63:1495-1499.
3036. Sionit, N., and D. T. Patterson. 1984. Responses of C4 grasses to
atmospheric CO2 enrichment. I. Effect of irradiance. Oecologia 65:30-34.
3038. Carter, D. R., and K. M. Peterson. 1983. Effects of a CO2 enriched
atmosphere on the growth and competitive interaction of a C3 and a C4 grass.
Oecologia 58:188-193.
3041. Morison, J. I. L., and R. M. Giford. 1984. Plant growth and water use
with limited water supply in high CO2 concentrations. II. Plant dry weight,
partitioning, and water use efficiency. Australian Journal of Plant Physiology
11:375-384.
3042. Wong, S. C. 1979. elevated atmospheric partial pressure of CO2 and plant
growth. I. Interactions of nitrogen nutrition and photosynthetic capacity in
C3 and C4 plants. Oecologia 44:68-74.
Listed are
paper number (PAP_NO, as defined in Sect. 9.)
 CO2 exposure facility
 light
 temperature
 watering
 humidity
 nutrient
 interacting treatment
 biome
 location, and
 comments.
Abbreviations are as described in the body of this report for data files
ndp073.dat and ndp073.wk1.
38
 GC
 600+/-90 UE M-2 S-1
 14/10
 24/18
 40 OR 10 ML PL-1 D-1
 0.588235294
 HOAGLAND'S
 H2O
 GRASS
 EU
186
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 NONE
 CO2 ONLY
 WETL
 NA
488
 GH
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 FIELD CAPACITY OR NONE
 NONE
 CO2 AND WATER
 GRASS
 NA
 2ND YEAR; NO TEMP DATA; FIELD PLANTS.
618
 GC
 AMB
 12H
 20/15 C (DAY/NIGHT)
 WW
 AMB
 NITRATE' SOLUTION
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 .
754
 GC
 0.6 MMOL M-2 S-1
 14 H
 "15, 20, 25, 30 DEG C CONSTANT DAY/NIGHT"
 WW
 &gt;50 %
 COMPLETE NUTRIENT SOLUTION ADDED DAILY
 TEMP
 MEAD
 NA
 MAINTENANCE RESPIRATION RECORDED HERE. GROWTH RESPIRATION
 ALSO REPORTED ONE GC PER CO2 TREATMENT
765
 GC
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 WW
 .
 .
 TEMP
 GRASS_C
 NA
 CONTROL: 28/21/25 C; HI: 40/33/37 C
2066
 GH
 24.8 MOL M-2 D-1
 16 H
 20/14
 .
 .
 COMPLETE FERTILIZER ADDED
 H2O
 GRASS_C
 AU
 TWO VARIETIES USED
2119
 GC
 700 UMOL M-2 S-1
 1/12/00
 12/7; 18/13; 28/23
 WW
 0.4/0.3 +- 0.05 KPA VPD
 HALF-STRENGTH HOAGLAND'S
 TEMP
 GRASS
 AU
 "USABLE DATA ON 4 SPP ONLY, FOR PN"
2125
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW DAILY FC
 AMB
 0.2 MOL M-3 N AND 0.05 MOL M-3 P
 CO2 ONLY
 GRASS
 EU
 "OTHER NUTRIENT DATA, EFFICIENCIES - P,"
2132
 GC
 500 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 25/18
 WW
 50-70
 HOAGLAND'S ALTERNATE DAYS
 O3
 GRASS
 NA
2133
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 NPK APPLIED
 .
 GRASS_C
 EU
2158
 GC
 200 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16 H
 220
 WW
 0.8
 SURPLUS NUTRIENTS
 NONE
 BOREAL
 EU
 "1 GC AT EACH CO2 LEVEL. QY, RHZWT, LWR, LAR"
2159
 GC
 .6 MMOL M-25-1
 14H
 "15,20,25,30"
 WW
 &gt;50%
 """COMPLETE"" IN DAILY WATER"
 TEMP
 GRASS
 NA
2168
 OTC
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
 1991 PRECIPITATION: 17.1 CM; 1992 PRECIPITATION: 26.8 CM; SAMPLE
 SIZE INFERRED FROM DESIGN. LFY.MD
2184
 OTC
 AMBIENT
 15-18
 12-Nov
 AMB AND DRIP
 .
 ADDED WITH DRIP WATER; AMT NOT STATED
 HARVEST
 GRASS
 EU
 CLIPPED TO 5CM AT EACH HARVEST
2192
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 CO2
 GRASS
 NA
 "DATA USED FROM LAST MEASUREMENT PRIOR TO SHADING, F2."
2202
 GC
 725-890 UE
 .
 .
 WW
 .
 HOAGLAND'S; 2 G/M2 N WEEKLY
 CLIPPING TO 5 CM
 GRASS
 AF
 C4; SPOROBOLUS KENTROPHYLLUS; ADDT'L LF NUTRIENTS AVAILABLE IN T1
2208
 GC
 700 UMOL M-2
 12 H
 .
 WW
 AMB
 FERT
 TEMP
 GRASS_C
 NA
 THERE ARE TWO LOLIUM HYBRIDS (2N AND 4N). EACH ONE WAS TREATED
AS A
 SPECIES.
2211
 GH
 ~900 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 25/16
 WW
 35/90
 NONE
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
2227
 GC
 600 UMOL M-2 S-1 AT SEEDLING HT
 15/9
 20/15
 WW
 65/70
 0.8 NM NH4NO3 + 50% LONG ASHTON SOLUTION
 "HI N, LOW N"
 GRASS
 EU
2229
 GC
 AMB
 .
 +4C
 .
 .
 HI/LOW
 TEMP/FERT
 GRASS_C
 EU
2246
 OTC
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 WW
 AMBIENT
 "WEEKLY 1/5 MODIFIED LONG ASHTON- 0.2 MOL M-3 N, 0.05 MOL M-3 P"
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 "NAR, LAR, LWR"
2300
 GC
 800 UMOL/M2S ACTIVE RADIATION
 18 H
 15 C
 WATERED DAILY TO SATURATION
 .
 HALF-STRENGTH MODIFIED HOAGLAND SOLUTION WITH AMMONIUM
NITRATE AND P
 CONCENTRATION OF 32 PPM
 "SOIL TEMPERATURE (5,15, AND 25 C)"
 TUNDRA
 NA
 THIS STUDY FOCUSES ON THE EFFECTS OF SOIL TEMPERATURE. RATE OF PO4
 ABSORPTION WAS LEFT OUT.
2312
 GC
 615 UE (603-621)
 23/11
 100 ML EACH 3 D
 NOT CONTROLLED
 C= HOAGLAND'S T=HOAGLAND'S + UREA (40 G/M2)
 "UREA, CLIPPING"
 GRASS
 NA
 RINSED SAND; CONTROLS HAD HOAGLAND'S
2315
 GH
 AMB/SEASONAL
 AMB/SEASONAL
 AMB/SEASONAL
 SEASONAL; SUMMER WW/DEFICIT
 .
 N-= 160 KG/HA YR; N+=530 KG/HA YR
 "N HI, LO"
 GRASS
 EU
 2 YR STUDY; MICROCLIMATE DETAILS AVAIL. PKS ALSO APPLIED. DATA
USED
FROM
 SUMMER DROUGHT ONLY.
2316
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 IRRIGATION AT AMB LEVELS
 AMB
 160 OR 530 KG N HA-1 YR-1
 FERT
 GRASS
 EU
 "PLASTIC TUNNELS. SWARDS, SOWN. PERIODIC CLIPPING OF ALL PLOTS."
2329
 OTC
 REDUCED ~20%
 AMB
 "AMB + 1-2 DAY, 0-1 NIGHT"
 WW
 .
 NPK; 600 KG N/HA FOR SEASON
 CLIPPING
 GRASS
 EU
 SOWN IN GROUND. DATA FROM 2 GROWING SEASONS. CO2 TMNT YR-ROUND
2330
 OTC and GC
 "OTC= AMBIENT, GC NOT AVAILABLE"
 "OTC=AMBIENT, GC=NOT AVAILABLE"
 "OTC= AMBIENT, GC= FOLLOWED AMBIENT"
 "OTC= AMBIENT, GC= EVERY 1-3 DAYS"
 "OTC= AMBIENT, GC= NOT AVAILABLE"
 GROWTH CHAMBERS; 5-10-15 NPK PLUS MICRONUTRIENTS. 2 ML/H EVERY TWO
WEEKS
 COMPETITION AND METHOD (OTC AND GC)
 GRASS
 NA
 "GC (PH = 6.5) PHOTOPERIOD, LIGHT AND HUMIDITY ARE REPORTED IN
WANT,
 LECHOWICZ AND POTWIN (1994). COMPETING SPECIES (TRIFOLIUM REPENS,
POA
 PRATENSIS, PHLEUM PRATENSE, AGROSTIS STOLONIFERA) NO INDIVIDUAL
POTS."
2337
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB; X=11.3
 DRIP
 AMB
 "YES, UNKNOWN"
 NONE
 MEAD
 EU
 COMMON SPP + CULTIVARS; NORWAY; MARITIME
2341
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB/WW
 AMB
 NPK 1.5:1:1.5; =40 KG N HA-1 Y-1
 "CO2, NUTRIENTS"
 EU
 3 YR EXP. OTCS UP 98-108 D Y-1. SOME DATA ALSO FROM YEARS 1 &amp; 2
2342
 OTC
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 "N, P, K 20 G M-2, 120 DAY TIME-RELEASE OSMOCOTE"
 "ADDITIONAL NUTRIENTS N, P, K"
 GRASS
 NA
 MONOCULTURES OF SIX SPECIES AND ONE MIXED COMMUNITY. SERPENTIME
SOIL
2345
 otc
 amb
 AMR
 AMB; AMB +3
 WW
 .
 NPK + NUTRIENTS
 TEMP
 GRASS
 EU
 OTCS PLACED IN GH FOR WARMING
2347
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 NONE
 CO2 ONLY
 GRASS
 NA
 JASPER RIDGE
2350
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 17
 WW
 .
 7 G M-2 N; 5 G M-2 P; 7 G M-2 K
 CLIPPING EVERY 4 WK
 GRASS
 EU
 "ALSO INCLUDED TEMP, CO2 X TEMP, MIXTURES OF SPP"
2351
 GC
 700 UMOL M-2 S-1
 12
 12/7; 18/13; 28/23
 WW
 .
 HALF-STRENGTH HOAGLAND'S GX D-1
 TEMP
 GRASS
 AU
 GROWN IN STERILE SAND
2357
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 OSMOCOTE: 20 G M
 NUTRIENTS
 GRASS
 NA
 JASPER RIDGE
2358
 GH
 AMB; 640 UMOL M-2 S-1
 AMB; 640 UMOL M-2 S-1
 13-26
 WW
 0.08
 13 G N M-2; 3.18 G P M-2; 10.61 G K M-2
 TEMP (+4)
 GRASS
 EU
 GERMINATION IN POTS IN FIELD; CO2 BEGAN AFTER ~6.5 MONTHS
2362
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 13;10
 WW
 .
 NOT LIMITING
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 TUNNELS = GH
2363
 GC
 552 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14 H
 26/21
 WW
 60-70%
 HALF STRENGTH HOAGLAND'S; N=6 OR .5 mM
 O3 + FERT
 GRASS
 NA
 "OZONE = 3 +/- .3, 92 +/- .4 nMOL MOL-1; FERT = 6 OR .5 nM N.
 MACRONUTRIENTS SAME FOR HI/LO FERT TMNT."
2364
 FACE
 AMB
 .
 .
 .
 .
 .
 .
 GRASS_C
 EU
 MINIFACE
2366
 OTC
 89% OF AMB
 AMB
 32 / 24.9
 WW
 .
 .
 FERT
 GRASS_C
 AS
 NO SUPPLEMENTAL N
2367
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 IRRIGATED WITH NUTRIENT ENRICHED WATER
 NONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
 .
2369
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 29/21 OR 37/29
 WW
 70 +/- 5
 PROVIDED
 WETL
 WETL
 AS
 29/21= CTL; 37/29 = HI TEMP (PC.1354). 17 CULTIVARS TREATED AS REPS
2372
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 "AMB/AMB+2.5, 18-30"
 WW
 AMB
 7 G N M-2
 TEMP
 GRASS
 EU
 "TEMP INCREASE USING INFRA-RED LAMPS ALL MATERIAL CLIPPED PRIOR
 TO START OF TEMP TMT. EFFECTIVE CO2 DURATION USED. 12- AGWT, LFN, PN"
2379
 GC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 .
 NONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
 10 CULTIVARS TREATED AS REPS.
2383
 GH
 .
 AMB
 AMB AND AMB+4
 WW
 .
 FERTILIZED
 TEMP
 GRASS_C
 EU
2387
 GH
 AMB- ~MAX=800 UMOL M-2 S-1
 "16, W LIGHTS"
 18/10-24/18
 WW 1X WK-1
 .
 NO ADDITIONAL
 "330, 500, 660 UL L-1 CO2"
 GRASS
 EU
 "CALCEROUS GRASSLAND. SPP AND ECOSYS 76 PLANTS/ CONTAINER
 REPRESENTING FIELD %, PESTICIDES USED."
2395
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WATERED OCCASIONALLY
 AMB
 .
 .
 GRASS
 EU
 THE SPECIES GROW IN A XERIC TEMPERATE LOESS STEPPE.
2398
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB (~11)
 WW
 ..
 "ADDED, BUT NOT SPECIFIC; SEE TEXT."
 SEASONALITY
 GRASS
 EU
 USING GRAND MEANS AND SE ONLY; NOT USING SEASONAL DATA.
2401
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 AMB
 LOW/HI NPK
 FERT
 GRASS
 NA
2403
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 150 KG N HA-1 AND 270 KG N HA-1
 FERT/OZONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
2407
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 3 C LESS THAN AMB
 WW + DROUGHT
 .
 .
 H2O
 GRASS_C
 NA
 .
2420
 GC
 550 UMOL M-2 S-1
 SEASONAL
 SEASONAL
 WW
 .
 NONE
 TEMP
 GRASS
 NA
 "WATER TMT ALSO, BUT NOT USED IN DATASET. ""WINTER"" TEMP = 3"
2427
 GH
 AMB + SUPPL (28.4 MOL M-2 S-1)
 16
 28/22
 WW/DRY
 .
 5KG M-3 15:10:10:2 NPK MG 3 MO RELEASE
 H2O
 GRASS
 AU
2430
 GH
 AMB 2-3.9 MJ M-2 D-1
 AMB
 19 - 22.5
 WW
 .
 SUPPLEMENTED
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 NOT USING 1992 DATA
2440
 GC
 1115 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 25/15
 WW
 .
 N= 0 OR 300 KG HA-1; P= 56 KG HA-1; K= 46 KG HA-1
 "FERT, TEMP"
 GRASS
 NA
2441
 GC
 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 12/12/98
 "DAY 20, 35; NIGHT 15"
 WW
 60/~100
 HALF STRENGTH HOAGLAND'S; =400 UL L-1 N
 TEMP 20 = CTL
 GRASS
 NA
2443
 GH
 SEASONAL
 SEASONAL
 SEASONAL
 WW
 .
 HOAGLAND'S + - N; SEE METHODS AND RESULTS
 NONE. SEE RESULTS
 GRASS
 NA
 "N HAD NO EFFECT ON PN, OR APPARENTLY ON TOTWT"
2444
 GC
 600 UMOL/M2S PFD
 15 H
 20/15 DEGREES C
 WW
 "65/70 % (DAY,NIGHT)"
 "NITROGEN CONCENTRATIONS (.01, .1, 1.0, AND 5.0 MG N/L)"
 NITROGEN CONCENTRATIONS BY N SUPPLY (AMMONIUM OR NITRATE)
 GRASS
 EU
 SAMPLE SIZE OF GAS EXCHANGE MEASUREMENTS WAS USED FOR ALL
MEASUREMENTS
 BECAUSE IT WAS THE ONLY ONE AVAILABLE. AGROSTIS CAPILLARIS IS A FAST
 GROWING GRASS. NARDUS ESTRICTA IS A SLOW GROWING GRASS.
2448
 GC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 .
 TEMP
 GRASS_C
 NA
 .
2454
 GC
 AMB
 14 HR
 AMB
 WW
 60-70%RH
 NUTRIENTS SUPPLEMENTED TWICE A WEEK
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 .
2468
 GC
 200 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14H
 19/15 C
 .
 .
 .
 .
 GRASS_C
 EU
 ANOTHER SET OF DATA (CO2 * SO2) CAN BE EXTRACTED
2474
 GH
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 .
 WW
 .
 MODIFIED HOAGLANDS
 "N= 5, 20, OR 50 MG L-1; P= 2, 11, OR 30 MG L-1; K=5, 20, 50 MG L-1"
 GRASS
 EU
 "CO2= AMB, AMB+250...1:1 SAND:PEAT; DATA TAKEN FROM P=3 + K=3 ONLY.
 AGN, AGC, AGK, AGP"
2480
 GH
 200 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14 H
 25/18
 "WW, FLD"
 .
 NATIVE SOIL
 "FLD, SALT"
 WETL
 EU
 PLANTS ROTATED BETWEEN 2 GHS
2492
 GC
 220-250 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 23.5/19
 80% OF FIELD CAPACITY
 30/55
 "194 MG N, 13 MG P, 24 MG K, 39 MG MG POT-1"
 DENSITY
 GRASS
 EU
 "USING LOWEST AND HIGHEST DENSITIES ONLY, AS REPS"
2502
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 PRECIP
 AMB
 NONE
 NONE
 WETL
 NA
 "SAME PARAMETERS WERE MEASURED AT DIFFERENT YEARS AND/OR THE
SAME YEAR,
 BUT DIFFERENT MONTHS. EACH MONTH AND/OR YEAR WAS CONSIDERED A
SEPARATE
 DATA POINT BECAUSE TIME OF EXPOSITION CHANGED. THE PAPER INCLUDES
DATA
 ON LEAF RUBISCO AND LEAF SOLUBLE PROTEIN."
2503
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 SEASONAL; -5-25
 AMB
 SEASONAL
 N (100 OR 420 KG HA-1 Y-1); 120 KG HA-1 P205; 240 KG HA-1 K2O; 16 KG HA-1
 MGO
 FERT: 100 OR 420 KG N HA-1 Y-1
 GRASS
 EU
 OOT IN GROWTH BAGS. ETHANOL SOLUBLE TNC USED IN DATABASE.
WATER-
SOLUBLE
 TNC ALSO AVAILABLE.
2504
 GH
 AMB; 180 UMOL M-2 S-1 + 100 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 20
 WW
 .
 HI N=54 G M-2; LO N=9.5 G M-2; + OTHER NUTRIENTS
 FERT
 GRASS
 EU
 .
2510
 GC
 AMB
 .
 AMB
 WW
 AMB
 FERTILIZED WEEKLY
 .
 .
 EU
2521
 GC
 500 UMOL M-2 S-1
 13.5 H
 23/17
 WW
 60-70
 .
 OZONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
 .
2522
 GC
 500 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 24/14
 WW
 65+/-5
 INITIAL AND EVERY 21 DAYS
 O3
 GRASS
 EU
2525
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 AMB
 .
 .
 WETL
 NA
 CARBON CONTENT WITH SE/SD &amp; N; ADDT'L VAR
2531
 OTC
 AMB - 11%
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 NONE
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
 CO2 FROM APRIL/ MAY THRU OCT EACH OF 3 YRS
2541
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB+
 AMB
 AMB
 NO ADDITIONAL
 CO2
 GRASS
 NA
 "JASPER RIDGE. GS, E, LFY, PN, SEEDS, HT, AGWT, WVE, DNSITY,
 ISOTOPE, SEED WT, FRUITWT, SEED C, SEED N."
2547
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 28/21/25(H20)
 WW
 .
 NPK INITIAL; VARIABLE N ADDED DURING SEASON
 CO2 ONLY APPROPRIATE
 WETL
 NA
2579
 GC
 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 23/16
 WW
 70-80
 ALL: 4.6 MG P; 5.8 MG K; N= 0 OR 32 MG POT-1
 FERT
 .
 .
2580
 GH
 amb
 amb
 32/23; 35/26; 38/29
 ww
 .
 "12.6, 6.3, 6.3, G N M-2 AT 7, 31 + 63 D"
 NONE
 WETL
 NA
 .
2595
 GC
 350 UMOL M-2 S-1
 15/9
 20/17
 WW
 .
 .
 .
 .
 .
2597
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 .
 NONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
 .
2644
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 101 KG N HA-1; SEE ALSO T1
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
2654
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
 JASPER RIDGE
2666
 GH
 AMB 25-29 MOL M-2 D-1
 16 H
 20/14
 WW / DRY
 .
 SOLUBLE OR SLOW RELEASE ADDED
 H2O
 GRASS_C
 AU
2669
 GC
 220-250 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 17-Dec
 WW
 0.571428571
 N: 0 OR 765 MG POT-1; 114 MG P; 193 MG K; 26 MG MG
 FERT
 GRASS
 EU
 USING ONLY CTL; HIGHEST FERT LEVELS
2692
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 32/23; 35/26; 38/29
 WET/DRY
 AMB
 NON-LIMITING; REPEATED APPLICATIONS
 H2O
 GRASS
 NA
 DRY = HALF OF WET (WW). USE WET AS CTL
2698
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 NONE
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
 "SUM Y EXPERIMENT. 2 OTC'S W/ CO2, OTC'S - CO2"
2709
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 .
 FERT/COMP
 GRASS
 EU
 TIME ASSUMED TO BE 730 BECAUSE AGWT WAS SUM OF TWO SEASONS
2710
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 LO: 10-14 G N M-2 Y-1; HI: 42-56 G N M-2 Y-1
 DEFOL: 4 OR 7-8 Y-1; FERT
 GRASS
 EU
 MET IN TABLE 1
2711
 GH
 9.2 + 24.9 MOL M-2 S-1
 AMB
 30/25
 WW
 &gt;90
 "30 MG N POT-1 + 60 G N POT-1, SEASONALLY"
 LIGHT
 GRASS
 AU
2715
 GC
 300 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 18/4
 WW; 14% H20
 0.928571429
 28 MG P + 50 MG K KG-1 + N TREATMENTS
 N 8KG N HA-1 OR 278 KG N HA-1
 GRASS
 EU
2718
 GC
 794
 AMB
 25/13 (DAY/NIGHT)
 WW
 AMB
 HOAGLAND'S SOLUTION EVERY 3 D
 DEFOL
 GRASS
 NA
 .
2723
 GH
 85-90% AMB
 14-H
 AMB/AMB + 3 C
 WW
 AMB
 .
 TEMP
 .
 EU
 GS WITH NO SE/SD. Vc MAX WITH SE/SD AND N IN FIG. 4
2735
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 "AMB, AMB+4"
 WW
 AMB
 10 G M-2 N; 15 G M-2 P; 15 G M-2 K
 TEMP
 GRASS
 EU
 80% OF UVB
2737
 GH
 25 MOL M-2 DAY-1
 16/8
 17
 WW
 65
 "COMPLETE, INCLUDE 188 MG L-1 N"
 "O3, SOIL"
 GRASS
 EU
 O3 NOT USED FOR PHYL DATASET
2756
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB + DROUGHT
 AMB
 NONE
 H2O
 GRASS
 NA
 "UNDISTURBED TALL GRASS PRAIRIE; EARLY, MID + LATE SEASON DATA;
EXP.
RAN
 4Y PRIOR TO THIS STUDY"
2758
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 .
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 .
2785
 OTC
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 HI FERT TRT ONLY
 FERT. 20 G M-2 NPK OSMOCOTE
 GRASS
 NA
 JASPER RIDGE. SERPENTINE SOIL
2793
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 GRASS
 EU
 MINI-RHIZOTRONE. DATA USED FROM 10 CM
2802
 GH (TUNNEL)
 AMB
 AMB
 0.3 C HIGHER DURING DAY; 0.2 C LOWER AT NIGHT
 .
 .
 FERT
 GRASS
 EU
 .
2821
 GH
 79% OF AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 8 G N M-2 PER 24 DAYS
 CO2
 GRASS
 EU
2834
 GC
 750 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 16
 WW
 0.54 KPA
 0.2 OR 2.5 MOL M-3 N; 0.04 OR 0.5 MOL M-3 P
 LOW N+LOW P OR HI N + HI P
 GRASS
 EU
 "P, OTHER MINERALS"
2835
 GC
 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16
 30/20
 WW
 0.0025
 "HOAGLAND'S, ALTERNATE WATERING"
 .
 GRASS
 NA
2839
 OTC
 85% OF AMB
 AMB
 "25/29 ( AMB, AMB+4)"
 WW
 .
 220 KG N HA-1
 TEMP
 WETL
 AS
2855
 GH
 AMB+
 16/8
 20/15
 WW
 70
 NPK (HOAGLAND'S) OR 0.1 N (MODIFIED HOAGLAND'S)
 FERT
 GRASS
 EU
2856
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 26/16 C DAY/NIGHT
 WW
 .
 .
 FERT
 GRASS_C
 AS
 .
2892
 GC
 645 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 24/18
 WW
 .
 MODIFIED SHIVE'S SOLUTION
 O3
 GRASS
 EU
 TIME FOR BIOMASS ASSUMED &gt; 42 D; SEE FIG 6
2893
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 19
 WW
 67-71%
 0.4 G L-1 N; 0.3 G L-1 P205; 0.4 G L-1 K20
 NONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
 INTRODUCED IN 1890
2895
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
2911
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 O3
 GRASS
 EU
 CTL O3 = 26-29 NMOL MOL-1; HI O3= 84 NMOL MOL-1 AVE FOR ALL DAYS
2919
 GC
 AMB
 AMB
 15 C MEAN
 .
 .
 "150 MG N, 18.1 MG P AND 34 MG K"
 H20
 GRASS_C
 EU
2924
 GH
 AMB; PN &gt;1200 UMOL M-2 S-1
 AMB
 32/23; 35/26; 38/29
 WW
 .
 "P, K= 9 G M-2; N (UREA) 12.6-6.3 G M-2 X3 DATES"
 TEMP
 WETL
 NA
2928
 OTC
 85% OF AMB
 AMB
 X= 25; AMB+4
 WW
 .
 N: 110 KG HA-1 WET SEASON; 220 KG HA-1 DRY
 TEMP
 WETL
 AS
 DATA ON DEVELOPMENT STAGES
2935
 OTC
 AMB
 .
 28/21 (DAY / NIGHT)
 .
 .
 .
 H2O
 GRASS_C
 NA
 SPAR: SOIL-PLANT-ATMOSPHERE-RESEARCH CHAMBER
3034
 GC
 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 28/22; 24/18; 21/25
 WW
 70
 .
 TEMP. NOTE ECOTYPES
 GRASS
 NA
 "TEMPS: MISS: CTL=28, L0=2, . ; N.C: CTL=24, LO=21, HI=28; QUEBEC:
 CTL=21, . , HI =28"
3033
 GC
 65 UE M-2 S-1
 14/10
 28/22
 WW
 0.7
 HALF STRENGTH HOAGLANDS
 NONE
 MIXED
 NA
3035
 GC
 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 28/22; 24/18; 21/15
 WW
 70
 .
 TEMP NOTE ECOTYPES
 GRASS
 NA
 "TEMPS: MISS: CTL=28, LO=21, . ; N.C: CTL=24, LO-21, HI=28; QUEBEC:
 CTL=21, . , HI=28"
3036
 GC
 150 OR 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 29/23
 WW
 70
 HALF STRENGTH HOAGLANDS
 LIGHT
 GRASS
 NA
3038
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 34
 WW
 .
 .
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
 MIXED AND UNMIXED CULTURES
3042
 GH
 AMB; 2ME M-2 S-1
 AMB
 32/20
 WW
 50-70
 "4 LEVELS OF HENITTS: 24,12, 4, OR MM NITRATE"
 FERT
 GRASS_C
 NA
 ONLY MAIZE DATA WERE TAKEN
3401
 GH
 AMB + LOW INTENSITY INCANDESCENT
 1/16/00
 28/23
 "AT PLANTING ONLY, DRYING THEREAFTER"
 60-70
 ..
 H20
 GRASS
 AU
 ASSUMING THAT TIME COURSE FOR WATER LOSS IS SIMILAR FOR ALL GRASS
SPECIES
 (USING WHEAT (COMPANION PAPER)); WE USE TIME CLASSES FOR ANALYSES.
&#239;&#187;&#191;
 &#160;&amp;middot;&#160;]]></Text>
    </Documentation_Link>
    <OME_Software_Version>Version 4.7.5, Revision Date: 04 Apr 2006</OME_Software_Version>
    <OME_DTD_Version>metadata10.dtd</OME_DTD_Version>
    <Temporal_Resolution></Temporal_Resolution>
    <enddate_blank></enddate_blank>
    <Harvest_Date>2017-09-01</Harvest_Date>
    <File_ID>Created 20050809 165142 by 160.91.18.40</File_ID>
    <Spatial_Extent></Spatial_Extent>
    <Metadata_URL><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/xml/cdp/metadata/Tom_Boden/NDP_073.xml]]></Metadata_URL>
    <CDIAC>
      <Product_number><![CDATA[doi 10.3334/CDIAC/vrc.ndp073]]></Product_number>
      <Product_title><![CDATA[Database of Herbaceous Vegetation Responses to Elevated Atmospheric CO2]]></Product_title>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Jones, M. H.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[Department of Evolution, Ecology, and Organismal Biology]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Curtis, P. S.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[Department of Evolution, Ecology, and Organismal Biology]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Thematic_area><![CDATA[Vegetation Response to CO2 and Climate]]></Thematic_area>
      <Site_info>
        <Site_name><![CDATA[Herbaceous Vegetation Responses]]></Site_name>
        <Site_URL><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/epubs/ndp/ndp073/ndp073.html]]></Site_URL>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/ndp073/ndp073.dat]]></Site_data_file>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/ndp073/comments.dat]]></Site_data_file>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/ndp073/refs.dat]]></Site_data_file>
      </Site_info>
      <Data_site></Data_site>
      <Variable><![CDATA[AMB]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CO2_UNIT]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CV_AMB]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[CV_ELEV]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[DIV1]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[DIV2]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[DIV3]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[DIV4]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[ELEV]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[GENUS]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[LEVEL]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[MTHD]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[N_AMB]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[N_ELEV]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[PAP_NO]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[PARAM]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[POT]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[P_UNIT]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[QUANT]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SDC]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SD_AMB]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SD_ELEV]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SE_AMB]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SE_ELEV]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SOURCE]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[SPECIES]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[STOCK]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[TIME]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[XTRT]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[X_AMB]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[X_ELEV]]></Variable>
      <Descriptive_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/epubs/ndp/ndp073/ndp073.htmlContributed by
Michael H. Jones
Peter S. Curtis
Department of Evolution, Ecology, and Organismal Biology
Prepared by Robert M. Cushman and Antoinette L. Brenkert
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
Publication No. 4909
Prepared for the
Prepared by the
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center
Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831-6290
managed by
LOCKHEED MARTIN ENERGY RESEARCH CORP.
for the
under contract DE-AC05-96OR22464
PAP_NO = 3034
PARAM = PN
SOURCE = F1
X_ELEV = 44.400
SE_ELEV = 0.100
CV*_ELEV = 0.694
and
PAP_NO = 2723
PARAM = PN
SOURCE = F4
X_ELEV = 40.120
SE_ELEV = 0.505
PAP_NO = 2184
PARAM = TILLERS
SOURCE = T2
X_ELEV = 726.000
SE_ELEV = 52.000
CV*_ELEV = 28.203
and
PAP_NO = 2717
PARAM = TILLERS
SOURCE = F1
X_ELEV = 4.590
SE_ELEV = 0.400
 38AGWT G PLANT-1 TRITICUM AESTIVUM ANGIO GRASS_CC3 GRASS
330
660UL L-1 461.45 GC SEED H2O LO 10 ML PL-1 D-1 F4
3.61 -9.99 -9.99 -9.99 10 5.13 -9.99 -9.99 -9.99 10 .
 38AGWT G PLANT-1 TRITICUM AESTIVUM ANGIO GRASS_CC3 GRASS
330
660UL L-1 371.45 GC SEED H2O CTL 40 ML PL-1 D-1 F4
2.98 -9.99 -9.99 -9.99 10 3.97 -9.99 -9.99 -9.99 10 .
 3042PN UMOL M-2 S-1 ZEA MAYS ANGIO GRASS_CC4 GRASS 330
640UBAR 305 GH SEED FERT HI . F2
64.80 2.10 5.94 9.45 8 52.40 0.90 2.55 5.01 8 Y
 3042PN UMOL M-2 S-1 ZEA MAYS ANGIO GRASS_CC4 GRASS 330
640UBAR 305 GH SEED FERT LO . F2
27.90 1.84 5.20 19.24 8 21.90 2.10 5.94 27.97 8 Y
*SAS data retrieval routine to read ndp073.dat;
data ndp073;
infile 'ndp073.dat';
input PAP_NO 6. @7 PARAM $char7. P_UNIT $ 14-27 GENUS $ 28-40
 SPECIES $ 41-53 DIV1 $ 54-59 DIV2 $ 60-66 DIV3 $ 67-71
 DIV4 $ 72-77 AMB $ 78-80 ELEV $ 81-84
 CO2_UNIT $ 85-94 TIME $ 95-99 POT $ 100-112 MTHD $ 113-116
 STOCK $ 117-125 XTRT $ 126-131 LEVEL $ 132-138 QUANT $ 139-155
 SOURCE $ 156-161 X_AMB 162-169 SE_AMB 170-177 SD_AMB 178-185
 CV_AMB 186-192 N_AMB 193-197 X_ELEV 198-206 SE_ELEV 207-213
 SD_ELEV 214-221 CV_ELEV 222-229 N_ELEV 230-235 SDC $ 236-238 ;
* In the above INPUT statement, the variables CV*_AMB and CV*_ELEV have
 been renamed CV_AMB and CV_ELEV, respectively.;
proc print;
run;
C *** Fortran program to read the file "ndp073.dat"
C
 INTEGER PAP_NO, N_AMB, N_ELEV
C
 REAL X_AMB, SE_AMB, SD_AMB, CV_AMB, X_ELEV, SE_ELEV,
 + SD_ELEV, CV_ELEV
C
 CHARACTER PARAM*7, P_UNIT*14, GENUS*13, SPECIES*13, DIV1*6,
 + DIV2*7, DIV3*5, DIV4*6, AMB*3, ELEV*4, CO2_UNIT*10,
 + TIME*5, POT*13, MTHD*4, STOCK*9, XTRT*6, LEVEL*7,
 + QUANT*17, SOURCE*6, SDC*3
C
 OPEN (UNIT=1, FILE='ndp073.dat')
C
C Note that the variables CV*_AMB and CV*_ELEV have
C been renamed CV_AMB and CV_ELEV, respectively
C
 10 READ (1,100,END=99) PAP_NO, PARAM, P_UNIT, GENUS, SPECIES,
 + DIV1, DIV2, DIV3, DIV4, AMB, ELEV, CO2_UNIT, TIME, POT,
 + MTHD, STOCK, XTRT, LEVEL, QUANT, SOURCE, X_AMB, SE_AMB,
 + SD_AMB, CV_AMB, N_AMB, X_ELEV, SE_ELEV, SD_ELEV, CV_ELEV,
 + N_ELEV, SDC
C
 100 FORMAT (I6,A7,A14,2A13,A6,A7,A5,A6,A3,A4,A10,A5,A13,A4,A9,
 + A6,A7,A17,A6,3F8.2,F7.2,I5,F9.2,F7.2,2F8.2,I6,A3)
C
 GO TO 10
 99 CLOSE (UNIT=1)
 STOP
 END
Agropyron caninum
Agropyron smithii
Agrostis capillaris
Andropogon gerardii
Avena barbata
Avena fatua
Avena sativa
Bouteloua curtipendula
Bouteloua eriopoda
Bouteloua gracilis
Briza subaristata
Bromus erectus
Bromus hordaeceus
Bromus willdenowii
Calamagrostis epigejos
Carex curvula
Dactylis glomerata
Digitaria macroblephara
Digitaria sanguinalis
Echinochloa crusgalli
Eleusine indica
Eriophorum vaginatum
Festuca arundinacea
Festuca durviscula
Festuca elatior
Festuca idahoensis
Festuca ovina
Festuca pratense
Festuca rupicola
Festuca vivipara
Hordeum vulgare
Lolium boucheanum
Lolium multiflorum
Lolium perenne
Nardus stricta
Oryza sativa
Panicum antidotale
Panicum laxum
Panicum millioides
Pascopyrum smithii
Paspalum dilatatum
Pennisetum clandestinum
Phalaris aquatica
Phleum pratense
Poa alpina
Poa annua
Poa pratensis
Puccinellia maritima
Rottboellia exaltata
Schizachyrium scoparium
Scirpus olneyi
Setaria faberi
Sorghum bicolor
Sorghum helpense
Spartina patens
Sporobolus kentrophyllus
Stipa occidentalis
Themeda triandra
Triticum aestivum
Vulpia microstachys
38. Andre, M., and H. Du Cloux. 1993. Interaction of CO2 Enrichment and Water
Limitations on Photosynthesis and Water-Use Efficiency in Wheat. Plant
Physiology and Biochemistry 31:103-112.
186. Drake, B. G. 1992. A Field Study of the Effects of Elevated CO2 on
Ecosystem Processes in a Chesapeake Bay Wetland. Australian Journal of Botany
40:579-595.
488. Nie, D., H. He, M. B. Kirkham, and E. T. Kanemasu. 1992. Photosynthesis
of a C3 Grass and a C4 Grass under Elevated CO2. Photosynthetica 26:189-198.
618. Ryle, G. J. A., C. E. Powell, and V. Tewson. 1992. Effect of elevated co2
on photosynthesis, respiration and growth of perennial ryegrass. Journal of
Experimental Botany 43:811-818.
754. Ziska, L. H., and J. A. Bunce. 1993. Inhibition of Whole Plant
Respiration by Elevated CO2 as Modified by Growth Temperature. Physiologia
Plantarum 87:459-466.
765. Baker, J. T., L. H. Allen Jr., and K. J. Boote. 1992. Response of Rice to
Carbon Dioxide and Temperature. Agricultural and Forest Meteorology
60:153-166.
2066. Samarakoon, A. B., W. J. Muller, and R. M. Gifford. 1995. Transpiration
and leaf area under elevated CO2: Effects of soil water status and genotype in
wheat. Australian Journal of Plant Physiology 22:33-44.
2119. Greer, D. H., W. A. Laing, and B. D. Campbell. 1995. Photosynthetic
responses of thirteen pasture species to elevated CO2 and temperature.
Australian Journal of Plant Physiology 22:713-722.
2125. Baxter, R., M. Gantley, T. W. Ashenden, and J. F. Farrar. 1994. Effects
of elevated carbon dioxide on three grass species from montane pasture.
Journal of Experimental Botany 45:1267-1287.
2132. Rao, M. V., B. A. Hale, and D. P. Ormrod. 1995. Amelioration of
ozone-induced oxidative damage in wheat plants grown under high carbon
dioxide. Plant Physiology 109:421-432.
2133. Tuba, Z., K. Szente, and J. Koch. 1994. Response of photosynthesis,
stomatal conductance, water use efficiency and production to long-term
elevated CO2 in winter wheat. Journal of Plant Physiology 144:661-668.
2158. Gloser, J., and M. Bartak. 1994. Net photosynthesis, growth rate and
biomass allocation in a rhizomatous grass Icalamagrostis epigejos grown at
elevated CO2 concentration. Photosynthetica 30(1):143-150.
2159. Ziska, L. H., and J. A. Bunce. 1994. Increasing growth temperature
reduces the stimulatory effect of elevated CO2 on photosynthesis or biomass in
two perennial species. Physiologia Plantarum 91:183-190.
2168. Knapp, A. K., E. P. Hamerlynck, and C. E. Owensby. 1993. Photosynthetic
and water relations responses to elevated CO2 in the C4 grass Andropogon
geradii. International Journal of Plant Science 154(4):459-466.
2184. Saebo, A., and L. M. Mortensen. 1995. Growth and regrowth of Phleum
pratense, Lolium perenne, Trifolium repens and Trifolium pratense at normal
and elevated O2 concentration. Agriculture, Ecosystems and Environment
55:29-35.
2192. Knapp, A. K., J. T. Fahnestock, and C. E. Owensby. 1994. Elevated
atmospheric O2 alters stomatal responses to variable sunlight in a C4 grass.
Plant, Cell and Environment 17:189-195.
2202. Wilsey, B. J., S. J. McNaughton, and J. S. Coleman. 1994. Will increases
in atmospheric O2 affect regrowth following grazing in C4 grasses from
tropical grasslands? Oecologia 99:141-144.
2208. Crush, J. R. 1994. Elevated atmospheric O2 concentration and rhizosphere
nitrogen fixation in four forage plants. New Zealand Journal of Agricultural
Research 37:455-463.
2211. Morgan, J. A., W. G. Knight, L. M. Dudley, and H. W. Hunt. 1994.
Enhanced root system C-sink activity, water relations and aspects fo nutrient
acquisistion in mycotrophic Bouteloua gracilis subjected to CO2 enrichment.
Plant and Soil 165:139-146.
2227. Bowler, J. M., and M. C. Press. 1993. Growth responses of two
contrasting upland grass species to elevated CO2 and nitrogen concentration.
New Phytologist 124:515-522.
2229. Mitchell, R. A. C., V. J. Mitchell, S. P. Driscoll, J. Franklin, and D.
W. Lawlor. 1993. Effects of increased CO2 concentration and temperature on
growth and yield of winter wheat at two levels of nitrogen application. Plant,
Cell and Environment 16:521-529.
2246. Baxter, R., T. W. Ashenden, T. H. Sparks, and J. F. Farrar. 1994.
Effects of elevated carbon dioxide on three montane grass species. Journal of
Experimental Botany 45 (272):305-315.
2300. Bassirirad, H., D. T. Tissue, J. F. Reynolds, and F. S. Chapin. 1996.
Response of Eriophorum vaginatum to CO2 enrichment at different soil
temperature: effects on growth, root respiration and PO-4 uptake kinetics. New
Phytologist 133:423-430.
2312. Wilsey, B. J. 1996. Urea additions and defoliation affect plant
responses to elevated CO2 in a C3 grassland from Yellowstone National Park.
Oecologia 108:321-327.
2315. Casella, E., J. F. Soussana, and P. Loiseau. 1996. Long-term effects of
CO2 enrichment and temperature increase on a temperate grass sward. 1.
Productivity and water use. Plant and Soil 182:83-99.
2316. Soussana, J. F., E. Casella, and P. Loiseau. 1996. Long-term effects of
CO2 enrichment and temperature increase on a temperate grass sward. 2. Plant
nitrogen budgets and root fraction. Plant and Soil 182:101-114.
2329. Jones, M. B., M. Jongen, and T. Doyle. 1996. Effects of elevated carbon
dioxide concentrations on agricultural grassland production. Agricultural and
Forest Meteorology 79:243-252.
2330. Stewart, J., and C. Potvin. 1996. Effects of elevated CO2 on an
artificial grassland community: competition, invasion and neighbourhood area.
Functional Ecology 10:157-166.
2337. Saebo, A., and L. M. Mortensen. 1996. The influence of elevated CO2
concentration on growth of seven grasses and one clover species in a cool
maritime climate. Acta Agriculturae Scandinavia Section B-Sorland Plant
Science 46:49-54.
2341. Schappi, B., and C. Korner. 1996. Growth responses of an alpine
grassland to elevated CO2. Oecologia 105:43-52.
2342. Jackson, R. B., and H. L. Reynolds. 1996. Nitrate and ammonium uptake
for single and mixed species communities grown at elevated CO2. Oecologia
105:74-80.
2345. Hakala, K., and T. Mela. 1996. The effects of prolonged exposure to
elevated temperatures and elevated CO2 leveles on the growth, yield and dry
matter partitioning of filed-sown meadow fescue. Agricultural and Food Science
in Finland 5(3):285-298.
2347. Jackson, R. B., Y. Luo, Z. G. Cardon, O. E. Sala, C. B. Field, and H. A.
Mooney. 1995. Photosynthesis, growth and density for the dominant species in a
CO2 enriched grassland. Journal of Biogeography 22:221-225.
2350. Teughels, H., I. Nijs, P. Van Hecke, and I. Impens. 1995. Competition in
a global change environment: The importance of different plant traits for
competitive success. Journal of Biogeography 22:297-305.
2351. Campbell, B. D., W. A. Laing, D. H. Gree, J. R. Crush, H. Clark, D. Y.
WIlliamson, and M. D. J. Given. 1995. Variation in grassland populations and
species and the implications for community responses to elevated CO2. Journal
of Biogeography 22:315-322.
2357. Chu, C. C., C. B. Field, and H. A. Mooney. 1996. Effects of CO2 and
nutrient enrichment on tissue quality of two California annuals. Oecologia
107:433-440.
2358. Ferris, R., I. Niy, T. Bejaeghe, and I. Impens. 1996. Contrasting CO2
and temperature effects on leaf growth of perennial rye grass in spring and
summer. Journal of Experimental Botany 47:1033-1043.
2362. Wheeler, T. R., G. R. Batts, R. H. Ellis, P. Hadley, and J. J. L.
Morison. 1996. Growth and yield of winter wheat (Triticum aestium) crops in
response to CO2 and temperature. Journal of Agricultural Science 127:37-48.
2363. Volin, J. C., and P. B. Reich. 1996. Interaction of elevated CO2 and O3
on growth, photosynthesis and respiration of three perennial species grown in
low and high nitrogen. Physiologia Plantarum 97:674-684.
2364. Miglietta, F., A. Giuntoli, and M. Bindi. 1996. The effect of free air
carbon dioxide enrichment (FACE) and soil nitrogen availability on the
photosynthetic capacity of wheat. Photosynthesis Research 47:281-290.
2366. Ziska, L. H., W. Weerakoon, O. S. Namuco, and R. Pamplona. 1996.
Influence of nitrogen on the elevated CO2 response in field-grown rice.
Australian Journal of Plant Physiology 23:45-52.
2367. Saebo, A., and L. M. Mortensen. 1996. Growth, morphology and yield of
wheat, barley and oats grown at elevated atmospheric CO2 concentration in a
cool maritime climate. Agriculture, Ecosystems and Environment 57:9-15.
2369. Ziska, L. H., P. A. Manalo, and R. A. Ordonez. 1996. Intraspecific
variaiton in the response of rice (Oryza sativa L) to increased CO2 and
temeprature: growth and yield response of seventeen cultivars. Journal of
Experimental Botany 47:1353-1359.
2372. Nijs, I., H. Teughels, H. Blum, G. Hendrey, and I. Impens. 1996.
Simulation of climate change with infrared heaters reduces the productivity of
Lolium perenne L in summer. Environmental and Experimental Botany 36:271-280.
2379. Veisz, O., N. Harnos, L. Szunies, and T. Tischner. 1996. Overwintering
of winter cereals in Hungary in the case of global warming. Euphytica
92:249-253.
2383. Nijs, I., and I. Impens. 1996. Effects of elevated CO2 concentration and
climate-warming on photosynthesis during winter in Lolium perenne. Journal of
Experimental Botany 47:915-924.
2387. Leadley, P. W., and J. Stocklin. 1996. Effects of elevated CO2 on model
calcareous grasslands: Community, species, and genotype responses. Global
Change Biology 2:389-397.
2395. Tuba, Z., K. Szente, Z. Nagy, Z. Csintalan, and J. Koch. 1996. Responses
of CO2 assimilation, transpiration and water use efficiency to long-term
elevated CO2 in perennial C3 xeric loess steppe species. Journal of Plant
Physiology 148:356-361.
2398. Mortensen, L. M., and A. Saebo. 1996. The effects of elevated CO2
concentration on growth of Phleum pratense L. in different parts of the growth
season. Acta Agriculturaie Scandinavia Section B-Soil and Plant Science
46:128-134.
2401. Jackson, R. B., and A. L. Reynolds. 1996. Nitrate and annomium uptake
for single- and mixed species communities grown at elevated CO2. Oecologia
105:74-80.
2403. Fanymeier, A., U. Geuters, U. Hesstein, H. Sandhagel, A. Hoffmann, B.
Vermebren, and A. J. Jager. 1996. Effects of elevated CO2, nitrogen supply and
tropospheric ozone on spring wheat. 1. Growth and Yields. Environmental
Pollution 91:381-390.
2407. Kinball, B. A., P. J. Pinter, R. L. Garcia, R. L. La Mort, G. W. Wall,
D. J. Hunsaker, G. WEchsung, F. Wechsung, and T. Kartschall. 1995.
Productivity and water use of wheat under free-air CO2 enrichment. Global
Change Biology 1:429-442.
2420. Hunt, H. W., E. T. Elliot, J. K. Detling, J. A. Morgan, and D. X. Chen.
1996. Responses of a C3 and a C4 perennial grass to elevated CO2 and
temperature under different water regimes. Global Change Biology 2:35-47.
2427. Samarakoon, A. B., and R. M. Gifford. 1996. Elevated CO2 effects on
water use and growth of maize in wet and drying soils. Australian Journal of
Plant Physiology 23:53-62.
2430. Ruget, F., O. Bethenod, and L. Combe. 1996. Repercussions of increased
atmospheric CO2 on maize morphogenesis and growth for various temperature and
radiation levels. Maydica 41:181-191.
2440. Frank, A. B., and A. Bauer. 1996. Temperature, nitrogen and carbon
dioxide effects on spring wheat development and spikelet numbers. Crop Science
36:659-665.
2441. Read, J. J., and J. A. Morgan. 1996. Growth and partitioning in
Pascopyrum smithii (C3) and Bouteloua graciles (C4) as influenced by carbon
dioxide and temperature. Annals of Botany 77:487-496.
2443. Polley, H. W., H. B. Johnson, H. S. Mayeux, D. A. Brown, and J. W. C.
White. 1996. Leaf and plant water use efficiency of C4 species grown at
glacial to elevated CO2 concentrations. International Journal of Plant
Sciences 157:164-170.
2444. Bowler, J. M., and M. C. Press. 1996. Effects of elevated CO2 nitrogen
form and concentration on growth and photosynthesis of a fast- adn
slow-growing grass. New Phytologist 132:391-401.
2448. RowlandBamford, A. J., J. T. Baker, H. L. Allen, and G. Bowes. 1996.
Interactions of CO2 enrichment and temperature on carbohydrate accumulation
and partitioning in rice. Environmental and Experimental Botany 36:111-124.
2454. Bagash, D. Z., M. J. Paul, M. A. J. Parry, A. J. Keys, and D. W. Lawlor.
1995. Increased capacity for photosynthesis in wheat grown at elevated CO2.
The relationship between electron-transport and carbon metabolism. Planta
197:482-489.
2468. Rao, M. V., and L. J. Dekok. 1994. Interactive effects of high CO2 and
SO2 on growth and antioxidant levels in wheat. Phyton-Annales Rei Botanicae
34:279-290.
2474. Newbery, R. M., J. Wolfenden, T. A. Mansfield, and A. F. Harrison. 1995.
Nitrogen, phosphorus and potassium uptake and demand Agrostis capillaria. The
influence of elevated CO2 and nutrient supply. New Phytologist 130:565-574.
2480. Lenssen, G. M., W. E. Vandium, P. Jak, and J. Roxema. 1995. The response
of Aster tripolium and Puccinellia maritima to atmospheric carbon dioxide
enrichment and their interaction with flooding and salinity. Aquatic Botany
50:181-192.
2492. Schenk, U., R. Maderscheid, J. Hugen, and H. J. Weigel. 1995. Effects of
CO2 enrichment and intraspecific competition on biomass partitioning, nitrogen
content, and microbial biomass carbon in soil of perennial rye grass and white
clover. Journal of Experimental Botany 46:987-993.
2502. Jacob, J., C. Greitner, and B. G. Drake. 1995. Acclimation of
photosynthesis in relation to Rubisco and non-structural carbohydrate contents
and in-situ carboxylase activity in Scirpus olnei grown at elevated CO2 in the
field. Plant, Cell and Environment 18:875-884.
2503. Jongen, M., M. B. Jones, T. Hebeisen, H. Blum, and G. Hendrey. 1995. The
effects of elevated CO2 concentrations on the root growth of Lolium perenne
and Trifolium repens grown in a FACE system. Global Change Biology 1:361-371.
2504. Kleemola, J., J. Peltonen, and P. Peltonen-Sainio. 1994. Apical
development and growth of Barley under different CO2 and nitrogen regimes.
Journal of Agronomy and Crop Science 173:79-92.
2510. Demothes, M. A. G., and D. Knoppik. 1994. Effects of long term enhanced
CO2 partial pressure on gas exchange parameters and saccharide pools of wheat
leaves. Photosynthetica 30:435-445.
2521. Balaguer, L., J. D. Barnes, A. Panicucci, and A. M. Borland. 1995.
Production and utilization of assimilates in wheat leaves exposed to elevated
O3 and/or CO2. New Phytologist 129:557-568.
2522. Barnes, J. D., J. H. Ollerenshaw, and C. P. Whitfield. 1995. Effects of
elevated CO2 and/or O3 on growth, development and physiology of wheat. Global
Change Biology 1:129-142.
2525. Hattenschwiler, S., and C. Korner. 1996. System-level adjustments to
elevated CO2 in model spruce ecosystems. Global Change Biology 2:377-387.
2531. Owensby, C. E., P. I. Coyne, J. M. Ham, L. M. Avea, and A. K. Knapp.
1993. Biomass production in a tallgrass prairie ecosystem exposed to ambient
and elevated CO2. Ecological Applications 3:644-653.
2541. Jackson, R. B., O. E. Sala, C. B. Field, and H. A. Mooney. 1994. CO2
alters water use, carbon gain, and yield for the dominant species in a natural
grassland. Oecologia 98:257-262.
2547. Baker, J. T., L. H. Allen, and K. J. Boote 1992. Temperature effects on
rice at elevated CO2 concentration. Journal of Experimental Botany 43:959-964.
2579. Billes, G., H. Rouhier, and P. Bottner. 1993. Modifications of the
carbon and nitrogen allocations in the plant Triticum aestivum L. soil system
in response to increased atmospheric CO2 concentration. Plant and Soil
157:215-225.
2580. Baker, J. T., S. L. Albrecht, D. Pan, L. H. Allen, N. B. Pickering, and
K. J. Boote. 1994. Carbon dioxide and temperature effects on rice (Oryza
sativa L., CV 1R-72). Soil and Crop Science Society of Florida, Proceedings
53:90-97.
2595. Santruce, J., H. Santurckova, J. Kueton, M. Simkoua, and K. Rohacek.
1994. The effect of elevated CO2 concentration on photosynthetic CO2 fixation,
respiration and carbon economy of wheat plants. Rostlinna Vyroba 40:689-696.
2597. Ingaurdsen, C., and B. Veierskov. 1994. Response of young barley plants
to CO2 enrichment. Journal of Experimental Botany 45:1373-1378.
2644. Reeves, D. W., H. H. Royers, S. A. Prior, C. W. Wood, and G. B. Runion.
1994. Elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide effects on sorghum and soybean
nutrient status. Journal of Plant Nutrition 17:1939-1954.
2654. Jackson, R. B., Y. Lou, Z. G. Cardon, O. E. Sala, C. B. Field, and H. A.
Mooney. 1995. Photosynthesis, growth and density for the dominant species in a
CO2 enriched grassland. Journal of Biogeography 22:221-225.
2666. Samarakoon, A. B., and R. M. Gifford. 1995. Soil water content under
plants at high CO2 concentrations and interaction with the direct CO2 effects:
A species comparison. Journal of Biogeography 22:193-202.
2669. Schenk, U., A. J. Jager, and H. J. Weigel. 1996. Nitrogen supply
determine responses of yeild and biomass partitioning of perennial rye grass
to elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations. Journal of Plant
Nurtition 19:1423-1440.
2692. Kimball, B. A., P. J. P. Pinter, R. L. Garcia, R. L. LaMorte, G. W.
Wall, D. J. Hunsaker, G. Wechsung, F. Wechsong, and T. Kartschall. 1995.
Productivity and water use of wheat under free-air CO2. Global Change Biology
1:429-442.
2698. Potvin, C., and L. Vasseur. 1997. Long-term CO2 enrichment of a pasture
community: species richness, dominance, and succession. Ecology 78:666-677.
2709. Hebeisen, T., A. Luscher, and J. Nosberger. 1997. Effects of elevated
atmospheric CO2 and nitrogen fertilisation on yield of Trifolium repens and
Lolium perenne. Acta Oecologica/Oecologia Plantarum 18:277-284.
2710. Hebeisen, T., A. Luscher, S. Zanetti, B. U. Fischer, U. A. Hartwig, M.
Frehner, G. R. Hendrey, H. Blum, and J. Nosberger. 1997. Growth response of
Trifolium repens L and Lolium perenne L as monocultures and bi-species mixture
to free air CO2 enrichment and management. Global Change Biology 3:149-160.
2711. Ghannoum, O., S. vonCaemmerer, E. W. R. Barlow, and J. P. Conroy. 1997.
The effect of CO2 enrichment and irradiance on the growth, morphology and gas
exchange of a C3 (Panicum laxum) and a C4 (Panicum antidotale) grass.
Australian Journal of Plant Physiology 24:227-237.
2715. Cotrufo, M. F., and A. Gorissen. 1997. Elevated CO2 enhances
below-ground C allocation in three perennial grass species at different levels
of N availibility. New Phytologist 137:421-431.
2718. Wilsey, B. J., J. S. Coleman, and S. J. McNaughton. 1997. Effects of
elevated CO2 and defoliation of grasses: A comparative ecosystem approach.
Ecological Applications 7:844-853.
2723. Stirling, C. M., P. A. Davey, T. G. Williams, and S. P. Long. 1997.
Acclimation of photosynthesis to elevated CO2 and temperature in five British
native species of contrasting functional type. Global Change Biology
3:237-246.
2735. Nijs, I., and I. Impens. 1997. An analysis of the balance between root
and shoot activity in Lolium perenne cv Melvina. Effects of CO2 concentration
and air temperature. New Phytologist 135:81-91.
2737. Mortensen, L. M. 1997. Effects of carbon dioxide concentrations on three
grass species grown in mixture in two soil types at different ozone
concentrations or temperatures. Acta Agriculturae Scandinavica, Section B,
Soil and Plant Sciences 47:14-19.
2756. Hamerlynck, E. P., C. A. McAllister, A. K. Knapp, J. M. Ham, and C. E.
Owensby. 1997. Photosynthetic gas exchange and water relation responses of
three tallgrass prairie species to elevated carbon dioxide and moderate
drought. International Journal of Plant Sciences 158:608-616.
2758. Stocker, R., P. W. Leadley, and C. Korner. 1997. Carbon and water fluxes
in a calcareous grassland under elevated CO2. Functional Ecology 11:222-230.
2785. Hungate, B. A., J. Canadell, and F. S. Chapin. 1996. Plant species
mediate changes in soil microbial N in response to elevated CO2. Ecology
77:2505-2515.
2793. Fitter, A. H., G. K. Self, J. Wolfenden, M. M. I. vanVuuren, T. K.
Brown, L. Williamson, J. D. Graves, and D. Robinson. 1996. Root production and
mortality under elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide. Plant and Soil
187:299-306.
2802. Casela, E., and J. F. Soussana. 1997. Long-term effects of CO2
enrichment and temperature increase on the carbon balance of a temperate grass
sward. Journal of Experimental Botany 48:1309-1321.
2821. Schapendonk, A. H. C. M., P. Dijkstra, J. Groenwold, C. S. Pot, and S.
C. vandeGeijn. 1997. Carbon balance and water use effciency of frequently cut
Lolium perenne L swards at elevated carbon dioxide. Global Change Biology
3:207-216.
2834. Baxter, R., T. W. Ashenden, and J. F. Farrar. 1997. Effect of elevated
CO2 and nutrient status on growth, dry matter partitioning and nutrient
content of Poa alpina var vivipara L. Journal of Experimental Botany
48:1477-1486.
2835. Bassirirad, H., J. F. Reynolds, R. A. Virginia, and M. H. Brunelle.
1997. Growth and root NO3- and PO43- uptake capacity of three desert species
in response to atmospheric CO2 enrichment. Australian Journal of Plant
Physiology 24:353-358.
2839. Lin, W. H., L. H. Ziska, O. S. Namuco, and K. Bai. 1997. The interaction
of high temperature and elevated CO2 on photosynthetic acclimation of single
leaves of rice in situ. Physiologia Plantarum 99:178-184.
2855. Wolf, J. 1996. Effects of nutrient supply (NPK) on spring wheat response
to elevated atmospheric CO2. Plant and Soil 185:113-123.
2856. Nakamura, T., M. Osaki, T. Koike, Y. T. Hanba, E. Wada, and T. Tadano.
1997. Effect of CO2 enrichment on carbon and nitrogen interaction in wheat and
soybean. Soil Science and Plant Nutrition 43:789-798.
2892. McKee, I. F., J. F. Bullimore, and S. P. Long. 1997. Will elevated CO2
concentrations protect the yield of wheat from O3 damage? . Plant, Cell and
Environment 20:77-84.
2893. Manderscheid, R., and H. J. Weigel. 1997. Photosynthetic and growth
responses of old and modern spring wheat cultivars to atmospheric CO2
enrichment. Agriculture, Ecosystems and Environment 64:65-73.
2895. Sicher, R. C., and J. A. Bunce. 1997. Relationship of photosynthetic
acclimation to changes of Rubisco activity in field-grown winter wheat and
barley during growth in elevated carbon dioxide. Photosynthesis Research
52:27-38.
2911. Mulholland, B. J., J. Craigon, C. R. Black, J. J. Colls, J. Atherton,
and G. Landon. 1997. Impact of elevated atmospheric CO2 and O3 on gas exchange
and chlorophyll content in spring wheat (Triticum aestivum L). Journal of
Experimental Botany 48:1853-1863.
2919. VanVuuren, M. M. I., D. Robinson, A. H. Fitter, S. D. Chasalow, L.
Williamson, and J. A. Raven. 1997. Effects of elevated atmospheric CO2 and
soil water availability on root biomass, root length, and N, P and K uptake by
wheat. New Phytologist 135:455-465.
2924. Vu, J. C. V., L. H. Allen, K. J. Boote, and G. Bowes. 1997. Effects of
elevated CO2 and temperature on photosynthesis and Rubisco in rice and
soybean. Plant, Cell and Environment 20:68-76.
2928. Ziska, L. H., O. Namuco, T. Moya, and J. Quilang. 1997. Growth and yield
response of field-grown tropical rice to increasing carbon dioxide and air
temperature. Agronomy Journal 89:45-53.
2935. Baker, J. T., L. H. Allen, K. J. Boote, and N. B. Pickering. 1997. Rice
responses to drought under carbon dioxide enrichment. 1. Growth and yield.
Global Change Biology 3:119-128.
3033. Patterson, D. T., and E. P. Flint. 1980. Potential effects of global
atmospheric CO2 enrichment on the growth and competitiveness of C3 and C4 weed
and crop plants. Weed Science 28:71-75.
3034. Potvin, C., and B. R. Strain. 1985. Photosynthetic response to growth
temperature and CO2 enrichment in two species of C4 grasses. Canadian Journal
of Botany 63:483-487.
3035. Potvin, C., and B. R. Strain. 1985. Effects of CO2 enrichment and
temperature on growth in two C4 weeds, Enchinochloa crus-galli and Eleusine
indica. Canadian Journal of Botany 63:1495-1499.
3036. Sionit, N., and D. T. Patterson. 1984. Responses of C4 grasses to
atmospheric CO2 enrichment. I. Effect of irradiance. Oecologia 65:30-34.
3038. Carter, D. R., and K. M. Peterson. 1983. Effects of a CO2 enriched
atmosphere on the growth and competitive interaction of a C3 and a C4 grass.
Oecologia 58:188-193.
3041. Morison, J. I. L., and R. M. Giford. 1984. Plant growth and water use
with limited water supply in high CO2 concentrations. II. Plant dry weight,
partitioning, and water use efficiency. Australian Journal of Plant Physiology
11:375-384.
3042. Wong, S. C. 1979. elevated atmospheric partial pressure of CO2 and plant
growth. I. Interactions of nitrogen nutrition and photosynthetic capacity in
C3 and C4 plants. Oecologia 44:68-74.
Listed are
paper number (PAP_NO, as defined in Sect. 9.)
 CO2 exposure facility
 light
 temperature
 watering
 humidity
 nutrient
 interacting treatment
 biome
 location, and
 comments.
Abbreviations are as described in the body of this report for data files
ndp073.dat and ndp073.wk1.
38
 GC
 600+/-90 UE M-2 S-1
 14/10
 24/18
 40 OR 10 ML PL-1 D-1
 0.588235294
 HOAGLAND'S
 H2O
 GRASS
 EU
186
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 NONE
 CO2 ONLY
 WETL
 NA
488
 GH
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 FIELD CAPACITY OR NONE
 NONE
 CO2 AND WATER
 GRASS
 NA
 2ND YEAR; NO TEMP DATA; FIELD PLANTS.
618
 GC
 AMB
 12H
 20/15 C (DAY/NIGHT)
 WW
 AMB
 NITRATE' SOLUTION
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 .
754
 GC
 0.6 MMOL M-2 S-1
 14 H
 "15, 20, 25, 30 DEG C CONSTANT DAY/NIGHT"
 WW
 &gt;50 %
 COMPLETE NUTRIENT SOLUTION ADDED DAILY
 TEMP
 MEAD
 NA
 MAINTENANCE RESPIRATION RECORDED HERE. GROWTH RESPIRATION
 ALSO REPORTED ONE GC PER CO2 TREATMENT
765
 GC
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 WW
 .
 .
 TEMP
 GRASS_C
 NA
 CONTROL: 28/21/25 C; HI: 40/33/37 C
2066
 GH
 24.8 MOL M-2 D-1
 16 H
 20/14
 .
 .
 COMPLETE FERTILIZER ADDED
 H2O
 GRASS_C
 AU
 TWO VARIETIES USED
2119
 GC
 700 UMOL M-2 S-1
 1/12/00
 12/7; 18/13; 28/23
 WW
 0.4/0.3 +- 0.05 KPA VPD
 HALF-STRENGTH HOAGLAND'S
 TEMP
 GRASS
 AU
 "USABLE DATA ON 4 SPP ONLY, FOR PN"
2125
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW DAILY FC
 AMB
 0.2 MOL M-3 N AND 0.05 MOL M-3 P
 CO2 ONLY
 GRASS
 EU
 "OTHER NUTRIENT DATA, EFFICIENCIES - P,"
2132
 GC
 500 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 25/18
 WW
 50-70
 HOAGLAND'S ALTERNATE DAYS
 O3
 GRASS
 NA
2133
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 NPK APPLIED
 .
 GRASS_C
 EU
2158
 GC
 200 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16 H
 220
 WW
 0.8
 SURPLUS NUTRIENTS
 NONE
 BOREAL
 EU
 "1 GC AT EACH CO2 LEVEL. QY, RHZWT, LWR, LAR"
2159
 GC
 .6 MMOL M-25-1
 14H
 "15,20,25,30"
 WW
 &gt;50%
 """COMPLETE"" IN DAILY WATER"
 TEMP
 GRASS
 NA
2168
 OTC
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
 1991 PRECIPITATION: 17.1 CM; 1992 PRECIPITATION: 26.8 CM; SAMPLE
 SIZE INFERRED FROM DESIGN. LFY.MD
2184
 OTC
 AMBIENT
 15-18
 12-Nov
 AMB AND DRIP
 .
 ADDED WITH DRIP WATER; AMT NOT STATED
 HARVEST
 GRASS
 EU
 CLIPPED TO 5CM AT EACH HARVEST
2192
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 CO2
 GRASS
 NA
 "DATA USED FROM LAST MEASUREMENT PRIOR TO SHADING, F2."
2202
 GC
 725-890 UE
 .
 .
 WW
 .
 HOAGLAND'S; 2 G/M2 N WEEKLY
 CLIPPING TO 5 CM
 GRASS
 AF
 C4; SPOROBOLUS KENTROPHYLLUS; ADDT'L LF NUTRIENTS AVAILABLE IN T1
2208
 GC
 700 UMOL M-2
 12 H
 .
 WW
 AMB
 FERT
 TEMP
 GRASS_C
 NA
 THERE ARE TWO LOLIUM HYBRIDS (2N AND 4N). EACH ONE WAS TREATED
AS A
 SPECIES.
2211
 GH
 ~900 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 25/16
 WW
 35/90
 NONE
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
2227
 GC
 600 UMOL M-2 S-1 AT SEEDLING HT
 15/9
 20/15
 WW
 65/70
 0.8 NM NH4NO3 + 50% LONG ASHTON SOLUTION
 "HI N, LOW N"
 GRASS
 EU
2229
 GC
 AMB
 .
 +4C
 .
 .
 HI/LOW
 TEMP/FERT
 GRASS_C
 EU
2246
 OTC
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 WW
 AMBIENT
 "WEEKLY 1/5 MODIFIED LONG ASHTON- 0.2 MOL M-3 N, 0.05 MOL M-3 P"
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 "NAR, LAR, LWR"
2300
 GC
 800 UMOL/M2S ACTIVE RADIATION
 18 H
 15 C
 WATERED DAILY TO SATURATION
 .
 HALF-STRENGTH MODIFIED HOAGLAND SOLUTION WITH AMMONIUM
NITRATE AND P
 CONCENTRATION OF 32 PPM
 "SOIL TEMPERATURE (5,15, AND 25 C)"
 TUNDRA
 NA
 THIS STUDY FOCUSES ON THE EFFECTS OF SOIL TEMPERATURE. RATE OF PO4
 ABSORPTION WAS LEFT OUT.
2312
 GC
 615 UE (603-621)
 23/11
 100 ML EACH 3 D
 NOT CONTROLLED
 C= HOAGLAND'S T=HOAGLAND'S + UREA (40 G/M2)
 "UREA, CLIPPING"
 GRASS
 NA
 RINSED SAND; CONTROLS HAD HOAGLAND'S
2315
 GH
 AMB/SEASONAL
 AMB/SEASONAL
 AMB/SEASONAL
 SEASONAL; SUMMER WW/DEFICIT
 .
 N-= 160 KG/HA YR; N+=530 KG/HA YR
 "N HI, LO"
 GRASS
 EU
 2 YR STUDY; MICROCLIMATE DETAILS AVAIL. PKS ALSO APPLIED. DATA
USED
FROM
 SUMMER DROUGHT ONLY.
2316
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 IRRIGATION AT AMB LEVELS
 AMB
 160 OR 530 KG N HA-1 YR-1
 FERT
 GRASS
 EU
 "PLASTIC TUNNELS. SWARDS, SOWN. PERIODIC CLIPPING OF ALL PLOTS."
2329
 OTC
 REDUCED ~20%
 AMB
 "AMB + 1-2 DAY, 0-1 NIGHT"
 WW
 .
 NPK; 600 KG N/HA FOR SEASON
 CLIPPING
 GRASS
 EU
 SOWN IN GROUND. DATA FROM 2 GROWING SEASONS. CO2 TMNT YR-ROUND
2330
 OTC and GC
 "OTC= AMBIENT, GC NOT AVAILABLE"
 "OTC=AMBIENT, GC=NOT AVAILABLE"
 "OTC= AMBIENT, GC= FOLLOWED AMBIENT"
 "OTC= AMBIENT, GC= EVERY 1-3 DAYS"
 "OTC= AMBIENT, GC= NOT AVAILABLE"
 GROWTH CHAMBERS; 5-10-15 NPK PLUS MICRONUTRIENTS. 2 ML/H EVERY TWO
WEEKS
 COMPETITION AND METHOD (OTC AND GC)
 GRASS
 NA
 "GC (PH = 6.5) PHOTOPERIOD, LIGHT AND HUMIDITY ARE REPORTED IN
WANT,
 LECHOWICZ AND POTWIN (1994). COMPETING SPECIES (TRIFOLIUM REPENS,
POA
 PRATENSIS, PHLEUM PRATENSE, AGROSTIS STOLONIFERA) NO INDIVIDUAL
POTS."
2337
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB; X=11.3
 DRIP
 AMB
 "YES, UNKNOWN"
 NONE
 MEAD
 EU
 COMMON SPP + CULTIVARS; NORWAY; MARITIME
2341
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB/WW
 AMB
 NPK 1.5:1:1.5; =40 KG N HA-1 Y-1
 "CO2, NUTRIENTS"
 EU
 3 YR EXP. OTCS UP 98-108 D Y-1. SOME DATA ALSO FROM YEARS 1 &amp; 2
2342
 OTC
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 "N, P, K 20 G M-2, 120 DAY TIME-RELEASE OSMOCOTE"
 "ADDITIONAL NUTRIENTS N, P, K"
 GRASS
 NA
 MONOCULTURES OF SIX SPECIES AND ONE MIXED COMMUNITY. SERPENTIME
SOIL
2345
 otc
 amb
 AMR
 AMB; AMB +3
 WW
 .
 NPK + NUTRIENTS
 TEMP
 GRASS
 EU
 OTCS PLACED IN GH FOR WARMING
2347
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 NONE
 CO2 ONLY
 GRASS
 NA
 JASPER RIDGE
2350
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 17
 WW
 .
 7 G M-2 N; 5 G M-2 P; 7 G M-2 K
 CLIPPING EVERY 4 WK
 GRASS
 EU
 "ALSO INCLUDED TEMP, CO2 X TEMP, MIXTURES OF SPP"
2351
 GC
 700 UMOL M-2 S-1
 12
 12/7; 18/13; 28/23
 WW
 .
 HALF-STRENGTH HOAGLAND'S GX D-1
 TEMP
 GRASS
 AU
 GROWN IN STERILE SAND
2357
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 OSMOCOTE: 20 G M
 NUTRIENTS
 GRASS
 NA
 JASPER RIDGE
2358
 GH
 AMB; 640 UMOL M-2 S-1
 AMB; 640 UMOL M-2 S-1
 13-26
 WW
 0.08
 13 G N M-2; 3.18 G P M-2; 10.61 G K M-2
 TEMP (+4)
 GRASS
 EU
 GERMINATION IN POTS IN FIELD; CO2 BEGAN AFTER ~6.5 MONTHS
2362
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 13;10
 WW
 .
 NOT LIMITING
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 TUNNELS = GH
2363
 GC
 552 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14 H
 26/21
 WW
 60-70%
 HALF STRENGTH HOAGLAND'S; N=6 OR .5 mM
 O3 + FERT
 GRASS
 NA
 "OZONE = 3 +/- .3, 92 +/- .4 nMOL MOL-1; FERT = 6 OR .5 nM N.
 MACRONUTRIENTS SAME FOR HI/LO FERT TMNT."
2364
 FACE
 AMB
 .
 .
 .
 .
 .
 .
 GRASS_C
 EU
 MINIFACE
2366
 OTC
 89% OF AMB
 AMB
 32 / 24.9
 WW
 .
 .
 FERT
 GRASS_C
 AS
 NO SUPPLEMENTAL N
2367
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 IRRIGATED WITH NUTRIENT ENRICHED WATER
 NONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
 .
2369
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 29/21 OR 37/29
 WW
 70 +/- 5
 PROVIDED
 WETL
 WETL
 AS
 29/21= CTL; 37/29 = HI TEMP (PC.1354). 17 CULTIVARS TREATED AS REPS
2372
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 "AMB/AMB+2.5, 18-30"
 WW
 AMB
 7 G N M-2
 TEMP
 GRASS
 EU
 "TEMP INCREASE USING INFRA-RED LAMPS ALL MATERIAL CLIPPED PRIOR
 TO START OF TEMP TMT. EFFECTIVE CO2 DURATION USED. 12- AGWT, LFN, PN"
2379
 GC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 .
 NONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
 10 CULTIVARS TREATED AS REPS.
2383
 GH
 .
 AMB
 AMB AND AMB+4
 WW
 .
 FERTILIZED
 TEMP
 GRASS_C
 EU
2387
 GH
 AMB- ~MAX=800 UMOL M-2 S-1
 "16, W LIGHTS"
 18/10-24/18
 WW 1X WK-1
 .
 NO ADDITIONAL
 "330, 500, 660 UL L-1 CO2"
 GRASS
 EU
 "CALCEROUS GRASSLAND. SPP AND ECOSYS 76 PLANTS/ CONTAINER
 REPRESENTING FIELD %, PESTICIDES USED."
2395
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WATERED OCCASIONALLY
 AMB
 .
 .
 GRASS
 EU
 THE SPECIES GROW IN A XERIC TEMPERATE LOESS STEPPE.
2398
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB (~11)
 WW
 ..
 "ADDED, BUT NOT SPECIFIC; SEE TEXT."
 SEASONALITY
 GRASS
 EU
 USING GRAND MEANS AND SE ONLY; NOT USING SEASONAL DATA.
2401
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 AMB
 LOW/HI NPK
 FERT
 GRASS
 NA
2403
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 150 KG N HA-1 AND 270 KG N HA-1
 FERT/OZONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
2407
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 3 C LESS THAN AMB
 WW + DROUGHT
 .
 .
 H2O
 GRASS_C
 NA
 .
2420
 GC
 550 UMOL M-2 S-1
 SEASONAL
 SEASONAL
 WW
 .
 NONE
 TEMP
 GRASS
 NA
 "WATER TMT ALSO, BUT NOT USED IN DATASET. ""WINTER"" TEMP = 3"
2427
 GH
 AMB + SUPPL (28.4 MOL M-2 S-1)
 16
 28/22
 WW/DRY
 .
 5KG M-3 15:10:10:2 NPK MG 3 MO RELEASE
 H2O
 GRASS
 AU
2430
 GH
 AMB 2-3.9 MJ M-2 D-1
 AMB
 19 - 22.5
 WW
 .
 SUPPLEMENTED
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 NOT USING 1992 DATA
2440
 GC
 1115 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 25/15
 WW
 .
 N= 0 OR 300 KG HA-1; P= 56 KG HA-1; K= 46 KG HA-1
 "FERT, TEMP"
 GRASS
 NA
2441
 GC
 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 12/12/98
 "DAY 20, 35; NIGHT 15"
 WW
 60/~100
 HALF STRENGTH HOAGLAND'S; =400 UL L-1 N
 TEMP 20 = CTL
 GRASS
 NA
2443
 GH
 SEASONAL
 SEASONAL
 SEASONAL
 WW
 .
 HOAGLAND'S + - N; SEE METHODS AND RESULTS
 NONE. SEE RESULTS
 GRASS
 NA
 "N HAD NO EFFECT ON PN, OR APPARENTLY ON TOTWT"
2444
 GC
 600 UMOL/M2S PFD
 15 H
 20/15 DEGREES C
 WW
 "65/70 % (DAY,NIGHT)"
 "NITROGEN CONCENTRATIONS (.01, .1, 1.0, AND 5.0 MG N/L)"
 NITROGEN CONCENTRATIONS BY N SUPPLY (AMMONIUM OR NITRATE)
 GRASS
 EU
 SAMPLE SIZE OF GAS EXCHANGE MEASUREMENTS WAS USED FOR ALL
MEASUREMENTS
 BECAUSE IT WAS THE ONLY ONE AVAILABLE. AGROSTIS CAPILLARIS IS A FAST
 GROWING GRASS. NARDUS ESTRICTA IS A SLOW GROWING GRASS.
2448
 GC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 .
 TEMP
 GRASS_C
 NA
 .
2454
 GC
 AMB
 14 HR
 AMB
 WW
 60-70%RH
 NUTRIENTS SUPPLEMENTED TWICE A WEEK
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 .
2468
 GC
 200 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14H
 19/15 C
 .
 .
 .
 .
 GRASS_C
 EU
 ANOTHER SET OF DATA (CO2 * SO2) CAN BE EXTRACTED
2474
 GH
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 .
 WW
 .
 MODIFIED HOAGLANDS
 "N= 5, 20, OR 50 MG L-1; P= 2, 11, OR 30 MG L-1; K=5, 20, 50 MG L-1"
 GRASS
 EU
 "CO2= AMB, AMB+250...1:1 SAND:PEAT; DATA TAKEN FROM P=3 + K=3 ONLY.
 AGN, AGC, AGK, AGP"
2480
 GH
 200 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14 H
 25/18
 "WW, FLD"
 .
 NATIVE SOIL
 "FLD, SALT"
 WETL
 EU
 PLANTS ROTATED BETWEEN 2 GHS
2492
 GC
 220-250 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 23.5/19
 80% OF FIELD CAPACITY
 30/55
 "194 MG N, 13 MG P, 24 MG K, 39 MG MG POT-1"
 DENSITY
 GRASS
 EU
 "USING LOWEST AND HIGHEST DENSITIES ONLY, AS REPS"
2502
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 PRECIP
 AMB
 NONE
 NONE
 WETL
 NA
 "SAME PARAMETERS WERE MEASURED AT DIFFERENT YEARS AND/OR THE
SAME YEAR,
 BUT DIFFERENT MONTHS. EACH MONTH AND/OR YEAR WAS CONSIDERED A
SEPARATE
 DATA POINT BECAUSE TIME OF EXPOSITION CHANGED. THE PAPER INCLUDES
DATA
 ON LEAF RUBISCO AND LEAF SOLUBLE PROTEIN."
2503
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 SEASONAL; -5-25
 AMB
 SEASONAL
 N (100 OR 420 KG HA-1 Y-1); 120 KG HA-1 P205; 240 KG HA-1 K2O; 16 KG HA-1
 MGO
 FERT: 100 OR 420 KG N HA-1 Y-1
 GRASS
 EU
 OOT IN GROWTH BAGS. ETHANOL SOLUBLE TNC USED IN DATABASE.
WATER-
SOLUBLE
 TNC ALSO AVAILABLE.
2504
 GH
 AMB; 180 UMOL M-2 S-1 + 100 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 20
 WW
 .
 HI N=54 G M-2; LO N=9.5 G M-2; + OTHER NUTRIENTS
 FERT
 GRASS
 EU
 .
2510
 GC
 AMB
 .
 AMB
 WW
 AMB
 FERTILIZED WEEKLY
 .
 .
 EU
2521
 GC
 500 UMOL M-2 S-1
 13.5 H
 23/17
 WW
 60-70
 .
 OZONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
 .
2522
 GC
 500 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 24/14
 WW
 65+/-5
 INITIAL AND EVERY 21 DAYS
 O3
 GRASS
 EU
2525
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 AMB
 .
 .
 WETL
 NA
 CARBON CONTENT WITH SE/SD &amp; N; ADDT'L VAR
2531
 OTC
 AMB - 11%
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 NONE
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
 CO2 FROM APRIL/ MAY THRU OCT EACH OF 3 YRS
2541
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB+
 AMB
 AMB
 NO ADDITIONAL
 CO2
 GRASS
 NA
 "JASPER RIDGE. GS, E, LFY, PN, SEEDS, HT, AGWT, WVE, DNSITY,
 ISOTOPE, SEED WT, FRUITWT, SEED C, SEED N."
2547
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 28/21/25(H20)
 WW
 .
 NPK INITIAL; VARIABLE N ADDED DURING SEASON
 CO2 ONLY APPROPRIATE
 WETL
 NA
2579
 GC
 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 23/16
 WW
 70-80
 ALL: 4.6 MG P; 5.8 MG K; N= 0 OR 32 MG POT-1
 FERT
 .
 .
2580
 GH
 amb
 amb
 32/23; 35/26; 38/29
 ww
 .
 "12.6, 6.3, 6.3, G N M-2 AT 7, 31 + 63 D"
 NONE
 WETL
 NA
 .
2595
 GC
 350 UMOL M-2 S-1
 15/9
 20/17
 WW
 .
 .
 .
 .
 .
2597
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 .
 NONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
 .
2644
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 101 KG N HA-1; SEE ALSO T1
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
2654
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
 JASPER RIDGE
2666
 GH
 AMB 25-29 MOL M-2 D-1
 16 H
 20/14
 WW / DRY
 .
 SOLUBLE OR SLOW RELEASE ADDED
 H2O
 GRASS_C
 AU
2669
 GC
 220-250 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 17-Dec
 WW
 0.571428571
 N: 0 OR 765 MG POT-1; 114 MG P; 193 MG K; 26 MG MG
 FERT
 GRASS
 EU
 USING ONLY CTL; HIGHEST FERT LEVELS
2692
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 32/23; 35/26; 38/29
 WET/DRY
 AMB
 NON-LIMITING; REPEATED APPLICATIONS
 H2O
 GRASS
 NA
 DRY = HALF OF WET (WW). USE WET AS CTL
2698
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 NONE
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
 "SUM Y EXPERIMENT. 2 OTC'S W/ CO2, OTC'S - CO2"
2709
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 .
 FERT/COMP
 GRASS
 EU
 TIME ASSUMED TO BE 730 BECAUSE AGWT WAS SUM OF TWO SEASONS
2710
 FACE
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 LO: 10-14 G N M-2 Y-1; HI: 42-56 G N M-2 Y-1
 DEFOL: 4 OR 7-8 Y-1; FERT
 GRASS
 EU
 MET IN TABLE 1
2711
 GH
 9.2 + 24.9 MOL M-2 S-1
 AMB
 30/25
 WW
 &gt;90
 "30 MG N POT-1 + 60 G N POT-1, SEASONALLY"
 LIGHT
 GRASS
 AU
2715
 GC
 300 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 18/4
 WW; 14% H20
 0.928571429
 28 MG P + 50 MG K KG-1 + N TREATMENTS
 N 8KG N HA-1 OR 278 KG N HA-1
 GRASS
 EU
2718
 GC
 794
 AMB
 25/13 (DAY/NIGHT)
 WW
 AMB
 HOAGLAND'S SOLUTION EVERY 3 D
 DEFOL
 GRASS
 NA
 .
2723
 GH
 85-90% AMB
 14-H
 AMB/AMB + 3 C
 WW
 AMB
 .
 TEMP
 .
 EU
 GS WITH NO SE/SD. Vc MAX WITH SE/SD AND N IN FIG. 4
2735
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 "AMB, AMB+4"
 WW
 AMB
 10 G M-2 N; 15 G M-2 P; 15 G M-2 K
 TEMP
 GRASS
 EU
 80% OF UVB
2737
 GH
 25 MOL M-2 DAY-1
 16/8
 17
 WW
 65
 "COMPLETE, INCLUDE 188 MG L-1 N"
 "O3, SOIL"
 GRASS
 EU
 O3 NOT USED FOR PHYL DATASET
2756
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB + DROUGHT
 AMB
 NONE
 H2O
 GRASS
 NA
 "UNDISTURBED TALL GRASS PRAIRIE; EARLY, MID + LATE SEASON DATA;
EXP.
RAN
 4Y PRIOR TO THIS STUDY"
2758
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 .
 NONE
 GRASS
 EU
 .
2785
 OTC
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 AMBIENT
 HI FERT TRT ONLY
 FERT. 20 G M-2 NPK OSMOCOTE
 GRASS
 NA
 JASPER RIDGE. SERPENTINE SOIL
2793
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 GRASS
 EU
 MINI-RHIZOTRONE. DATA USED FROM 10 CM
2802
 GH (TUNNEL)
 AMB
 AMB
 0.3 C HIGHER DURING DAY; 0.2 C LOWER AT NIGHT
 .
 .
 FERT
 GRASS
 EU
 .
2821
 GH
 79% OF AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 WW
 .
 8 G N M-2 PER 24 DAYS
 CO2
 GRASS
 EU
2834
 GC
 750 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 16
 WW
 0.54 KPA
 0.2 OR 2.5 MOL M-3 N; 0.04 OR 0.5 MOL M-3 P
 LOW N+LOW P OR HI N + HI P
 GRASS
 EU
 "P, OTHER MINERALS"
2835
 GC
 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16
 30/20
 WW
 0.0025
 "HOAGLAND'S, ALTERNATE WATERING"
 .
 GRASS
 NA
2839
 OTC
 85% OF AMB
 AMB
 "25/29 ( AMB, AMB+4)"
 WW
 .
 220 KG N HA-1
 TEMP
 WETL
 AS
2855
 GH
 AMB+
 16/8
 20/15
 WW
 70
 NPK (HOAGLAND'S) OR 0.1 N (MODIFIED HOAGLAND'S)
 FERT
 GRASS
 EU
2856
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 26/16 C DAY/NIGHT
 WW
 .
 .
 FERT
 GRASS_C
 AS
 .
2892
 GC
 645 UMOL M-2 S-1
 16/8
 24/18
 WW
 .
 MODIFIED SHIVE'S SOLUTION
 O3
 GRASS
 EU
 TIME FOR BIOMASS ASSUMED &gt; 42 D; SEE FIG 6
2893
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 19
 WW
 67-71%
 0.4 G L-1 N; 0.3 G L-1 P205; 0.4 G L-1 K20
 NONE
 GRASS_C
 EU
 INTRODUCED IN 1890
2895
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 .
 .
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
2911
 OTC
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 AMB
 O3
 GRASS
 EU
 CTL O3 = 26-29 NMOL MOL-1; HI O3= 84 NMOL MOL-1 AVE FOR ALL DAYS
2919
 GC
 AMB
 AMB
 15 C MEAN
 .
 .
 "150 MG N, 18.1 MG P AND 34 MG K"
 H20
 GRASS_C
 EU
2924
 GH
 AMB; PN &gt;1200 UMOL M-2 S-1
 AMB
 32/23; 35/26; 38/29
 WW
 .
 "P, K= 9 G M-2; N (UREA) 12.6-6.3 G M-2 X3 DATES"
 TEMP
 WETL
 NA
2928
 OTC
 85% OF AMB
 AMB
 X= 25; AMB+4
 WW
 .
 N: 110 KG HA-1 WET SEASON; 220 KG HA-1 DRY
 TEMP
 WETL
 AS
 DATA ON DEVELOPMENT STAGES
2935
 OTC
 AMB
 .
 28/21 (DAY / NIGHT)
 .
 .
 .
 H2O
 GRASS_C
 NA
 SPAR: SOIL-PLANT-ATMOSPHERE-RESEARCH CHAMBER
3034
 GC
 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 28/22; 24/18; 21/25
 WW
 70
 .
 TEMP. NOTE ECOTYPES
 GRASS
 NA
 "TEMPS: MISS: CTL=28, L0=2, . ; N.C: CTL=24, LO=21, HI=28; QUEBEC:
 CTL=21, . , HI =28"
3033
 GC
 65 UE M-2 S-1
 14/10
 28/22
 WW
 0.7
 HALF STRENGTH HOAGLANDS
 NONE
 MIXED
 NA
3035
 GC
 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 28/22; 24/18; 21/15
 WW
 70
 .
 TEMP NOTE ECOTYPES
 GRASS
 NA
 "TEMPS: MISS: CTL=28, LO=21, . ; N.C: CTL=24, LO-21, HI=28; QUEBEC:
 CTL=21, . , HI=28"
3036
 GC
 150 OR 1000 UMOL M-2 S-1
 14/10
 29/23
 WW
 70
 HALF STRENGTH HOAGLANDS
 LIGHT
 GRASS
 NA
3038
 GH
 AMB
 AMB
 34
 WW
 .
 .
 NONE
 GRASS
 NA
 MIXED AND UNMIXED CULTURES
3042
 GH
 AMB; 2ME M-2 S-1
 AMB
 32/20
 WW
 50-70
 "4 LEVELS OF HENITTS: 24,12, 4, OR MM NITRATE"
 FERT
 GRASS_C
 NA
 ONLY MAIZE DATA WERE TAKEN
3401
 GH
 AMB + LOW INTENSITY INCANDESCENT
 1/16/00
 28/23
 "AT PLANTING ONLY, DRYING THEREAFTER"
 60-70
 ..
 H20
 GRASS
 AU
 ASSUMING THAT TIME COURSE FOR WATER LOSS IS SIMILAR FOR ALL GRASS
SPECIES
 (USING WHEAT (COMPANION PAPER)); WE USE TIME CLASSES FOR ANALYSES.
&#239;&#187;&#191;
 &#160;&amp;middot;&#160;]]></Descriptive_file>
      <Data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/ndp073/ndp073.txt]]></Data_file>
      <Data_IO_file></Data_IO_file>
      <Initial_date_of_data_publication><![CDATA[19991101]]></Initial_date_of_data_publication>
      <Most_recent_date_of_data_publication><![CDATA[19991101]]></Most_recent_date_of_data_publication>
      <Data_file_location><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/ndp073/]]></Data_file_location>
      <Total_size_of_all_files><![CDATA[921KB]]></Total_size_of_all_files>
      <Distribution><![CDATA[external]]></Distribution>
      <CDIAC_contact><![CDATA[Thomas A. Boden; email: bodenta@ornl.gov]]></CDIAC_contact>
      <Notes><![CDATA[ To perform a statistically rigorous meta-analysis of research results on the response by herbaceous vegetation to increased atmospheric CO2 levels, a multiparameter database of responses was compiled from the published literature. Seventy-eight independent CO2-enrichment studies, covering 53 species and 26 response parameters, reported mean response, sample size, and variance of the response (either as standard deviation or standard error). An additional 43 studies, covering 25 species and 6 response parameters, did not report variances. This numeric data package accompanies the Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center's (CDIAC's) NDP- 072, which provides similar information for woody vegetation.
<br><br>
 This numeric data package contains a 30-field data set of CO2- exposure experiment responses by herbaceous plants (as both a flat ASCII file and a spreadsheet file), files listing the references to the CO2-exposure experiments and specific comments relevant to the data in the data sets, and this documentation file (which includes SAS and Fortran codes to read the ASCII data file; SAS is a registered trademark of the SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, North Carolina 27511). ]]></Notes>
    </CDIAC>
  </mercury>
</metadata>
