<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin><![CDATA[Blasing, T. J. ]]></origin>
        <origin><![CDATA[Marland, G.]]></origin>
        <origin><![CDATA[Broniak, C. T.]]></origin>
        <title><![CDATA[Estimates of Annual Fossil-Fuel CO2 Emitted for Each State in the U.S.A. and the District of Columbia for Each Year from 1960 through 2001]]></title>
        <geoform></geoform>
        <onlink><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/xml/cdp/metadata/Trends/Emissions/Est_Annual_Fossil_Fuel_CO2_Emissions_1960_2001.xml]]></onlink>
        <onlink><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/trends/emis_mon/stateemis/emis_state.html]]></onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract><![CDATA[Estimates of Annual Fossil-Fuel CO2 Emitted for Each State in the U.S.A. and the District of Columbia for Each Year from 1960 through 2001]]></abstract>
      <supplinf></supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate><![CDATA[19600101]]></begdate>
          <enddate><![CDATA[20011231]]></enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress></progress>
      <update> As appropriate</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc></westbc>
        <eastbc></eastbc>
        <northbc></northbc>
        <southbc></southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>CDIAC</themekt>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Carbon]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Carbon Dioxide]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Emissions]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[trends]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[energy]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Fossil Fuel]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Annual]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[CO2 ]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[State ]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[U.S.A. ]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[District of Columbia ]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[D. C. ]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[1960 ]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[2001]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Coal ]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Petroleum]]></themekey>
        <themekey><![CDATA[Natural Gas]]></themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Thematic Area</themekt>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Place Keywords</placekt>
        <placekey></placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper><![CDATA[T. J. Blasing; email: blasingtj@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntfax></cntfax>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg></cntorg>
          <cntper><![CDATA[T. J. Blasing; email: blasingtj@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice></cntvoice>
        <cntfax></cntfax>
        <cntemail></cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc></resdesc>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/]]></computer>
            <accinstr></accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20120919 163605</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntper><![CDATA[T. J. Blasing; email: blasingtj@ornl.gov]]></cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper></cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice></cntvoice>
        <cntemail></cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  </metainfo>
  <Local-Control-Number>Created 20050809 152910 by 160.91.18.40</Local-Control-Number>
  <mercury>
    <begdate></begdate>
    <enddate></enddate>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Carbon]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Carbon Dioxide]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Emissions]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[trends]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[energy]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Fossil Fuel]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Annual]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[CO2 ]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[State ]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[U.S.A. ]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[District of Columbia ]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[D. C. ]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[1960 ]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[2001]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Coal ]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Petroleum]]></Keywords>
    <Keywords><![CDATA[Natural Gas]]></Keywords>
    <Documentation_Link>
      <Text><![CDATA[ &#187;&#160;USA State-Level Emission Estimates
T.J. Blasing and Gregg Marland
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center, Environmental Sciences Division, 
Christine Broniak
Department of Agricultural &amp; Resource Economics, Oregon State University, 
Consumption data for coal, petroleum, and natural gas are multiplied by 
their respective thermal conversion factors, which are in units of heat energy 
per unit of fuel consumed (i.e., per cubic foot, barrel, or ton), to calculate 
the amount of heat energy derived from fuel combustion. The thermal conversion 
factors are given in Appendix A of each issue of Monthly Energy Review, published 
by the Energy Information Administration (EIA) of the U.S. Department of 
Energy (DOE). Results are expressed in terms of heat energy obtained from 
each fuel type. These energy values were obtained from the State Energy Data Report 
(EIA, 2003a), 
(
http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/states/sep_use/total/csv/use_csv.html), and 
served as our basic input. The energy data are also available in hard copy from the 
Energy Information Administration, U.S. Department of Energy, as the State 
Energy Data Report (EIA, 2003a,b).
These energy consumption data were multiplied by their respective carbon 
dioxide emission factors, which are called carbon content coefficients by 
the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA). These factors quantify the 
mass of oxidized carbon per unit of energy released from a fuel. In the U.S.A., 
they are typically expressed in units of teragrams of carbon 
(Tg-C = 10 grams of carbon) per quadrillion 
British thermal units (quadrillion Btu = 10 Btu, 
or "quad"), and are highest for coal and lowest for natural gas. Our results are 
given in teragrams of , 
multiply by 44/12 (= 3.67).
Carbon content coefficients for various fuels are given in Tables 2-16 through 2-20 of 
Annex 2 in EPA (2004), and (for coal) in Appendix E of EIA (2003b). Emissions factors 
we used for coal from 1980 through 1999 are from Appendix E of EIA (2003b). 
Because emissions factors were not available for all years for which we have energy data, 
the 1980 values were used for preceding years, and 1999 values were used for years 2000 
and 2001. Because carbon dioxide emission factors changed very litte, if at all, from 
year-to-year (typically less than 1% of their longer-term average) the use of 1980 values 
for prior years did not appear to have any affect on our results at the national level. 
However, caution is suggested for detailed interpretation of variability of carbon 
emissions from coal in individual states that import much of their coal so that the 
locations of the producing mines may vary widely from year to year. Caution is also 
suggested when using state data with abrupt increases or decreases in carbon emitted 
from one fuel. Usually, these are real changes that can be traced back to the 
installation of a natural gas pipeline or the opening of a large facility in a small 
state. However, in some cases (e.g., the abrupt increase in natural gas use in 
Rhode Island in 1992) the cause of an abrupt change in emissions values is not clear, 
and more detailed investigation is suggested before making conclusions about such 
changes. For assistance, begin by contacting 
The energy data we used are categorized by end use; for coal and natural 
gas, end uses largely include fuel for energy production, with only a small 
or negligible percentage going to non-fuel uses. End uses for petroleum are 
vastly more complicated, and include petrochemicals used in the manufacture 
of plastic products (e.g., bags, toys, prosthetic limbs) and fabrics (e.g., nylon 
and polyester) as well as waxes, asphalt, graphite, lubricants, solvents waxes, etc. 
The carbon in some petroleum products (e.g., lubricants) is largely oxidized while 
virtually none of the carbon is oxidized in others (e.g., asphalt, waxes). The 
energy amount that would be realized from the oxidation of 100% of any petroleum 
product was multiplied by the fraction that is assumed to be actually oxidized, 
and the rest of the carbon was assumed to be sequestered. The sequestered fractions 
used to estimate the amounts of carbon dioxide release during consumption are 
given in Table 2-32 of EPA (2004). This procedure led to higher values of oxidized 
carbon than earlier procedures incorporating the assumption that all carbon in 
these products was sequestered.
The carbon dioxide emission factors for some petroleum products vary from 
year to year due to factors such as changing blends of motor gasoline. Carbon 
coefficients we used for petroleum products from 1990 forward are given by the 
EPA in Table 2-17 and 2-19, in Annex 2 of EPA (2004). Values 
for 1984-1989 are given in Table A1 of EIA (1995); for years prior to 1984, the 
1984 values were used. Because year-to year changes in carbon coefficients for 
petroleum products are less than 1% of their longer-term averages, the use of 
constant (1984) values for prior years did not noticeably affect our results.
Data are available for over 30 different petroleum products, with the exact 
breakdown varying somewhat from year to year. These products have been treated 
individually until the final step of the estimation, at which time 
CO emissions were summed and attributed 
to liquid petroleum products.
Natural gas is almost all methane or other combustible hydrocarbons, with only 
a very small fraction of impurities such as sulfur and heavy metals; its carbon 
coefficient is, therefore, relatively small and practically constant. The 
carbon coefficient for natural gas is given in Table 2-19 in Annex 2 of EPA (2004), as 
a constant of 14.47 Tg-C/quad.
These carbon emissions estimates were ultimately derived from values of fuel 
consumed at full combustion: in billions of cubic feet for natural gas; in 
millions of barrels, for petroleum products, and in thousand of short tons, 
for coal. In reality, a small percentage of carbon is released as soot, ash, 
or long-lived hydrocarbons. We assume that combustion is only 99 per cent 
complete; which is the same factor used by the EPA (EPA 2004, Table 2-16 of 
Annex 2) except that EPA used a factor of 0.995 for natural gas for liquid 
petroleum gas (LPG).
, 
results are presented here in terms of the mass of carbon only (multiply the 
mass of carbon by 44/12 to convert to CO). 
We assume that any carbon emitted to the atmosphere as CO will soon be 
converted to CO
Differences from other (CDIAC) emissions estimates: Marland et al. (2004) have 
presented estimates of annual carbon dioxide emissions (as carbon) from fossil 
fuel consumption for all countries. The annual values presented there for the 
U.S.A. differ slightly from the national sums of the state data presented here 
for 3 primary reasons.
In order to provide comparable estimates for all 
countries, Marland et al. have relied on energy data from the United Nations 
whereas this analysis relies on energy data directly from DOE. United Nations 
data are presumably derived from the same DOE 
data sets but differences in detail occur due to differences in units, categories, 
accounting conventions, and the complexity of handling large amounts of data.
Estimates from the United Nations data are based on "apparent consumption," which 
is defined as production + imports - exports - changes in stocks; whereas the 
U.S. DOE data provide direct estimates of consumption. There are systematic 
differences between these two data sets that are attributable to data sampling 
and collection; the data sets differ by around 2%.
The Marland et al. estimates 
are for CO emissions during fuel combustion 
whereas the estimates here include a contribution from the oxidation of petrochemical 
products that are used for non-fuel purposes, such as lubricants and petroleum coke.
As a consequence of these 3 factors, the national estimates presented here tend to 
be higher than those of Marland et al. even though they do not yet account for carbon 
oxidized during gas flaring or from the calcining of limestone during manufacture of 
cement [when combined, these processes represent about 1 per cent of the total 
anthropogenic carbon emissions from the U.S. (Marland et al., 2004)]. We believe 
the estimates presented here provide a more complete account of total national 
emissions. However, for comparing U.S. emissions with those of other nations, 
we still recommend the use of the U.S. data in Marland et al., 2004, which are 
derived similarly for all nations, and systematic errors applicable to any one 
nation are likely to apply to other nations as well. Neither set of total emissions 
estimates includes carbon from bunker fuels, i.e. (fuels that are loaded in the 
U.S. but used by planes and ships in international commerce). Marland et al. (2004) 
provide carbon esissions estimates for bunker fuels, but they are not included 
in the totals as given.
These estimates of total annual carbon emissions for the USA have been compared 
with estimates derived from monthly data using similar methods. These estimates 
are consistently about 1.5% greater than those derived from the monthly data; the 
reason for this is not presently known.
Total carbon emissions almost doubled from 1960-2001, increasing from 790 Teragrams/year 
(Tg/yr) to 1542 Tg/yr. For the United States as a whole, and for many individual states, 
carbon emissions peaked sometime in the 1970s, declined in the early 1980s, and then 
resumed growth at a rate somewhat less than that before 1970. Per capita emissions 
have shown a much more modest increase since the decline in the early 1980s, and have 
not yet returned to the 1970s levels of around 6 Mg per person per year. This has 
been especially true for states whose energy supply is largely petroleum dependent.
Coal had the most rapid increase of the three fuels, both in total carbon (301 Tg/year 
increase) and in percentage (221% of its 1960 value by 2001). Per capita coal emissions 
grew from 1.38 Megagrams/person (Mg/person) to 1.93 Mg/person, or to 140% of their 1960 
value, while per capita emissions of oil increased to only 115%, and per capita emissions 
of natural gas increased to only 116%, of their 1960 value. The states differ widely 
in per capita emissions for year 2001; California emitted about 3 Mg/capita while Wyoming 
emitted more than 10 times that (about 34 Mg/person).
Carbon emissions from coal combustion have increased sharply in states that export 
electricity produced from local deposits of low-sulfur coal, so that states with low 
populations and large repositories of low-sulfur coal (e.g., North Dakota and Wyoming) 
are emitting about 10 times the carbon per capita (from coal, oil, and gas, combined) 
of more heavily populated states, such as California, that are importing electricity 
generated from coal combustion. 
EIA (Energy Information Administration, U.S. Department of Energy) 1995. Emissions of 
Greenhouse gases in the United States: 1987-1994. DOE/EIA-0573(94), Office of Integrated 
Analysis and Forecasting, Washington DC.
EIA (Energy Information Administration, U.S. Department of Energy) 2003a. State Energy 
Data Report. 
http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/states/sep_use/total/csv/use_csv.html
EIA (Energy Information Administration, U.S. Department of Energy) 2003b. State Energy 
Data 2000: Consumption, Technical Notes, 
http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/states/_use_multistate.html
EPA (U.S. Environmental Protection Agency) 2004. Inventory of Greenhouse Gas Emissions and 
Sinks: 1990-2002, EPA 430-R-04-003, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Washington D.C., 
308 pp. plus annexes, available electronically from:
Marland, G., T.A. Boden, and R.J. Andres. 2004. Global, Regional, and National Fossil-Fuel 
CO Emissions. In Trends: A Compendium of Data on Global 
Change. Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, 
U.S. Department of Energy, Oak Ridge, TN, U.S.A., available electronically 
from: 
CITE AS: Blasing, T.J., C.T. Broniak, and G. Marland, 2004. Estimates of Annual Fossil-Fuel CO Emitted for Each State in the U.S.A. and the District of Columbia for Each Year from 1960 through 2001. Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, U.S. Department of Energy, Oak Ridge, TN, U.S.A. doi 10.3334/CDIAC/00003
&#239;&#187;&#191;
 &#160;&amp;middot;&#160;]]></Text>
    </Documentation_Link>
    <OME_Software_Version>Version 4.7.5, Revision Date: 04 Apr 2006</OME_Software_Version>
    <OME_DTD_Version>metadata10.dtd</OME_DTD_Version>
    <Temporal_Resolution></Temporal_Resolution>
    <enddate_blank></enddate_blank>
    <Harvest_Date>2017-09-01</Harvest_Date>
    <File_ID>Created 20050809 152910 by 160.91.18.40</File_ID>
    <Spatial_Extent></Spatial_Extent>
    <Metadata_URL><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/xml/cdp/metadata/Trends/Emissions/Est_Annual_Fossil_Fuel_CO2_Emissions_1960_2001.xml]]></Metadata_URL>
    <CDIAC>
      <Product_number><![CDATA[doi 10.3334/CDIAC/00003]]></Product_number>
      <Product_title><![CDATA[Estimates of Annual Fossil-Fuel CO2 Emitted for Each State in the U.S.A. and the District of Columbia for Each Year from 1960 through 2001]]></Product_title>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Blasing, T. J. ]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[Oak Ridge National Laboratory]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Marland, G.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[Oak Ridge National Laboratory]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Author>
        <Name><![CDATA[Broniak, C. T.]]></Name>
        <Company><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Company>
        <Organization><![CDATA[Department of Agricultural &amp; Resource Economics]]></Organization>
      </Author>
      <Thematic_area><![CDATA[Fossil-Fuel CO2 Emissions]]></Thematic_area>
      <Site_info>
        <Site_name><![CDATA[United States]]></Site_name>
        <Site_URL><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/trends/emis_mon/stateemis/emis_state.htm]]></Site_URL>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/trends/emis_mon/stateemis/graphics/graphics.html]]></Site_data_file>
        <Site_data_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/ftp/trends/emis_mon/stateemis/percapbystate.csv]]></Site_data_file>
      </Site_info>
      <Data_site></Data_site>
      <Variable><![CDATA[Years (1960 - 2001)]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[State: Coal]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[State: Oil]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[State: Gas]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[United States: Coal]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[United States: Oil]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[United States: Gas]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[United States: Total]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[United States/Capita: Coal]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[United States/Capita: Oil]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[United States/Capita: Gas]]></Variable>
      <Variable><![CDATA[United States/Capita: Total/Capita]]></Variable>
      <Descriptive_file><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/trends/emis_mon/stateemis/emis_state.html &#187;&#160;USA State-Level Emission Estimates
T.J. Blasing and Gregg Marland
Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center, Environmental Sciences Division, 
Christine Broniak
Department of Agricultural &amp; Resource Economics, Oregon State University, 
Consumption data for coal, petroleum, and natural gas are multiplied by 
their respective thermal conversion factors, which are in units of heat energy 
per unit of fuel consumed (i.e., per cubic foot, barrel, or ton), to calculate 
the amount of heat energy derived from fuel combustion. The thermal conversion 
factors are given in Appendix A of each issue of Monthly Energy Review, published 
by the Energy Information Administration (EIA) of the U.S. Department of 
Energy (DOE). Results are expressed in terms of heat energy obtained from 
each fuel type. These energy values were obtained from the State Energy Data Report 
(EIA, 2003a), 
(
http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/states/sep_use/total/csv/use_csv.html), and 
served as our basic input. The energy data are also available in hard copy from the 
Energy Information Administration, U.S. Department of Energy, as the State 
Energy Data Report (EIA, 2003a,b).
These energy consumption data were multiplied by their respective carbon 
dioxide emission factors, which are called carbon content coefficients by 
the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA). These factors quantify the 
mass of oxidized carbon per unit of energy released from a fuel. In the U.S.A., 
they are typically expressed in units of teragrams of carbon 
(Tg-C = 10 grams of carbon) per quadrillion 
British thermal units (quadrillion Btu = 10 Btu, 
or "quad"), and are highest for coal and lowest for natural gas. Our results are 
given in teragrams of , 
multiply by 44/12 (= 3.67).
Carbon content coefficients for various fuels are given in Tables 2-16 through 2-20 of 
Annex 2 in EPA (2004), and (for coal) in Appendix E of EIA (2003b). Emissions factors 
we used for coal from 1980 through 1999 are from Appendix E of EIA (2003b). 
Because emissions factors were not available for all years for which we have energy data, 
the 1980 values were used for preceding years, and 1999 values were used for years 2000 
and 2001. Because carbon dioxide emission factors changed very litte, if at all, from 
year-to-year (typically less than 1% of their longer-term average) the use of 1980 values 
for prior years did not appear to have any affect on our results at the national level. 
However, caution is suggested for detailed interpretation of variability of carbon 
emissions from coal in individual states that import much of their coal so that the 
locations of the producing mines may vary widely from year to year. Caution is also 
suggested when using state data with abrupt increases or decreases in carbon emitted 
from one fuel. Usually, these are real changes that can be traced back to the 
installation of a natural gas pipeline or the opening of a large facility in a small 
state. However, in some cases (e.g., the abrupt increase in natural gas use in 
Rhode Island in 1992) the cause of an abrupt change in emissions values is not clear, 
and more detailed investigation is suggested before making conclusions about such 
changes. For assistance, begin by contacting 
The energy data we used are categorized by end use; for coal and natural 
gas, end uses largely include fuel for energy production, with only a small 
or negligible percentage going to non-fuel uses. End uses for petroleum are 
vastly more complicated, and include petrochemicals used in the manufacture 
of plastic products (e.g., bags, toys, prosthetic limbs) and fabrics (e.g., nylon 
and polyester) as well as waxes, asphalt, graphite, lubricants, solvents waxes, etc. 
The carbon in some petroleum products (e.g., lubricants) is largely oxidized while 
virtually none of the carbon is oxidized in others (e.g., asphalt, waxes). The 
energy amount that would be realized from the oxidation of 100% of any petroleum 
product was multiplied by the fraction that is assumed to be actually oxidized, 
and the rest of the carbon was assumed to be sequestered. The sequestered fractions 
used to estimate the amounts of carbon dioxide release during consumption are 
given in Table 2-32 of EPA (2004). This procedure led to higher values of oxidized 
carbon than earlier procedures incorporating the assumption that all carbon in 
these products was sequestered.
The carbon dioxide emission factors for some petroleum products vary from 
year to year due to factors such as changing blends of motor gasoline. Carbon 
coefficients we used for petroleum products from 1990 forward are given by the 
EPA in Table 2-17 and 2-19, in Annex 2 of EPA (2004). Values 
for 1984-1989 are given in Table A1 of EIA (1995); for years prior to 1984, the 
1984 values were used. Because year-to year changes in carbon coefficients for 
petroleum products are less than 1% of their longer-term averages, the use of 
constant (1984) values for prior years did not noticeably affect our results.
Data are available for over 30 different petroleum products, with the exact 
breakdown varying somewhat from year to year. These products have been treated 
individually until the final step of the estimation, at which time 
CO emissions were summed and attributed 
to liquid petroleum products.
Natural gas is almost all methane or other combustible hydrocarbons, with only 
a very small fraction of impurities such as sulfur and heavy metals; its carbon 
coefficient is, therefore, relatively small and practically constant. The 
carbon coefficient for natural gas is given in Table 2-19 in Annex 2 of EPA (2004), as 
a constant of 14.47 Tg-C/quad.
These carbon emissions estimates were ultimately derived from values of fuel 
consumed at full combustion: in billions of cubic feet for natural gas; in 
millions of barrels, for petroleum products, and in thousand of short tons, 
for coal. In reality, a small percentage of carbon is released as soot, ash, 
or long-lived hydrocarbons. We assume that combustion is only 99 per cent 
complete; which is the same factor used by the EPA (EPA 2004, Table 2-16 of 
Annex 2) except that EPA used a factor of 0.995 for natural gas for liquid 
petroleum gas (LPG).
, 
results are presented here in terms of the mass of carbon only (multiply the 
mass of carbon by 44/12 to convert to CO). 
We assume that any carbon emitted to the atmosphere as CO will soon be 
converted to CO
Differences from other (CDIAC) emissions estimates: Marland et al. (2004) have 
presented estimates of annual carbon dioxide emissions (as carbon) from fossil 
fuel consumption for all countries. The annual values presented there for the 
U.S.A. differ slightly from the national sums of the state data presented here 
for 3 primary reasons.
In order to provide comparable estimates for all 
countries, Marland et al. have relied on energy data from the United Nations 
whereas this analysis relies on energy data directly from DOE. United Nations 
data are presumably derived from the same DOE 
data sets but differences in detail occur due to differences in units, categories, 
accounting conventions, and the complexity of handling large amounts of data.
Estimates from the United Nations data are based on "apparent consumption," which 
is defined as production + imports - exports - changes in stocks; whereas the 
U.S. DOE data provide direct estimates of consumption. There are systematic 
differences between these two data sets that are attributable to data sampling 
and collection; the data sets differ by around 2%.
The Marland et al. estimates 
are for CO emissions during fuel combustion 
whereas the estimates here include a contribution from the oxidation of petrochemical 
products that are used for non-fuel purposes, such as lubricants and petroleum coke.
As a consequence of these 3 factors, the national estimates presented here tend to 
be higher than those of Marland et al. even though they do not yet account for carbon 
oxidized during gas flaring or from the calcining of limestone during manufacture of 
cement [when combined, these processes represent about 1 per cent of the total 
anthropogenic carbon emissions from the U.S. (Marland et al., 2004)]. We believe 
the estimates presented here provide a more complete account of total national 
emissions. However, for comparing U.S. emissions with those of other nations, 
we still recommend the use of the U.S. data in Marland et al., 2004, which are 
derived similarly for all nations, and systematic errors applicable to any one 
nation are likely to apply to other nations as well. Neither set of total emissions 
estimates includes carbon from bunker fuels, i.e. (fuels that are loaded in the 
U.S. but used by planes and ships in international commerce). Marland et al. (2004) 
provide carbon esissions estimates for bunker fuels, but they are not included 
in the totals as given.
These estimates of total annual carbon emissions for the USA have been compared 
with estimates derived from monthly data using similar methods. These estimates 
are consistently about 1.5% greater than those derived from the monthly data; the 
reason for this is not presently known.
Total carbon emissions almost doubled from 1960-2001, increasing from 790 Teragrams/year 
(Tg/yr) to 1542 Tg/yr. For the United States as a whole, and for many individual states, 
carbon emissions peaked sometime in the 1970s, declined in the early 1980s, and then 
resumed growth at a rate somewhat less than that before 1970. Per capita emissions 
have shown a much more modest increase since the decline in the early 1980s, and have 
not yet returned to the 1970s levels of around 6 Mg per person per year. This has 
been especially true for states whose energy supply is largely petroleum dependent.
Coal had the most rapid increase of the three fuels, both in total carbon (301 Tg/year 
increase) and in percentage (221% of its 1960 value by 2001). Per capita coal emissions 
grew from 1.38 Megagrams/person (Mg/person) to 1.93 Mg/person, or to 140% of their 1960 
value, while per capita emissions of oil increased to only 115%, and per capita emissions 
of natural gas increased to only 116%, of their 1960 value. The states differ widely 
in per capita emissions for year 2001; California emitted about 3 Mg/capita while Wyoming 
emitted more than 10 times that (about 34 Mg/person).
Carbon emissions from coal combustion have increased sharply in states that export 
electricity produced from local deposits of low-sulfur coal, so that states with low 
populations and large repositories of low-sulfur coal (e.g., North Dakota and Wyoming) 
are emitting about 10 times the carbon per capita (from coal, oil, and gas, combined) 
of more heavily populated states, such as California, that are importing electricity 
generated from coal combustion. 
EIA (Energy Information Administration, U.S. Department of Energy) 1995. Emissions of 
Greenhouse gases in the United States: 1987-1994. DOE/EIA-0573(94), Office of Integrated 
Analysis and Forecasting, Washington DC.
EIA (Energy Information Administration, U.S. Department of Energy) 2003a. State Energy 
Data Report. 
http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/states/sep_use/total/csv/use_csv.html
EIA (Energy Information Administration, U.S. Department of Energy) 2003b. State Energy 
Data 2000: Consumption, Technical Notes, 
http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/states/_use_multistate.html
EPA (U.S. Environmental Protection Agency) 2004. Inventory of Greenhouse Gas Emissions and 
Sinks: 1990-2002, EPA 430-R-04-003, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Washington D.C., 
308 pp. plus annexes, available electronically from:
Marland, G., T.A. Boden, and R.J. Andres. 2004. Global, Regional, and National Fossil-Fuel 
CO Emissions. In Trends: A Compendium of Data on Global 
Change. Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, 
U.S. Department of Energy, Oak Ridge, TN, U.S.A., available electronically 
from: 
CITE AS: Blasing, T.J., C.T. Broniak, and G. Marland, 2004. Estimates of Annual Fossil-Fuel CO Emitted for Each State in the U.S.A. and the District of Columbia for Each Year from 1960 through 2001. Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, U.S. Department of Energy, Oak Ridge, TN, U.S.A. doi 10.3334/CDIAC/00003
&#239;&#187;&#191;
 &#160;&amp;middot;&#160;]]></Descriptive_file>
      <Data_file></Data_file>
      <Data_IO_file></Data_IO_file>
      <Initial_date_of_data_publication><![CDATA[20040901]]></Initial_date_of_data_publication>
      <Most_recent_date_of_data_publication><![CDATA[20040901]]></Most_recent_date_of_data_publication>
      <Data_file_location><![CDATA[http://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/trends/emis_mon/stateemis/emis_state.html]]></Data_file_location>
      <Total_size_of_all_files></Total_size_of_all_files>
      <Distribution></Distribution>
      <CDIAC_contact><![CDATA[T. J. Blasing; email: blasingtj@ornl.gov]]></CDIAC_contact>
      <Notes><![CDATA[These estimates of total annual carbon emissions for the USA have been compared with estimates derived from monthly data using similar methods. These estimates are consistently about 1.5% greater than those derived from the monthly data; the reason for this is not presently known.]]></Notes>
    </CDIAC>
  </mercury>
</metadata>
